[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Spectroscopy deals with interaction of electromagnetic radiation with matter. What is the speed of this radiation in vacuum in m/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 x 108",
            "b) 5 x 108",
            "c) 7 x 108",
            "d) 3 x 108"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Speed of light is also the speed of all electromagnetic radiations. Speed of light is 3 x 108m/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Which type of Quantum Transition takes place in Ultra Violet and Visible spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotation of molecules",
            "b) Nuclear",
            "c) Bonding electrons",
            "d) Spin of nuclei in a magnetic field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In UV and Visible Spectroscopy, type of Quantum Transmission is Bonding electrons. The rest of the options are Quantum Transmission type of other spectroscopic methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property or parameter of electromagnetic radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wavelength",
            "b) Voltage",
            "c) Wave number",
            "d) Amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wavelength, Amplitude and Wavenumber are parameters of electromagnetic radiation. Other parameters are Velocity and Frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gamma ray",
            "b) X ray",
            "c) Nuclear magnetic resonance",
            "d) Sound"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sound is not a type of electromagnetic radiation. Hence, it is not a type of Spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which of the following is false about the wavelengths of electromagnetic radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiation with short wavelengths have high energies",
            "b) Energy does not depend on wavelength",
            "c) Radiation with long wavelengths have low energies",
            "d) Energy depends on wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electromagnetic radiation can travel through a vacuum. It does not need a medium for propagation."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the wavelength of microwave radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 780nm",
            "b) 0.78 – 30µm",
            "c) 0.6 – 10 m",
            "d) 0.75 – 3.75 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The radiations with short wavelength have high energies and vice versa. Thus, energy depends on wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "How is the wave number of electromagnetic radiation related to wavelength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the reciprocal of wavelength",
            "b) It is directly proportional to wavelength",
            "c) It is not related to wavelength",
            "d) It is equal to wavelength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The wavelength of Microwave radiation is 0.75 – 3.75 mm. The rest of the options are the wavelength of other Electro Magnetic radiations."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the wavenumber of UV and Visible radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 x 106 to 1.3 x 104 m-1",
            "b) 1 x 106 to 1.3 x 104 m",
            "c) 13 – 27 m-1",
            "d) 1 x 106 to 1.3 x 104 m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wave number is the number of waves spread in a length of one centimeter. It is the reciprocal of wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Beer Lambert’s law gives the relation between which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflected radiation and concentration",
            "b) Scattered radiation and concentration",
            "c) Energy absorption and concentration",
            "d) Energy absorption and reflected radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Beer Lambert’s law gives the relation between Energy absorption and Concentration. It was proposed by Beer and Lambert."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "In which of the following ways, absorption is related to transmittance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absorption is the logarithm of transmittance",
            "b) Absorption is the reciprocal of transmittance",
            "c) Absorption is the negative logarithm of transmittance",
            "d) Absorption is a multiple of transmittance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transmittance is the ratio of the radiant power transmitted by a sample to the radiant power incident on the sample. Absorption is the negative logarithm of transmittance."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a limitation of Beer Lambert’s law, which gives the relation between absorption, thickness and concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration must be lower",
            "b) Radiation must have higher bandwidth",
            "c) Radiation source must be monochromatic",
            "d) Does not consider factors other than thickness and concentration that affect absorbance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The law is derived assuming that the radiation is monochromatic. So, if bandwidth increases it will create deviation."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Beer’s law states that the intensity of light decreases with respect to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration",
            "b) Distance",
            "c) Composition",
            "d) Volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Beer’s law states that the intensity of light decreases with the concentration of the medium. It was stated by Beer."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Lambert’s law states that the intensity of light decreases with respect to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration",
            "b) Distance",
            "c) Composition",
            "d) Volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lambert’s law states that the intensity of light decreases with respect to the concentration of the medium. It was stated by Lambert."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The representation of Beer Lambert’s law is given as A = abc. If ‘b’ represents distance, ‘c’ represents concentration and ‘A’ represents absorption, what does ‘a’ represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intensity",
            "b) Transmittance",
            "c) Absorptivity",
            "d) Admittance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ‘a’ represents the absorption constant. It is also known as absorptivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Absorption spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It involves transmission",
            "b) Scattering is kept minimum",
            "c) Reflection is kept maximum",
            "d) Intensity of radiation leaving the substance is an indication of a concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Absorption spectroscopy, reflection must also be kept minimum along with scattering. Amount of absorption depends on the number of molecules in the material."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Transmittance is given as T = P/Po. If Po is the power incident on the sample, what does P represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiant power transmitted by the sample",
            "b) Radiant power absorbed by the sample",
            "c) Sum of powers absorbed and scattered",
            "d) Sum of powers transmitted and reflected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P represents radiant power transmitted by the sample. Transmittance is the ratio of radiant power transmitted by the sample to the radiant power that is incident on it."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "What is the unit of absorbance which can be derived from Beer Lambert’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L mol-1 cm-1",
            "b) L gm-1 cm-1",
            "c) Cm",
            "d) No unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Absorbance has no unit. The units of absorptivity, distance and concentration cancel each other. Hence, absorption has no unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is the unit of molar absorptivity or absorptivity which is used to determine absorbance A in Beer Lambert’s formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L mol-1 cm-1",
            "b) L gm-1 cm-1",
            "c) Cm",
            "d) No unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unit of absorptivity is L mol-1 cm-1. If concentration is represented as gm per litre it becomes L gm-1 cm-1."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors does not require a battery and is also known as barrier layer cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photomultiplier tube",
            "b) Photovoltaic cell",
            "c) Photoemissive tubes",
            "d) Photo reflector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To measure the amount of radiation absorbed and transmitted detector is very important. It detects the amount of radiation which is then inferred using read out device."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors is used to detect light intensities which are very weak?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photomultiplier tube",
            "b) Photovoltaic cell",
            "c) Photoemissive tubes",
            "d) Photo reflector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Photovoltaic cell does not require a battery for operation. Its working is entirely different from Photomultiplier tube or Photoemissive tubes."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "How is Tungsten Halogen lamp differs from normal Tungsten filament lamp used in absorption spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has a tungsten filament and is filled with inert gas",
            "b) Iodine is added to normal filling gas",
            "c) Iodine is coated on tungsten filament",
            "d) Iodine is added to inert gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PMT is used for detection of light intensities which are weak. As the name suggests, Photomultiplier tube multiplies the incident electrons using dynodes causing an avalanche of electrons."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Instead of glass filters, why gelatin filters could not be used for a long period while both are Absorption filters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gelatin tends to evaporate and hence they deteriorate",
            "b) Gelatin is affected by humidity in the environment",
            "c) They deteriorate due to absorption of heat leading to changes in gelatin",
            "d) Gelation is affected by temperature in the environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Tungsten filament lamp tungsten filament is enclosed in a bulb of glass filled with inert gas or vacuum. In Tungsten Halogen lamp iodine is added to the normal filling glass."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "How does continuous wedge filter differ from normal interference filter used in absorption spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It permits continuous selection of different wavelength",
            "b) It allows a narrow band of wavelengths to pass",
            "c) It has two semi-transparent layers of silver",
            "d) Space layer is made of a substance having low refractive index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: With the absorption of heat they deteriorate due to changes in gelatin. Bleaching of dye occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which of the following could be used as the layer of dielectric in interference filters used in Absorption Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graphite",
            "b) MgF2",
            "c) Fe",
            "d) AgNO3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It allows continuous selection of wavelength by using a spacer film of graded thickness. Rest of the options are properties of normal interference filters."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "How can stability of radiation be achieved in incandescent or discharge source used in Absorption Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using filters",
            "b) Using monochromators",
            "c) Using slits",
            "d) By controlling the source voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MgF2 is used as layer of dielectric in interference filters. Other material that can be used is ZnS."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "To tolerate high operating temperatures, which of the following has to be done in incandescent or tungsten filament lamps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alloys must be used",
            "b) Nitrogen be used instead of inert gas",
            "c) Envelope is fabricated with quartz",
            "d) Envelope is fabricated with copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The intensity of radiation in the incandescent source is proportional to the lamp source voltage. Therefore, by controlling the source voltage stability can be achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a reason for laser not being generally used as a source of radiation for UV, Visible Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High cost",
            "b) Limited range of wavelength",
            "c) Less intensity",
            "d) Complex to work with"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The envelope is fabricated with quartz to allow high operating temperatures. Tungsten filament and inert gas are generally used and are not modified."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is false about single beam absorption instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten bulb is used as a source",
            "b) Beam splitter is used to get parallel beam",
            "c) Test tube is used as sample holder",
            "d) Photovoltaic cell as detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Single beam instruments make use of one beam. Therefore, beam splitters are not required in single beam instruments."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is false about double beam absorption instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is similar to single beam instruments except two beams are present",
            "b) Tungsten bulb is used as a source",
            "c) Reference beam must have a higher intensity than sample beam",
            "d) Both the beams after they pass through respective samples are compared"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reference beam cannot have a higher intensity than sample beam. The beam is split into two beams of equal intensity."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of colorimeter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paints",
            "b) Inks",
            "c) Cosmetics",
            "d) Composition detection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Colorimeter is not used to determine composition. Its application is paints, dyes, inks, cosmetics and plastics."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "In photometers, the readings of the specimen are initially obtained in the form of which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmittance",
            "b) Absorption",
            "c) Wavelengths",
            "d) Volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In photometers, the reading is initially obtained in the form of transmittance as some radiation is absorbed by the sample and the rest of the beam is transmitted. This transmitted beam is measured by the detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the purpose of balance indicator in double beam photometer or colorimeter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selects a particular wavelength",
            "b) Splits the wavelength selected into two equal beams",
            "c) Detects and indicates the amount of light falling on it",
            "d) Indicates the difference between the output of two photometers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Colorimeters are used in applications where great accuracy is not required. They are also known as photometers."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the purpose of the beam splitter in double beam photometer or colorimeter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Splits beam into two equal intensity beams",
            "b) Splits beam in such a way that sample beam has higher intensity",
            "c) Splits beam in such a way that a reference beam has higher intensity",
            "d) Merge two equal intensity beams into single beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In single beam spectrophotometer, the beam passed through the sample which is held in the sample holder. The transmitted beam is measured by the detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a source used in spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LASER",
            "b) Tube light",
            "c) Sodium vapour lamp",
            "d) Tungsten lamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Colorimetry is the science of colour measurement. It is used to determine the concentrations of solutions."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a source used in Mid Infrared Spectrophotometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nernst glower",
            "b) High pressure mercury arc lamp",
            "c) Globar",
            "d) Nichrome wire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High pressure mercury arc lamp is used as the source for Far IR Spectrophotometer. Rest of the options are used as a source in Mid Infrared Spectrophotometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the wave number of near infrared spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4000 – 200 cm-1",
            "b) 200 – 10 cm-1",
            "c) 12500 – 4000 cm-1",
            "d) 50 – 1000 cm-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wave number of near infrared spectrometer ranges between 12500 – 4000. Wavenumber is the reciprocal of wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following options are correct in terms of wavelength for the different types of IR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near IR: 0.8 – 2.5 mm",
            "b) Mid IR: 0.8 – 2.5 mm",
            "c) Far IR: 2.5 – 50 mm",
            "d) Mid IR: 50 – 100 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wavelength of near IR is 0.8 – 2.5 mm and for mid IR it is 2.5 – 50 mm. The wavelength of far IR is 50 – 1000 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a composition of Nernst glower or Nernst filament?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxides of Zirconium",
            "b) Oxides of Barium",
            "c) Oxides of Yitrium",
            "d) Oxides of Thorium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxides of Barium is not present in Nernst glower. They are constructed by fusing oxides of Zirconium, yitrium and thorium."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "What is the composition of Globar rod which is used as a source in Mid IR spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon carbide",
            "b) Silver chloride",
            "c) Silicon dioxide",
            "d) Silver carbide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Globar is a silicon carbide rod. It is 5mm in diameter and 50mm long."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Bolometer, a type of detector, is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resistance temperature detector (RTD)",
            "b) Thermistor",
            "c) Thermocouple",
            "d) Golay cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bolometers are also known as thermistors. It is a type of resistance thermometer constructed of metals such as platinum or nickel."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a technique for preparing solid samples in IR spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solids run in solution",
            "b) Mull technique",
            "c) Solid films",
            "d) Thin films"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Four techniques are generally used to prepare solid samples. They are: Solids run in solution, Mull technique, Solid films and pressed pellet techniques."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used as pyroelectric material used in pyroelectric transducers in Infrared spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triglycine Sulphate",
            "b) Deutrated Triglycine Sulphate",
            "c) Some Polymers",
            "d) Tetraglycine sulphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pyroelectric materials are deutrated triglycine sulphate, triglycine sulphate and some polymers. They give rise to potential when subjected to a heating or cooling effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the principle of Golay cell which is used as a detector in IR spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expansion of gas upon heating",
            "b) Increase in resistance due to an increase in temperature and vice versa",
            "c) Temperature difference gives rise to a potential difference in the material",
            "d) Decrease in resistance due to an increase in temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is also known as pneumatic detector. The gases expand on heating and this in turn leads to the movement of a diaphragm just like in pneumatic sensors."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "In a solid sample treatment technique, the finely ground solid sample is mixed with mineral oil to make a thick paste which is then spread between IR transmitting windows. What is the name of this solid sample treatment technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressed pellet",
            "b) Mull technique",
            "c) Solid films",
            "d) Solids run in solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mentioned technique is Mull technique. This method is used for qualitative analysis but not quantitative analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Fourier Transform Infrared (FTIR) spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is of non-dispersive type",
            "b) It is useful where repetitive analysis is required",
            "c) Size has been reduced over the years",
            "d) Size has increased over the years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FTIR is of non-dispersive type of instruments and is used for repetitive analysis. Initially, it was bulky and the cost was high and hence, it was limited to a special application. Now, the size has been reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "In the most widely used beam splitter, a thin film of ________ is sandwiched between two plates of low refractive index solid. Fill the blank with a suitable option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mylar",
            "b) Silicon carbide",
            "c) Ferrous oxide",
            "d) Silver chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, mylar is the thin film used in beam splitters. Beam splitter has to pass 50% of the radiation and reflect 50% of the radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of the drive mechanism in Fourier Transform Infrared Spectrophotometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Movement of mirror to obtain a satisfactory interferogram",
            "b) Acquire a good interferogram pattern",
            "c) Allow 50% of the beam to pass",
            "d) Keep the speed of the moving mirror constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drive mechanism does the functions specified in the other options. It the function of the beam splitter to allow 50% of the beam to pass through."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Only pyroelectric transducer or pyroelectric crystals are used as detectors in Fourier Transform Infrared Spectrophotometer (FTIR). What is the main reason for other types of thermal detectors are not being used in FTIR spectrophotometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less accuracy",
            "b) Slower response",
            "c) Less precision",
            "d) Less sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Other thermal detectors are not employed due to slower response of the detectors. Pyroelectric transducers or pyroelectric crystals are chosen for their high speed, accuracy, precision, sensitivity and resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the advantage of Fourier Transform Spectrometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal to noise ratio is high",
            "b) Information could be obtained on all frequencies",
            "c) Retrieval of data is possible",
            "d) Easy to maintain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The instrument is not easy to maintain and it is a disadvantage. The other disadvantage is that the cost is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which of the following has to be computed to determine transmittance and absorbance at various frequencies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio of signal and noise",
            "b) Ratio of sample and reference spectra",
            "c) Sample spectra",
            "d) Reference spectra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio of sample and reference spectra needs to be computed to determine transmittance and absorbance. First, reference interferogram is obtained and then the sample is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the reference that is generally used in FTIR interferometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air",
            "b) NaCl solution",
            "c) Alcohol",
            "d) Base solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Computer does not accept analog signals directly. An A/D converter is required to feed the signals to the computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "In Michelson’s interferometer, the frequency of the detector output can be determined by translating the _________ of movable mirror and the ___________ of monochromatic radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity, wavelength",
            "b) Thickness, intensity",
            "c) Length, velocity",
            "d) Angle, intensity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Air is generally used as the reference. It is scanned for about 20 to 30 times and the results are stored in a computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "In Michelson’s interferometer, the __________ of the detector output will depend upon the intensity of incoming radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity",
            "b) Frequency",
            "c) Amplitude",
            "d) Phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the reflected and transmitted beams are in phase at the beam splitter then maximum intensity will reach the detector. If they are out of phase, then minimum intensity will reach the detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Why is the computer necessary in Fourier Transform Spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To display the detector output",
            "b) To process the detector output",
            "c) To determine the amplitude",
            "d) To determine the frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Computer does not accept analog signals directly. An A/D converter is required to feed the signals to the computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the principle of Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiation is absorbed by non-excited atoms in vapour state and are excited to higher states",
            "b) Medium absorbs radiation and transmitted radiation is measured",
            "c) Colour is measured",
            "d) Colour is simply observed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Atoms in gaseous state absorb the radiation and are excited to a higher state. Since the higher state is unstable the atom returns the ground state with the emission of radiation which is measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "In Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy, which of the following is the generally used radiation source?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten lamp",
            "b) Xenon mercury arc lamp",
            "c) Hydrogen or deuterium discharge lamp",
            "d) Hollow cathode lamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hollow cathode lamp is the source used in Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy. It emits stable and intense radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "In Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy, with what material is the cathode in Hollow cathode lamp constructed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten",
            "b) Quartz",
            "c) Element to be investigated",
            "d) Aluminium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cathode in Hollow cathode lamp is constructed of the element to be investigated. The anode is made of tungsten."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "How can the intensity of radiation be increased in Hollow cathode lamp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition of non-conductive protective shield of mica",
            "b) Addition of nitrogen to neon or argon in the lamp",
            "c) Increasing the pressure of the filling gas",
            "d) Changing the metal of the anode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intensity of radiation is increased in Hollow cathode lamp by the addition of a non-conductive protective shield of mica. The protective shield can be made of glass too."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the function of the chopper in Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To split the beam into two",
            "b) To break the steady light into a pulsating light",
            "c) To filter unwanted components",
            "d) To reduce the sample into atomic state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The function of the chopper in Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy is to break the steady light into pulsating light. It is a rotating wheel placed between the flame and the source."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the function of the Flame or Emission system in Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To split the beam into two",
            "b) To break the steady light into pulsating light",
            "c) To filter unwanted components",
            "d) To reduce the sample into atomic state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The function of Flame or Emission system in Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy is to reduce the sample into atomic state. In Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy, the production of atomic vapour by flame is the most important phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of the emission system in Flame photometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burner",
            "b) Atomiser",
            "c) Fuel gases and their regulation",
            "d) Chopper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy, sample is sprayed into the flame. Hence, it is called Absorption Flame Photometry."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the function of the atomiser in the emission system of Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To split the beam into two",
            "b) To break the steady light into pulsating light",
            "c) To break large mass of liquid into small drops",
            "d) To reduce the sample into atomic state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chopper is not a component of the emission system in Flame photometer. The parts of flame photometer are burner, atomiser, fuel gases and their regulation and flame."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a fuel used in flame photometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetylene",
            "b) Propane",
            "c) Hydrogen",
            "d) Camphor oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The function of atomiser in the emission system of Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy is to break large mass of liquid into small drops. It also introduces liquid sample into the flame at a stable rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the requirement of a good flame in flame photometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid sample must be evaporated to form solid residue",
            "b) Solid residue must decompose to form atoms",
            "c) Atoms must be produced such that they have the ability to get excited to higher states",
            "d) Atoms must be produced such that they are in stable state"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The commonly used fuel gases in flame photometry are acetylene, propane and hydrogen. Oxygen supply is given to the fuel gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Which of the following options explains the process of ‘sputtering’ that occurs in Hollow Cathode Lamp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Positive ions collide with cathode surface and metal atoms from cathode are ejected",
            "b) Negative ions collide with cathode surface and metal atoms from anode are ejected",
            "c) Positive ions collide with negative ions and metal atoms from anode are ejected",
            "d) Positive ions collide with negative ions and photons are ejected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Atoms must be produced such that they have the ability to get excited to higher states. These atoms in higher states return to ground state with the emission of photons."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "At what pressure should the gases in the sealed tube be maintained in the Hollow cathode lamp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5 torr",
            "b) 20 to 30 torr",
            "c) 40 to 50 torr",
            "d) 50 to 55 torr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy is used for the analysis of metals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the principle of Flame emission photometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiation is absorbed by non-excited atoms in vapour state and are excited to higher states",
            "b) Medium absorbs radiation and transmitted radiation is measured",
            "c) Colour and wavelength of the flame is measured",
            "d) Only wavelength of the flame is measured"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The function of pressure regulators is to have a steady flame which is free from flickers. Pressure gauges indicate pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "In Flame emission photometers, the measurement of _____________ is used for qualitative analysis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour",
            "b) Intensity",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Samples will enter the burner irrespective of their droplet size. Hence, it has the name Total consumption burner."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "In Flame emission photometers, the measurement of _____________ is used for quantitative analysis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colour",
            "b) Intensity",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Flame emission photometers, colour and intensity of the flame are measured. The intensity of light emitted when sample is introduced into the flame is also measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Laminar flow burner used in Flame photometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noiseless",
            "b) Stable flame for analysis",
            "c) Efficient atomization of sample",
            "d) Sample containing two or more solvents can be burned efficiently"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The colour and the wavelength of the flame are used for qualitative analysis. It is used to determine the element which is present in the sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Laminar flow burner used in Flame photometers is also known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbulent burner",
            "b) Premix burner",
            "c) Total consumption burner",
            "d) Nozzle mix burner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intensity of the flame is used for quantitative analysis. It is used to determine the amount of elements present in the sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the advantage of prism monochromators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersion is non-overlapping",
            "b) Dispersion occurs in non-linear manner",
            "c) Dispersion is overlapping",
            "d) Dispersion occurs in a linear manner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sample containing two or more solvents cannot be burned efficiently in Laminar flow burner. One more advantage of laminar flow burner is that it allows steady movement of gas flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the advantage of grating monochromators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dispersion is non-overlapping",
            "b) Dispersion occurs in non-linear manner",
            "c) Dispersion is overlapping",
            "d) Dispersion occurs in a linear manner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Laminar flow burner used in Flame photometers is also known as Premix burner. Sample, fuel and oxidant are mixed thoroughly before reaching the burner."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a detector used in Flame emission photometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photronic cell",
            "b) Photovoltaic cell",
            "c) Photoemissive tube",
            "d) Chromatogram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The advantage of a prism is that dispersion that occurs is non-overlapping. The disadvantage is that it occurs in a non-linear manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of Flame emission photometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analysis of biological fluids",
            "b) Determination of sodium, potassium in soil",
            "c) Determination of metals such as Mn, Cu",
            "d) Analysis of complex mixtures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The advantage of the grating is that dispersion that occurs is linear. The disadvantage is that the dispersion is overlapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of a photovoltaic cell which is used as a detector in Flame emission photometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Portable",
            "b) No external supply",
            "c) Robust in construction",
            "d) Does not show fatigue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Detectors used in Flame emission photometers are Photovoltaic cell and photo emissive tubes. Photovoltaic cell is also known as photronic cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Chromatography is a physical method that is used to separate and analyse __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple mixtures",
            "b) Complex mixtures",
            "c) Viscous mixtures",
            "d) Metals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chromatography is a physical method that is used to separate complex mixtures. The mixture of different components is flushed through the system at different rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "In which type of chromatography, the stationary phase held in a narrow tube and the mobile phase is forced through it under pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Column chromatography",
            "b) Planar chromatography",
            "c) Liquid chromatography",
            "d) Gas chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Column chromatography, the stationary phase held in a narrow tube and the mobile phase is forced through it under pressure. It is carried out in a long glass column having a stop-cock near the bottom."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "In chromatography, the stationary phase can be ___________ supported on a solid.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid or liquid",
            "b) Liquid or gas",
            "c) Solid only",
            "d) Liquid only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In chromatography, there are two phases namely, stationary phase and mobile phase. The stationary phase can be solid or a liquid supported on a solid."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "In chromatography, which of the following can the mobile phase be made of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid or liquid",
            "b) Liquid or gas",
            "c) Gas only",
            "d) Liquid only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In chromatography, the mobile phase can be composed of liquid or gas. It cannot be a solid material."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be used as an adsorbent in Column adsorption chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnesium oxide",
            "b) Silica gel",
            "c) Activated alumina",
            "d) Potassium permanganate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The given options are all examples of adsorbents in Column adsorption except potassium permanganate. Some other adsorbents are starch and chromatographic purified siliceous earth."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of chromatography involves the separation of substances in a mixture over a 0.2mm thick layer of an adsorbent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas liquid",
            "b) Column",
            "c) Thin layer",
            "d) Paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thin layer chromatography involves the separation of substances of a mixture over a 0.2mm thick layer (thin layer) of an adsorbent. The adsorbent can be silica gel or alumina."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "In Column chromatography, the stationary phase is made of _________ and the mobile phase is made of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid, liquid",
            "b) Liquid, liquid",
            "c) Liquid, gas",
            "d) Solid, gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chromatography can be used to purify volatile substances if the carrier fluid, operating conditions and right adsorbent material are employed."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "In Thin layer chromatography, the stationary phase is made of _________ and the mobile phase is made of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid, liquid",
            "b) Liquid, liquid",
            "c) Liquid, gas",
            "d) Solid, gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Column chromatography, the stationary phase is made of solid and the mobile phase is made of liquid. It is carried out in a long glass column which has a stop-cock near the bottom."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "In which of the following type of paper, chromatography does the mobile phase move horizontally over a circular sheet of paper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ascending paper chromatography",
            "b) Descending paper chromatography",
            "c) Radial paper chromatography",
            "d) Ascending – descending chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chromatography can be used to separate delicate products. This is because chromatography is not performed under severe conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Liquid chromatography can be performed in which of the following ways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only in columns",
            "b) Only on plane surfaces",
            "c) Either in columns or on plane surfaces",
            "d) Neither in columns nor on plane surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Thin layer chromatography, the stationary phase is made of solid and the mobile phase is made of liquid."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Gas chromatography can be performed in which of the following ways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only in columns",
            "b) Only on plane surfaces",
            "c) Either in columns or on plane surfaces",
            "d) Neither in columns nor on plane surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Radial paper chromatography, the mobile phase moves horizontally over a circular sheet of paper. Separation takes place based on partition."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "In Gas-liquid phase chromatography, the stationary phase is composed of _________ and the mobile phase is made of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid, liquid",
            "b) Liquid, liquid",
            "c) Liquid, gas",
            "d) Solid, gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Liquid chromatography can be performed either in columns or on plane surfaces. It could be liquid-solid chromatography or liquid-liquid chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of chromatography involves the process, where the mobile phase moves through the stationary phase by the influence of gravity or capillary action?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Column Chromatography",
            "b) High Pressure Liquid Chromatography",
            "c) Gas Chromatography",
            "d) Planar Chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gas chromatography can be performed only in columns. It could be gas-solid chromatography or gas-liquid chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of the following steps takes place after injection of feed in Column chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Detection of components",
            "b) Separation in the column",
            "c) Elution from the column",
            "d) Collection of eluted component"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The operation that occurs after the injection of feed is a separation in the column. After that, elution from the column and detection of components takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "What happens during the ‘elution from the column’ phase in chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Components with greatest affinity elute first",
            "b) Components with least affinity elute first",
            "c) Components elute in a random manner",
            "d) Components elute according to their concentration in the mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Different components will adsorb to the stationary phase in varying degrees. Components with a strong attraction to the support move more slowly than components with weak attraction."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "In chromatogram, the position of peaks on the time axis can be used to determine which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Components of the sample",
            "b) Amount of component in the sample",
            "c) Column efficiency",
            "d) Column resolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the elution phase, different components elute at different times. Components with least affinity elute first."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "In chromatogram, the area under the peak can be used to determine which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Components of the sample",
            "b) Amount of component in the sample",
            "c) Column efficiency",
            "d) Column resolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chromatogram is a detector that responds to concentration solute and is placed at the end of the column. The position of peaks on the time axis can be used to determine components of the sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Using Chromatogram as detector in Chromatography, a graph is obtained between ____________ and time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantity",
            "b) Density",
            "c) Concentration",
            "d) Specific gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chromatogram is a detector that responds to concentration solute and is placed at the end of the column. The area under the peak can be used to determine the amount of component in the sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "In older analytical methods, which of the following methods were used to allow movement of the mobile phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pumps",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Gravity",
            "d) Blowing air into the column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stationary phase could be a viscous liquid coated over a surface of solid particles. The solid particles can also be the stationary phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "How is the molar concentration of solute in stationary phase related to molar concentration of solute in the mobile phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In chromatography, molar concentration of solute in stationary phase is directly proportional to molar concentration of solute in mobile phase.\nCs α Cm\nCs = k Cm\n‘k’ is the distribution constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "If the value of the distribution constant ‘k’ is one, then what could be inferred about the distribution of solute?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its distribution in stationary phase is greater",
            "b) Its distribution in mobile phase is greater",
            "c) It is equally distributed in stationary and mobile phase",
            "d) It is distributed in a random manner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:\nCs α Cm\nCs = k Cm\nIf k=1, it denotes that the solute is equally distributed in the mobile and stationary phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "The time taken by the analyte after sample injection to reach the detector is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dead time",
            "b) Solute migration rate",
            "c) Adjusted retention time",
            "d) Retention time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The time taken by the analyte after sample injection to reach the detector is called retention time. The retention of a solute in the system can be used to identify the solute."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "The time required for a molecule of the mobile phase to pass through the column is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dead time",
            "b) Solute migration rate",
            "c) Adjusted retention time",
            "d) Retention time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time required for a molecule of the mobile phase to pass through the column is called dead time. The effectiveness of the system depends on dead time."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Adjusted retention time is the remaining retention time after subtracting __________ from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solute migration rate and retention time",
            "b) Retention time and solute migration rate",
            "c) Dead time and retention time",
            "d) Retention time and dead time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adjusted retention time is the remaining retention time after subtracting dead time from retention time. It affects the effectiveness of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the volume of mobile phase required to make a solute band move from the point of injection through the column to the detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dead volume",
            "b) Retention volume",
            "c) Void volume",
            "d) Adjusted retention volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Retention volume is the volume of mobile phase required to make a solute band move from the point of injection through the column to the detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Adjusted retention volume is the remaining retention volume after subtracting ___________ from _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solute migration rate and retention volume",
            "b) Retention volume and solute migration rate",
            "c) Dead volume and retention volume",
            "d) Retention volume and dead volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adjusted retention volume is the remaining retention volume after subtracting dead volume from retention volume.\nVadjusted retention = Vretention – Vdead"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Which of the following is defined as the ratio of moles of solute in stationary phase to the moles of solute in the mobile phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distribution constant",
            "b) Volumetric phase ratio",
            "c) Retention factor",
            "d) Total porosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Retention factor is defined as the ratio of moles of solute in stationary phase to the moles of solute in the mobile phase. It is used for determining the migration rates of solutes in the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ratio of the interstitial volume of packing to the volume of its total mass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distribution constant",
            "b) Volumetric phase ratio",
            "c) Retention factor",
            "d) Total porosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Total porosity is the ratio of the interstitial volume of packing to the volume of its total mass. In a capillary column, total porosity is 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ratio of the length of column packing to dead time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average linear rate of solute migration",
            "b) Average linear rate of mobile migration",
            "c) Relative migration rate",
            "d) Selectivity factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Average linear rate of mobile migration is the ratio of the length of column packing to dead time. It influences the effectiveness of the column in separating solutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ratio of a length of column packing to retention time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average linear rate of solute migration",
            "b) Average linear rate of mobile migration",
            "c) Relative migration rate",
            "d) Selectivity factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Average linear rate of solute migration is the ratio of a length of column packing to retention time. It influences the effectiveness of the column in separating solutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Retention volume can be obtained by finding the product of which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dead time and total porosity",
            "b) Retention time and volumetric flow rate",
            "c) Adjusted retention time and volumetric flow rate",
            "d) Retention time and total porosity."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Retention distance is the distance between point of injection and maximum peak in the recorder. The chart is drawn between time and concentration of the solute."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "What must be the value of the selectivity factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to 1",
            "b) Less than 1",
            "c) Greater than 1",
            "d) Greater than 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Retention volume can be obtained by finding the product of retention time and volumetric flow rate.\nFlow rate = Cross section of empty column × Average linear velocity × Total porosity"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the distance that the solute moves while undergoing one partition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retention distance",
            "b) Distribution constant",
            "c) Plate height",
            "d) Column packing length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plate height is the distance that the solute moves while undergoing one partition. It is expressed in length."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions will cause the efficiency of the column to increase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plate number becomes greater, plate height becomes smaller",
            "b) Plate number becomes smaller, plate height becomes smaller",
            "c) Plate number becomes greater, plate height becomes larger",
            "d) Plate number becomes greater, plate height becomes larger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The efficiency of the column increases when the plate number becomes greater and the plate height becomes smaller. Column efficiency greatly depends on plate height and plate number."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the expression for Eddy diffusion in the column, if ‘γ’ represents obstruction factor, ‘dp’ represents particle diameter, ‘DM’ represents Solute diffusion co-efficient and ‘λ’ represents function for packing uniformity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) λ dM",
            "b) 2 γ DM",
            "c) DM γ",
            "d) λ/dM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eddy diffusion is given as, A = λ dp. It is also called multipath term."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the expression for longitudinal diffusion in the column, if ‘γ’ represents obstruction factor, ‘dM’ represents particle diameter, ‘DM’ represents Solute diffusion co-efficient and ‘λ’ represents function for packing uniformity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) λ dM",
            "b) 2 γ DM",
            "c) DM γ",
            "d) λ/dM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Longitudinal diffusion is given as, B = 2 γ DM.It is also called axial diffusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "In gas-liquid chromatography, when films are used in the interior of the capillary column, then what is the value of Eddy diffusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than 1",
            "b) Less than 1",
            "c) Zero",
            "d) Less than zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In gas-liquid chromatography, when films are used in the interior of the capillary column the value of Eddy diffusion (A) is zero. To minimize A, diameter of packing should be small and uniform."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "For an unpacked coated capillary column, the obstruction factor takes which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 0.6",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 1.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For an unpacked coated capillary column, the value of the obstruction factor is 1. For a packed column, the value is 0.6."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Base line resolution is achieved when degree of resolution/separation is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Base line resolution is achieved when degree of resolution/separation is 1.5. The baseline bandwidths of adjacent bands are almost constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following equations give the expression for plate number, N when ‘tR’ is the adjusted retention time and ‘Wb’ is the width at the base of the peak which is equal to 4 standard deviations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 tR2/Wb",
            "b) 4 tR2/Wb",
            "c) (4tR/Wb)2",
            "d) 4 (tR/Wb)2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The expression for plate number, N is given as N = (4tR/Wb)2. It is a dimensionless quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "For the separation of which of the following substances, Gas-solid chromatography is being used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermally stable organic components",
            "b) Volatile organic components",
            "c) Thermally stable inorganic components",
            "d) Low molecular weight gaseous species"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gas-solid chromatography is used for the separation of low molecular weight gaseous species. Its application is limited because of semi-permanent retention of the analyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of carrier gas used in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It must be chemically inert",
            "b) It should be suitable for the detector employed",
            "c) It should not be completely pure",
            "d) It should be cheap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It should be highly pure. Further, it should be readily available and non-inflammable."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of hydrogen, which can be used as carrier gas in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dangerous to use",
            "b) Expensive",
            "c) Reduced sensitivity",
            "d) High density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrogen is dangerous to use. It has better thermal conductivity and lower density."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of helium, which can be used as carrier gas in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dangerous to use",
            "b) Expensive",
            "c) Reduced sensitivity",
            "d) High density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Helium is expensive. Its advantages are that it has low density and it allows greater flow rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of nitrogen, which can be used as carrier gas in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dangerous to use",
            "b) Expensive",
            "c) Reduced sensitivity",
            "d) High density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitrogen has reduced sensitivity. It is still one of the commonly used carrier gas in gas chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "In which of the following methods are liquid samples injected into the column in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas tight syringe",
            "b) Micro-syringe",
            "c) Rotary sample valve",
            "d) Solid injection syringes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slow injection of large samples leads to band broadening and loss of resolution. Hence, for desired column efficiency, samples should not be too large."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "What must be done to the solid samples for it to be introduced into the column without using solid injection syringes in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Introduced in hot-zone of the column",
            "b) Dissolved in volatile liquids",
            "c) Introduced using rotary sample valve",
            "d) Introduced using sampling loops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Liquid samples injected into the column in gas chromatography using micro-syringe. Syringes of various capacities are available."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the commonly used support material for the packed column in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Metal",
            "c) Diatomaceous earth",
            "d) Stainless steel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solid samples must be dissolved in volatile liquids for introducing it into the column. They can be introduced directly using solid injection syringes."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the advantage of a straight packed column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be packed uniformly",
            "b) It can be repacked easily",
            "c) It is compact",
            "d) It is easier to heat it evenly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Diatomaceous earth is the commonly used support material for the packed column in gas chromatography. The columns could be made of glass or metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of coiled or helical shaped packed chromatographic column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It cannot be packed uniformly",
            "b) It cannot be repacked easily",
            "c) It is not compact",
            "d) It is not easy to heat it evenly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The advantage of the straight column is that it can be repacked easily. It is not compact in size."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Capillary columns are open tubular columns constructed from which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Metal",
            "c) Stainless steel",
            "d) Fused silica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The disadvantage of coiled or helical shaped packed chromatographic column is that it cannot be repacked easily. It is compact in size and can easily be heated in an even manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a desirable feature of the ovens used in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It must have a fast rate of heating",
            "b) Power consumption should be kept low",
            "c) It must have maximum thermal gradients",
            "d) It should have proper insulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Capillary columns are constructed using fused silica. It is a very high purity glass."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an ideal characteristic of a detector used in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear response to the solutes",
            "b) Short response time",
            "c) High reliability",
            "d) Sensitive to the changes in the flow rate of a carrier gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The detector used in gas chromatography must be insensitive to the changes in flow rate of carrier gas. There are many detectors used in gas chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of detector used in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon ionisation detector",
            "b) Thermal conductivity detector",
            "c) UV visible spectrometric detector",
            "d) Electron capture detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: UV visible spectrometric detector is not used in gas chromatography. It is used in liquid chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors have high sensitivity to all organic compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphur chemiluminescense detector",
            "b) Thermionic emission detector",
            "c) Flame ionization detector",
            "d) Argon ionisation detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flame ionization detector has high sensitivity to all organic compounds. It is the commonly used detector for gas chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the advantage of thermal conductivity detector used in gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple in construction",
            "b) High sensitivity",
            "c) Large linear dynamic range",
            "d) Non-destructive character"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal conductivity detector has relatively low density when compared to other detectors used in gas chromatography. It is based on the principle that all gases conduct heat in varying degrees."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors is widely used to detect environmental samples like chlorinated pesticides and polychlorinated biphenyls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flame ionization detector",
            "b) Thermal conductivity detector",
            "c) Argon ionisation detector",
            "d) Electron capture detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electron capture detector is used to detect environmental samples like polychlorinated biphenyls and chlorinated pesticides. It is highly sensitive to molecules containing functional groups such as halogen and phosphorous."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "In which of the following detector is the eluent mixed with hydrogen and burned and then mixed with ozone and its intensity is measured?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphur chemiluminescense detector",
            "b) Thermal conductivity detector",
            "c) Flame ionization detector",
            "d) Electron capture detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Sulphur chemiluminescense detector, the eluent is mixed with hydrogen and burned and then mixed with ozone and its intensity is measured. The resultant is a measure of sulphur compounds present."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Filter photometer detector is primarily responsive to which of the following compounds/elements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volatile sulphur or phosphorous compounds",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Halogen",
            "d) Potassium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flame photometric detector is primarily responsive to volatile sulphur or phosphorous compounds. It is also responsive to tin and nitrogen."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Which of the following detector uses ultraviolet radiation from lamps to produce ionisation of solute molecules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphur chemiluminescense detector",
            "b) Thermal conductivity detector",
            "c) Photo ionization detector",
            "d) Electron capture detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Photo ionization detector uses ultraviolet radiation from lamps to produce ionisation of solute molecules. The current produced is measured and recorded."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Thermionic emission detector used in gas chromatography is most sensitive to which of the following elements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) Phosphorous",
            "c) Halogen",
            "d) Carbon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermal conductivity detector is known as Katharometer. It uses heated filament as a sensing element and it is placed in the emerging gas stream."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors has a non-volatile bead of rubidium silicate placed above the flame tip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon ionisation detector",
            "b) Thermionic emission detector",
            "c) Flame ionization detector",
            "d) Electron capture detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermionic emission detector used in gas chromatography is most sensitive to phosphorous. It is 500 times more sensitive to phosphorous than Flame ionization detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "In which of the following detectors, the carrier gas is excited by a radioactive source and the atoms of carrier gas are excited to a metastable state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon ionisation detector",
            "b) Thermionic emission detector",
            "c) Flame ionization detector",
            "d) Electron capture detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermionic emission detector has a non-volatile bead of rubidium silicate placed above the flame tip. It is maintained at about 180V with respect to the collector."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used as a heating element in a Thermal conductivity detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platinum",
            "b) Gold",
            "c) Graphite",
            "d) Tungsten wire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Argon ionisation detector, the carrier gas is excited by a radioactive source and the atoms of carrier gas are excited to a metastable state. It uses argon as carrier gas."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Gas-solid chromatography is based on which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Partition of the analyte between a gaseous mobile phase and a stationary liquid phase",
            "b) Adsorption of gaseous substances on solid surface",
            "c) Ion exchange",
            "d) Large molecules cannot penetrate through the gel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gas-solid chromatography is based on the adsorption of gaseous substances on a solid surface. It is useful for the separation of rare gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following components cannot be retained by gas-liquid columns but can be separated by using gas-solid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formaldehyde",
            "b) Hydrogen sulphide",
            "c) Benzene",
            "d) Carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydrogen sulphide cannot be retained by gas-liquid columns. It can be separated using gas-solid chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of gas-solid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased column life",
            "b) Can be used for separation of rare gases",
            "c) Leads to semi-permanent retention of the analyte",
            "d) Ability to retain some components that cannot be easily retained by other gas chromatography method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gas-solid chromatography leads to semi-permanent retention of the analyte. Hence, it is used for limited applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which of the following columns can be used in Gas-solid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open tubular column",
            "b) Analytical column",
            "c) Separation column",
            "d) Guard column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The distribution coefficients of Gas-solid chromatography are greater than that of Gas-liquid chromatography. The stationary phase is a solid particle."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage for the conversion of packed columns into wide bore capillaries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longer retention times",
            "b) Longer life",
            "c) Higher efficiency",
            "d) Greater inertness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Open tubular column can be used in Gas-solid chromatography. Analytical/separation column and guard column is used in liquid chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a disadvantage of gas-solid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strong retention of polar solutes",
            "b) Lifetime is short",
            "c) Occurrence of catalytic changes",
            "d) Cannot be used for very wide range of components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wide bore capillary has a shorter retention time. It is an advantage. It is undesirable to have a longer retention time."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a special adsorbent used in gas-solid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecular sieves",
            "b) Silica gel",
            "c) Alumina",
            "d) Starch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lifetime of gas-solid chromatography is long. It can be used for geometrical isomers."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Which of the following properties of molecular sieves make it ideal for exclusion mechanism of separation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High thermal stability",
            "b) Large inner surface area",
            "c) Variable framework charge",
            "d) Ability to distinguish materials on the basis of their size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gas-solid chromatography can be used only for separation of certain low molecular weight gaseous species. This is because of gas-solid chromatography, semi-permanent retention of analyte only takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of reciprocating pump used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Produces pulsed flow",
            "b) Corrosive components",
            "c) Does not have small hold-up value",
            "d) Does not have moderate flow rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantage of reciprocating pump used in liquid chromatography is that it produces pulsed flow. Therefore, the flow must be damped before it affects the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a disadvantage of Pneumatic pumps used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulsed output",
            "b) Dependent on solvent viscosity",
            "c) Dependent on back pressure",
            "d) Inconvenient for solvent gradient elution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pneumatic pumps provide pulse free output. They are inexpensive."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a desired characteristic of pulse dampers or flow smootheners used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy mobile phase change over",
            "b) Constant flow must be maintained",
            "c) Should be effective at low system pressure",
            "d) Maximal dead volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pulse dampers are used to avoid variations in flow. They must have minimal dead volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which of the following will improve the efficiency of the separation process in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in sample size, increase in column diameter",
            "b) Reduction in sample size, increase in column diameter",
            "c) Increase in sample size, reduction in column diameter",
            "d) Reduction in sample size, reduction in column diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reduction in sample size and reduction in column diameter will improve the efficiency of the separation process in liquid chromatography. The effect of uneven flow will also be reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the practical problems that arise due to the decrease in column diameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Requirement of large particle size and high pressure drop",
            "b) Requirement of large particle size and low pressure drop",
            "c) Requirement of small particle size and high pressure drop",
            "d) Requirement of small particle size and low pressure drop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The practical problems that arise due to a decrease in column diameter are the requirement of small particle size and high pressure drop. But, it increases column efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the guard column used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It filters particles that clog the separation column",
            "b) It extends the lifetime of separation column",
            "c) It allows particles that cause precipitation upon contact with stationary or mobile phase",
            "d) The size of packing varies with the type of protection needed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Guard column removes particles that cause precipitation upon contact with stationary or mobile phase. It is placed before the separation column."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Which of the following columns are not used in liquid or high performance liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analytical column",
            "b) Separation column",
            "c) Guard column",
            "d) Capillary column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Capillary column is used in gas chromatography. Analytical column is also known as a separation column."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a Column-type Liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gel permeation",
            "b) Ion exchange",
            "c) Liquid-solid",
            "d) Paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Paper chromatography is not a column-type chromatography. It makes use of strips of hollow cylinders of filter paper."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the radial compression column when compared to standard separation column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal diameter decreases",
            "b) Overall operating pressure decreases",
            "c) Analysis time decreases",
            "d) Solvent flow increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radial compression columns have a wider diameter than the standard separation column. The cartridges used are of low cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about narrow bore column when compared to standard columns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal diameter decreases",
            "b) Volumetric flow decreases",
            "c) Solvent cost is saved",
            "d) Detector response time increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Detector response time increases in narrow bore columns. High purity solvents must be used in these columns."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of liquid chromatography uses immobilized biochemical as a stationary phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion exchange chromatography",
            "b) Exclusion chromatography",
            "c) Affinity chromatography",
            "d) Gel permeation chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Affinity chromatography, immobilized biochemical is used as stationary phase. It is used to separate one or few solutes from hundreds of unretained solutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about High pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It requires high pressure for the separation of the specious",
            "b) There is no need to vaporise the samples",
            "c) It is performed in columns",
            "d) It has high sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In High pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC), samples need to be vaporised. It has high sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Syringe type pumps used in High pressure liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Independent of viscosity",
            "b) Pulse-less flow",
            "c) High pressure capability",
            "d) Unlimited solvent capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High pressure liquid chromatography can be performed only in columns. This is because the application of high pressure in the open bed will not be effective."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about solvent programming which is done in high performance liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It provides unequal bandwidths",
            "b) It provides fast overall separation",
            "c) It provides maximum resolution",
            "d) It provides maximum sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The limitation of Syringe type pump is that it has a limited solvent capacity and is inconvenient when solvents are to be changed."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Which of the following pulse damper takes up some amount of the pulsation energy which is released to provide smooth pressure without pulsations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible bellows or compressible gas passed through tee columns",
            "b) Flexible inert diaphragm",
            "c) Electronic pulse damper",
            "d) Electrical pulse damper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Solvent programming is done to provide equal bandwidths. It provides maximum sensitivity for every solute in the sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of the syringe pump used in high pressure liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure capability is high",
            "b) Maintenance is frequent",
            "c) Limited reservoir capability",
            "d) Slight change of flow rate when extremely high pressure compresses the solvent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flexible bellows or compressible gas passed through tee columns take up some of the pulsation energy which is released to provide smooth pressure without pulsations. Its main purpose is to avoid pulses."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Syringe pumps used in High pressure liquid chromatography are most suitable for which of the following columns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capillary columns",
            "b) Guard columns",
            "c) Short-fast columns",
            "d) Small bore columns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In syringe pumps, maintenance is infrequent. However, it has high pressure capability."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be done to reduce ripple in High pressure liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using bellows",
            "b) Using restrictors",
            "c) Using long nylon tube between pump and column",
            "d) Avoiding the use of the solvent pump"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Syringe pumps used in High pressure liquid chromatography are most suitable for small bore columns. It is the most commonly used piston type pump."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Hydraulic capacitance flow control system used in HPLC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be used only for liquids with low viscosity",
            "b) It is irrespective of solvent compressibility",
            "c) It maintains a constant flow",
            "d) It smoothens high pressure pump pulsations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gravity feed method for solvent delivery is not used with narrow bore columns packed with fine mesh particles. This is because they cannot deliver solvent at high pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Bulk property detectors used in liquid chromatography does not respond to which of the following properties?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Refractive index",
            "b) Density",
            "c) Properties of solutes",
            "d) Dielectric constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bulk property detectors respond only to bulk properties of the mobile phase. It does not respond to properties of solutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of a good detector used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good sensitivity",
            "b) Ability to function in the presence of a large background signal",
            "c) Short response time",
            "d) Volume of detector must be large"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The volume of the detector must be small. If the volume of the detector is large it may lead to band broadening."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following UV absorbance detectors provide a real time spectrum of the component of interest?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous wavelength detector",
            "b) Variable wavelength detector",
            "c) Scanning wavelength detector",
            "d) Fixed wavelength detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Detector selectivity is more important in Liquid chromatography than in Gas chromatography. This is because of liquid chromatography, chances of overlapping are higher."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors depend on Snell’s law at the interface between the cell wall and the flowing liquid to deflect the light beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical detectors",
            "b) Fluorescence detectors",
            "c) Refractive index detectors",
            "d) Thermal conductivity detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Scanning wavelength detector provides a real time spectrum of the component of interest. UV visible detector is the most widely used detection system."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Refractive index detectors used in liquid chromatography are not based on which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interference",
            "b) Refraction",
            "c) Reflection",
            "d) Absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fluorescence detection is more selective than absorption detection. This is because of its high sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors can be used for detection of amino acids in protein hydrolyzates by introducing the reagent dansylchloride in the sample?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical detectors",
            "b) Fluorescence detectors",
            "c) Refractive index detectors",
            "d) Thermal conductivity detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Refractive index detectors depend on Snell’s law at the interface between the cell wall and the flowing liquid to deflect the light beam. Changes in refractive index are monitored by a position sensor."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "The reference cell is packed with which of the following in the Adsorption detector used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inactive glass beads",
            "b) Porous glass beads",
            "c) Alumina",
            "d) Silica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Refractive index detectors used in liquid chromatography are not dependent on absorption. It depends on reflection, refraction and interference."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about Laser detectors used in liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Causes thermal distortion has decreased sensitivity",
            "b) Causes thermal distortion has increased sensitivity",
            "c) Does not cause thermal distortion, has decreased sensitivity",
            "d) Does not cause thermal distortion, has increased sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fluorescence detectors can be used for detection of amino acids in protein hydrolyzates by introducing the reagent dansylchloride in the sample. Other compounds that can be detected are petroleum products and natural products."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors used in liquid chromatography is also called micro-adsorption detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrochemical detectors",
            "b) Fluorescence detectors",
            "c) Refractive index detectors",
            "d) Thermal detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Adsorption detector used in liquid chromatography, the reference cell is packed with inactive glass beads. The other detector cavity is packed with silica, alumina or porous glass beads."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "In UV-Visible detectors, the cells are not made of which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quartz",
            "b) Teflon",
            "c) Silica",
            "d) KELF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Laser detectors used in liquid chromatography cause thermal distortion and have decreased sensitivity. This is because of the high energies of a laser."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of refractive index type detectors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher potential sensitivity",
            "b) Low cost",
            "c) High volume flow rates",
            "d) Easy cell accessibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Another name for the thermal detector is micro-adsorption detector. The operation depends upon temperature changes taking place due to the heat of adsorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors can detect almost any component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combining two UV detectors",
            "b) Combining RI and UV detectors",
            "c) Mass detector",
            "d) Laser-based detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cells in UV-Visible detectors are made of quartz, KELF and Teflon. They are not made of silica."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "What is the drawback that occurs in using ion exchange chromatography on sulphonated polystyrene resin and colourimetry for amino-acid analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less accuracy",
            "b) Low resolution",
            "c) Inconvenient to handle many individual samples",
            "d) Slow in operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When ion exchange chromatography is used for amino-acid analysis, high accuracy is obtained. It is inconvenient to handle many individual samples and cleaning of glassware is laborious."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Which one of the following methods is the most suitable for amino-acid analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas chromatography",
            "b) Ion exchange chromatography",
            "c) Paper electrophoresis",
            "d) Resin column chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Resin column chromatography is the most suitable for amino-acid analysis. Here, ion exchange resin chromatography is followed."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following colour reagents are used in Resin column chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Marquis reagent",
            "b) Benedict reagent",
            "c) Ninhydrin",
            "d) Nessler’s reagent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ninhydrin is the colour reagent used in resin column chromatography. The colour reaction occurs during a known period and controlled temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following amino-acids is measured at a wavelength of 440nm using photometric systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proline",
            "b) Alanine",
            "c) Glutamine",
            "d) Valine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Proline and hydroxyproline are measured at 440nm. All the other amino acids are measured at 570nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "In Automatic amino-acid analyzer, the sample containing ___________ of each amino compound is introduced at the top of the ion exchange column.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 10 µmoles",
            "b) 1 to 10 moles",
            "c) 0.05 to 2 moles",
            "d) 0.05 to 2 µmoles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Automatic amino-acid analyzer, the sample having 0.05 to 2 µmoles of each amino compound is introduced at the top of the ion exchange column. Buffer is then supplied to the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be analysed using resin column chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptides",
            "b) Amines",
            "c) Amino compounds",
            "d) Components which are ninhydrin negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Components which are ninhydrin negative cannot be analysed using resin column chromatography. Only the components that are nindydrin positive are analysed using this method."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Trapped air in pumps of Automatic amino-acid analyzer is eliminated using which of the following ways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suction pump",
            "b) De-aerator",
            "c) Overcome naturally by pump pressure",
            "d) Using pulse damper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: De-aerator is used to eliminate trapper air in pumps of an automatic amino-acid analyzer. Here, bubble-trap type de-aerator is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What is the drawback that occurs in using gas chromatography for amino-acid analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Costly",
            "b) Cannot be used for proteins or polypeptides",
            "c) Slow process",
            "d) Complex in operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Amino-acids are distinguishable from each other only by one or two atoms in their structure. They are components of all proteins and are essential for growth of organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "Which among the following gases have diamagnetic property (ability to be repelled by magnetic fields)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Nitrogen dioxide",
            "d) Nitric oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nitrogen has diamagnetic property. Other components that have diamagnetic property are carbon, boron, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases have paramagnetic property (ability to get attracted to a magnetic field)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitric oxide",
            "b) Hydrogen",
            "c) Helium",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nitric oxide has paramagnetic property. Nitrogen dioxide and oxygen are other gases that have paramagnetic property."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The force produced during the operation of Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer is proportional to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic susceptibility of sphere",
            "b) Magnetic susceptibility of surrounding gas",
            "c) Difference between magnetic susceptibility of sphere and magnetic field strength",
            "d) Difference between magnetic susceptibility of sphere and that of surrounding gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The paramagnetic property of oxygen is used in this method for the analysis of oxygen. The force produced during operation of Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer is proportional to the difference between magnetic susceptibility of sphere and that of surrounding gas."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "In Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer, the expression for magnitude of force produced can be expressed as, F = C (K-KO), where K= magnetic susceptibility of surrounding gas and KO= magnetic susceptibility of sphere. C denotes which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic field strength",
            "b) Magnetic gradient",
            "c) Function of magnetic field strength and gradient",
            "d) Magnetic flux"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the expression for magnitude of force, C denotes the function of magnetic field strength and gradient. The forces are thus a measure of magnetic susceptibility and hence of oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "In Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer, the electrostatic force that is exerted should have which of the following features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It should be greater than the magnetic field and must be in the same direction",
            "b) It should be equal to the magnetic field and must be in the same direction",
            "c) It should be greater than the magnetic field and must be in the opposite direction",
            "d) It should be equal to the magnetic field and must be in the opposite direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electrostatic force that is exerted should be equal to the magnetic field and must be in the opposite direction. It is exerted by two charged vanes."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about the two charged vanes that produce electric field in Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both the vanes should be at higher potential than the test body",
            "b) Both the vanes should have the same potential as the test body",
            "c) One vane should be at higher potential than the test body and the other vane should be at lower potential",
            "d) Both the vanes should be at lower potential than the test body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer, the two charged vanes should be such that one vane should be at higher potential than the test body and the other vane should be at lower potential. This electric field produces a force."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "To improve paramagnetic oxygen analyzer, the quartz suspension must be replaced with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platinum-iridium",
            "b) Phosphor-bronze",
            "c) Gold-palladium",
            "d) Antimony"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Paramagnetic oxygen analyzer, when no oxygen is present the magnetic force balances torque of the fibre. If oxygen is present, it would displace the dumb-bell sphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "In the Beckman instrument, the flow rate recommended when the sample enters through a porous diffusion disc is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-200 cc/min",
            "b) 50-250 cc/min",
            "c) 40-60 cc/min",
            "d) 200-300 cc/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To improve paramagnetic oxygen analyzer, the quartz suspension must be replaced with Platinum-iridium. It is more robust."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "In the Beckman instrument, the flow rate recommended when the sample enters directly for rapid response is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-200 cc/min",
            "b) 50-250 cc/min",
            "c) 40-60 cc/min",
            "d) 200-300 cc/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the Beckman instrument, the flow rate recommended when the sample enters through a porous diffusion disc is 50-250 cc/min. paramagnetic oxygen analyzer was first described by Pauling."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Which of the following happens to the magnetic susceptibility of gases when the temperature changes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It increases with increase in temperature",
            "b) It decreases with increase in temperature",
            "c) It remains constant with increase in temperature",
            "d) It remains constant with decrease in temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the Beckman instrument, the flow rate recommended when the sample enters directly for rapid response is 40-60 cc/min. paramagnetic oxygen analyzer was first described by Pauling."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "If the oxygen content is not greater than 21%, which of the following gases must be used to set the span point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Dry air",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnetic susceptibility of gases decreases with increase in temperature. Magnetic susceptibility of oxygen decreases with increase in temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "If the oxygen content is greater than 21%, which of the following gases must be used to set the span point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Dry air",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the oxygen content is not greater than 21%, dry air is used to set the span point. This is done for calibration purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not occur in Hartman and Braun oxygen analyzer based on the magnetic wind?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen is attracted to the magnetic field",
            "b) Oxygen becomes less paramagnetic due to rise in temperature",
            "c) Resistance change in a resistance connected to the Wheatstone bridge occur",
            "d) Wheatstone Bridge becomes balanced due to temperature change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Hartman and Braun oxygen analyzer, the magnetic wind cools the heated winding. As a result, the bridge becomes unbalanced."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a cause of the error that could occur in Hartman and Braun oxygen analyzer based on the magnetic wind?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The filament temperature could be affected by changes in thermal conductivity of the carrier gas",
            "b) Hydrocarbons in sample stream may react on the heated filaments",
            "c) Gravitation chimney flow effect lead to errors when cross tube is horizontal",
            "d) Combustible gases may react on the heated filaments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Error occurs when a cross tube is vertical. When the cross tube is horizontal, errors due to gravitation chimney flow effect is avoided."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Magnetic wind analyzers are also known as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermo-magnetic analyzers",
            "b) Electro-magnetic analyzers",
            "c) Thermo-analytical analyzers",
            "d) Hot wire analyzers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrocarbons need to be removed from the sample gas to avoid errors. This is because they may react on the heated filaments and lead to a change in temperature and resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "In OXYMAT-M oxygen analyser which of the following is usually used as reference gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Helium",
            "d) Ambient air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic wind analyzers are also known as Thermo-magnetic analyzers. In Europe, it is known as Magnetic wind analyzers. In the United States, it is known as Thermo-magnetic analyzers."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used in magnetic wind instruments to determine the amount of oxygen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Change in resistance",
            "b) Change in capacitance",
            "c) Change in inductance",
            "d) Change in concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In OXYMAT-M oxygen analyser, ambient air is usually used as a reference gas. Its measuring procedure is based on pressure difference which develops between two gases having different oxygen concentration in the magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following concepts are not used in magnetic wind instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Change in resistance due to cooling by magnetic wind",
            "b) Displacement of membrane by magnetised oxygen",
            "c) Difference in pressure difference between two gases having varying concentration of oxygen",
            "d) By measuring temperature using thermometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In magnetic wind instruments to determine the amount of oxygen, change in temperature leads to a change in resistance. This change in resistance is measured to determine the amount of oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "How are the hydrocarbons in the samples removed in magnetic wind instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By using a cold trap",
            "b) By using a filter",
            "c) By using a semipermeable membrane",
            "d) By using magnetic effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Temperature is not measured in magnetic wind instruments. The cooling effect of magnetic wind causes a change in resistance which is measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following bridges are used in magnetic wind instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheatstone bridge",
            "b) Kelvin’s bridge",
            "c) Anderson’s bridge",
            "d) Schering’s bridge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydrocarbons in the samples are removed in magnetic wind instruments by using a cold trap. It is removed to avoid combustion."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the galvanic method of oxygen analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrodes are composed of noble and base metals",
            "b) It can measure dissolved content of oxygen",
            "c) Its principle is based on electrolysis",
            "d) It utilizes an electronic cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Galvanic method of oxygen analysis is based on the reverse of electrolysis. In this method, the electrical current developed is related to the rate of oxygen uptake by the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about Hersch cell which is one of the arrangements of a galvanic cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell is spherical in shape",
            "b) Cathode is made of porous material",
            "c) Cathode is placed centrally",
            "d) Cathode is formed by gauze which surrounds the anode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Hersch cell, cell is cylindrical in shape. Anode is placed centrally and is made of porous material. Cathode is formed by gauze which surrounds the anode."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Polarographic cells type of electrochemical method uses which of the following concepts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyclic reactions",
            "b) Exothermic reactions",
            "c) Reversible reactions",
            "d) Redox reactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polarographic cells type of electrochemical method uses redox reactions. It is used to measure the partial pressure of the percentage of oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods, is the widely used method for trace gas analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Galvanic methods",
            "b) Conductometric method",
            "c) Polarographic cells",
            "d) Thermal conductivity method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conductometric method is the widely used method for trace gas analysis. This method is very convenient."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "In the conductometric method, the difference in gas conductivity before and after passing sample gas denotes which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency of the cell",
            "b) Quantity of reagent",
            "c) Concentration of gas",
            "d) Density of the reagent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the conductometric method, the difference in gas conductivity before and after passing sample gas denotes the concentration of gas. The sample gas is passed through the liquid reagent."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Conductometric method is not very suitable for measuring traces of which of the following gases in ppb range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H2S",
            "b) SO2",
            "c) NH3",
            "d) CO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Conductometric method is not very suitable for measuring traces of CO. It is suitable for measuring traces of H2O."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Polarographic cells are not sensitive to which of the following gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon monoxide",
            "b) Carbon dioxide",
            "c) Nitrous oxide",
            "d) Oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polarographic cells are not sensitive to carbon monoxide. They show 0.1% error while measuring oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "In polarographic cell when potential is applied, oxygen is reduced at __________ when KCl is present.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anode",
            "b) Cathode",
            "c) Electrolyte",
            "d) Both the electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In polarographic cell when potential is applied, oxygen is reduced at the cathode. Reduction reactions take place at the cathode. KCl is the electrolyte."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Nitrogen oxide cannot be directly analysed using UV and Visible analyzers due to which of the following reasons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less accuracy",
            "b) Very low range",
            "c) It leads to contamination of the sample",
            "d) It is transparent in UV visible regions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nitrogen dioxide can be detected with a paramagnetic analyser. This is because nitrogen has paramagnetic property ie. it is attracted by magnetic fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "How is NO converted to NO2 for analysis in UV and Visible analyzers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treating sample gas with pressurized oxygen",
            "b) Treating sample gas with ozone",
            "c) Treating sample gas with oxygen at low pressure",
            "d) Treating sample gas with water at high pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nitrogen oxide cannot be directly analysed using UV and Visible analyzers because it is transparent in UV visible regions. Hence, it is converted into nitrogen dioxide and then analysed."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "How is NO converted to NO2 for analysis in Chemiluminescent analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treating sample gas with pressurized oxygen",
            "b) Treating sample gas with ozone",
            "c) Treating sample gas with oxygen at low pressure",
            "d) Treating sample gas with water at high pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NO is converted into NO2 for analysis in UV and Visible analyzers by treating sample gas with pressurized oxygen. This is because direct measurement of NO is not possible using UV and Visible analyzers."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "During analysis of NO2 using Chemiluminescent analyser, why is NO2 not made to react with ozone directly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less accuracy",
            "b) It is a slow process",
            "c) It leads to contamination of the sample",
            "d) It does not produce luminescence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: NO is converted to NO2 for analysis in Chemiluminescent analyser by treating sample gas with ozone.\nNO + O3 —>NO2 + O2"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "The instruments based on chemiluminescence maintain linearity in which of the following ranges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1ppb to 100ppb",
            "b) 100ppb to 1000ppb",
            "c) 1ppb to 1000ppb",
            "d) 100ppb to 1000ppb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During analysis of NO2 using Chemiluminescent analyser, NO2 is not made to react with ozone directly because it is a slow process. Hence, it is converted to NO using catalytic reactions or converters."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "How can absorption be enhanced while determining NO concentration using CO laser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By converting NO into NO2",
            "b) By placing NO in a magnetic field",
            "c) By using proper monochromators",
            "d) By using choppers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unmarked procedure is NO to NO2 oxidiser. NO2 is then analysed by NO2 analyser."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors are generally used for detection in NO analysis using CO laser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photomultiplier tube",
            "b) Photovoltaic cell",
            "c) Liquid nitrogen cooled Ge-Au element",
            "d) Photo emissive tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unmarked block is Difference. Difference between the concentration of NO2 and NO and the concentration of NO2 alone is determined and the result gives the concentration of NO."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following analyzers are used to measure trace amounts of nitrogen oxides in the stratosphere?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemiluminescence",
            "b) CO laser method",
            "c) Laser opto-acoustic spectroscopy",
            "d) Colorimetry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The instruments based on chemiluminescence maintain linearity between 1ppb to 1000ppb. These are used to measure NO in exhaust gases in vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "A pink coloured dye complex is formed when air containing NO2 is passed in an absorbing solution consisting of __________ and diamine dissolved in the acetic acid medium.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphuric acid",
            "b) Sulphonyl",
            "c) Sulphonic acid",
            "d) Sulphanilic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CO laser emits radiation that can absorb NO. Absorption is enhanced by placing NO in a magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "In Laser Opto-acoustic spectroscopy, the IR beam excites the molecules to higher states. In which of the following ways do the molecules return to the ground state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collisional de-excitation",
            "b) Random de-excitation",
            "c) By spontaneous emission",
            "d) By stimulated emission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Liquid nitrogen cooled Ge-Au element is used detection in NO analysis using CO laser. The signal amplitude varied with the concentration of NO."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of electrochemical cells used for analysis of H2S?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Portable battery operated instrument",
            "b) Pocket sized instrument",
            "c) No pumps are needed",
            "d) No interference from background gases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electrochemical cells are affected by interference from background gases. Some of them are sulphur dioxide, carbon monoxide, nitric oxide and chlorine."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods are mainly used in combustible gas detection equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lead acetate tape staining method",
            "b) Solid state sensor",
            "c) Gold film sensor",
            "d) Electrochemical cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solid state sensors are mainly used in combustible gas detection equipment. It is a semiconductor sensor."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of solid state sensor used for analysis of H2S?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No sampling system",
            "b) It can be used in conditions involving vibration",
            "c) It can be used in corrosive atmosphere",
            "d) No interference from background gases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Solid state sensors are affected by interference from background gases. Some of them are hydrogen, isopropanol and ethyl and methyl mercaptan."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which is the compound that forms the stain in Lead Acetate Tape Staining method used for the analysis of Hydrogen Sulphide and what is the colour of the stain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lead Sulphide, red colour",
            "b) Lead Sulphide, brown colour",
            "c) Hydrogen acetate, white colour",
            "d) Hydrogen acetate, green colour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydrogen Sulphide reacts with Lead Acetate to form Lead Sulphide which is brown in colour. Hydrogen acetate in other words is acetic acid and is colourless."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods is not used for detection of hydrogen sulphide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lead acetate tape staining method",
            "b) Solid state sensor",
            "c) Chemiluminescence method",
            "d) Electrochemical cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemiluminescence method cannot be used for the detection of hydrogen sulphide. Others method that are used are using photometric analyser and using gold film sensor."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "In solid state sensor, when heated to 150o to 300o which of the following occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resistance decreases with increase in H2S concentration",
            "b) Resistance increases with H2S concentration",
            "c) No change in resistance occurs",
            "d) Sensor does not respond in this temperature range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In solid state sensor, when heated to 150o to 300o resistance decreases with increase in H2S concentration. The decrease in resistance is a logarithmic function of H2S concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following occurs in Electrochemical cells used for the detection of hydrogen sulphide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Change in resistance",
            "b) Redox reaction",
            "c) Oxidation-reduction reaction",
            "d) Change in colour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gold film sensor works on the principle of absorption. The change in resistance is proportional to the concentration of H2S."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of solid state sensor used for detection of hydrogen sulphide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heater",
            "b) Thermistor",
            "c) Semiconductor film",
            "d) Photo detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Electrochemical cells, an oxidation-reduction reaction occurs in the presence of hydrogen sulphide. A current starts flowing and it is proportional to the concentration of hydrogen sulphide."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a detector used in mid Infrared Spectrophotometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermopile",
            "b) Thermistor",
            "c) Pyroelectric cell",
            "d) Golay cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Golay cell is not used in mid Infrared Spectrophotometer. It is used in a far infrared spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Why is the use of infrared analyzers limited when it comes to the analysis of inorganic compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slow response occurs",
            "b) Less accurate results occur",
            "c) Strong absorption of IR radiation by water",
            "d) Small range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The use of infrared analyzers is limited when it comes to the analysis of inorganic compounds because of the strong absorption of IR radiation by water. It is particularly used for organic compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the chopping frequency used for industrial analyzers in the simple infrared analyser for gas analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-10 Hz",
            "b) 2-50 Hz",
            "c) 2-100 Hz",
            "d) 2-150 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The chopping frequency used for industrial analysers in the simple infrared analyzer for gas analysis is 2-10 Hz. The chopper is motor driven."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as a source in the simple infrared analyzer for gas analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten filament lamp",
            "b) Nernst glower",
            "c) Hot-wire spiral",
            "d) Mercury arc lamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hot-wire spiral is used as a source in the simple infrared analyzer for gas analysis. Two sources are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the chopping frequency used for medical applications in simple infrared analyser for gas analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-10 Hz",
            "b) 2-50 Hz",
            "c) 2-100 Hz",
            "d) 2-150 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vibration excitation occurs only if the sample has hetero-atomic molecules. Hence, infrared analyzers are not used for gases whose molecules are formed by two identical atoms."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "The movement of diaphragm in simple infrared analyser for gas analysis results in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variable resistance",
            "b) Variable inductance",
            "c) Variable capacitance",
            "d) Variable conductance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chopping frequency used for medical applications in simple infrared analyser for gas analysis is 2-50 Hz. The chopper is motor driven."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the drawback of conventional infrared analyzers used for gas analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell is difficult to maintain",
            "b) It is expensive to replace",
            "c) Detector is vibration sensitive",
            "d) Only one source is used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The movement of diaphragm in simple infrared analyser for gas analysis results in variable apacitance. The diaphragm forms one plate of the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as detector in improved infrared analyzer used for gas analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PbSe",
            "b) MgCl2",
            "c) ZnCl",
            "d) CuCl2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two sources are used in conventional infrared analyzers used for gas analysis. To overcome the drawbacks an improved model was created."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "In calibration of CO2 analyser, in order to establish zero calibration which of the following is used as sample?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Hydrogen",
            "c) Inert gases",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PbSe is used as detector in improved infrared analyzer used for gas analysis. It is a solid state detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristics of Indium arsenide photovoltaic detector used in infrared analyzers for hydrocarbons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It operates at ambient temperature",
            "b) Has maximum detectivity at 3.4µm",
            "c)  Sensitivity increases at longer wavelength",
            "d) It has no response to radiation of wavelength greater than 4µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In calibration of CO2 analyser, in order to establish zero calibration inert gases are used as sample. Generally, room air is also used."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Which kind of filter is used in improved version of infrared gas analyzer at the output end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low pass filter",
            "b) High pass filter",
            "c) Narrow bandpass filter",
            "d) Wide bandpass filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sensitivity of Indium arsenide photovoltaic detector decreases at longer wavelength. It is insensitive to radiation having a wavelength greater than 4µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Thermal conductivity analyzers cannot be used in which of the following measurements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen in blast furnace gases",
            "b) Determination of argon in oxygen in the process of air decomposition",
            "c) Sulphur dioxide in roasting gases in production of sulphuric acid",
            "d) Oxygen from a mixture of oxygen and nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermal conductivity analyzers cannot be used in analysing oxygen from a mixture of oxygen and nitrogen. This is because the thermal conductivity of oxygen and nitrogen is almost the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "In which of the following conditions can thermal conductivity analyzer be used for multi-component mixtures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When all the components have same thermal conductivities",
            "b) When all the components have very different thermal conductivities",
            "c) When all but one component have same thermal conductivities",
            "d) When all components have very different thermal conductivities except two of them which are the same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When all but one component have the same thermal conductivities, thermal conductivity analyzer can be used for multi-component mixtures. The mixture is then treated as a binary mixture."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Which among the following elements has the highest thermal conductivity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Hydrogen",
            "d) Chlorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrogen has the highest thermal conductivity. Chlorine has the lowest thermal conductivity in the list."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are generally not used for the construction of filaments in thermal conductivity analyzers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten",
            "b) Gold",
            "c) Platinum",
            "d) Kovar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gold is generally not used for the construction of filaments in thermal conductivity analyzers. The materials used have high temperature-coefficient of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of thermistors used in thermal conductivity analyzers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High negative temperature coefficient of resistance",
            "b) Slow response",
            "c) Extremely sensitive",
            "d) Low cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermistors have negative temperature-coefficient of resistance. RTDs have positive temperature-coefficient of resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "How can the high speed of response be obtained in thermal conductivity analyzers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By increasing the pressure of gas surrounding the filaments",
            "b) By reducing the pressure of gas surrounding the filaments",
            "c) By reducing the temperature of gas surrounding the filaments",
            "d) By increasing the temperature of gas surrounding the filaments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermistors have fast response.  They are arranged as heat sensing elements in the Wheatstone bridge."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which of the following bridges are used in thermal conductivity analyzers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheatstone bridge",
            "b) Kelvin’s bridge",
            "c) Anderson’s bridge",
            "d) Schering’s bridge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High speed of response be obtained in thermal conductivity analyzers by reducing the pressure of gas surrounding the filaments. It is reduced to a few millimetres of mercury absolute."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following is generally used as indicators in bridges in thermal conductivity analyzers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voltmeter",
            "b) Ammeter",
            "c) Galvanometer",
            "d) Wattmeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wheatstone bridge is generally used in thermal conductivity analyzers. Themistors or hot-wires can be used as a filament."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the relationship between the density of ideal gas and its molecular weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Linear",
            "d) No relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Density of an ideal gas has a direct linear relation with the molecular weight of the gas. Density can be used to analyse gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Under which of the following conditions do all real gases behave as ideal gases to some extent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low temperature and low pressure",
            "b) Low temperature and high pressure",
            "c) High temperature and low pressure",
            "d) Room temperature and normal pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All real gases behave as ideal gases at room temperature and normal pressure. Hence, density can be used to analyse gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors are not used in analyzers based on gas density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hot wire",
            "b) Platinum filament",
            "c) Thermistor",
            "d) Thermometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermometer is not used as a detector in analyzers based on gas density. Thermistors and hot wires are generally used."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "When would the recorder indicate a zero base line in analyzers based on gas density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the detector on the sample side is cooler than that on the reference side",
            "b) When the detector on the reference side is cooler than that on the sample side",
            "c) When flow is unbalanced",
            "d) When both the detectors are equally cooled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The recorder indicates a zero base line in analyzers based on gas density when a flow is balanced. When a flow is balanced both the detectors are equally cooled."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "In analyzers based on gas density, the unbalance of the bridge is linearly proportional to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature of sample detector",
            "b) Pressure at sample detector",
            "c) Pressure difference between both the detectors",
            "d) Gas-density difference between both the detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The use of thermistor eliminates the requirement for amplification. Hence, it is generally used in analyzers based on gas density."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of the following bridges are used in analyzers based on gas density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheatstone bridge",
            "b) Kelvin’s bridge",
            "c) Anderson’s bridge",
            "d) Schering’s bridge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In analyzers based on gas density, the unbalance of the bridge is linearly proportional to a gas-density difference between both the detectors. Instruments based on the principle of gas-density balance are commercially available."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "In analyzers based on gas density, if the sample carries a gas having a higher density than the detector which of the following occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It will cause a net downward flow",
            "b) It will cause a net upward flow",
            "c) It splits into two beams",
            "d) There will be no difference in flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wheatstone bridge is generally used in analyzers based on gas density. Thermistors or hot-wires can be used as detectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the effective sample volume in analyzers based on gas density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 ml",
            "b) 20 ml",
            "c) 5 ml",
            "d) 50 ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In analyzers based on gas density, if the sample carries a gas having a higher density than the detector it will cause a net downward flow. It will obstruct flow in the lower path."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Gases emit radiation under which of the following conditions which can be used for determination of gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When mixed with other gases",
            "b) When kept at suitable temperature",
            "c) With sufficient electrical excitation and at suitable pressures",
            "d) When exposed to radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gases emit radiation with sufficient electrical excitation and at suitable pressures. Gases emit radiation in different ways. It can be in the form of spark, arc or glow discharge in different parts of the radiation spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the following measuring technique is utilized for measuring nitrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By using a method based on gas density",
            "b) By using paramagnetic analyzers",
            "c) By using magnetic wind instruments",
            "d) By using a photospectrometer where a gas sample is analysed and detected with a photocell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By using a photospectrometer gas sample is analysed, for measuring nitrogen. It is then selectively filtered by using a photocell which provides an appropriate electric signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "The characteristic emission of which colour, when discharge takes place in a low pressure chamber containing gas sample, will indicate the presence of nitrogen while using photospectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purple",
            "b) Blue",
            "c) Pink",
            "d) Green"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The characteristic emission of purple colour, when discharge takes place in a low pressure chamber containing gas sample, will indicate the presence of nitrogen while using photospectrometer. These are usually employed in medical applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Sample rates of nitrogen meter can be adjusted by doing which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By modifying the amplifier",
            "b) With the help of the needle valve",
            "c) By modifying the detector",
            "d) By changing chopper frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sample rates of nitrogen meter can be adjusted with the help of a needle valve. Modern nitrogen analyzers have digital displays."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the normal sampling rate used in nitrogen meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13 ml/min",
            "b) 33 ml/min",
            "c) 3 ml/min",
            "d) 43 ml/min"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The normal sampling rate used in nitrogen meters is 3 ml/min. Modern nitrogen analyzers have digital displays."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Nitrogen meters are calibrated for which of the following to measure nitrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixture of nitrogen and air",
            "b) Water saturated mixture of nitrogen and oxygen",
            "c) Mixture of nitrogen and hydrogen",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nitrogen meters are calibrated for water saturated mixture of nitrogen and oxygen. Hence, this calibration cannot be used for dry gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Why is nitrogen meters generally not calibrated for dry gases while measuring nitrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It causes error",
            "b) Range decreases",
            "c) Reading tend to be non-linear",
            "d) It cannot be measured"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nitrogen meters are generally not calibrated for dry gases because it will lead to error in the reading. The error will be up to 2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "In which of the following ways can nitrogen be calibrated for dry gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By modifying the amplifier",
            "b) By adjusting the needle valve",
            "c) By modifying the detector",
            "d) By changing chopper frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nitrogen can be calibrated for dry gases by adjusting the needle valve. In this way, the error will be compensated."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "In West-Gaeke colourimetric procedure, the intensity of the red purple colour is measured photometically and it is proportional to the concentration of sulphur dioxide. What is the red purple coloured compound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium tetra chloromercurate",
            "b) Dicholorosulphitomercurate complex",
            "c) Ammonia molybdate",
            "d) Paraosaniline sulphonic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Ans: d\nExplanation: Sulphur dioxide reacts with Sodium tetra chloromercurate to form Dicholorosulphitomercurate complex which then reacts with formaldehyde and pararosaniline to form Parapsaniline sulphonic acid which is red purple coloured."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": " The conductivitimetry method, involves bubbling sulphur dioxide through a solution containing sulphuric acid and which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Hydrogen peroxide",
            "c) Iodine",
            "d) Formaldehyde"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The conductivitimetry method, involves bubbling sulphur dioxide through a solution containing sulphuric acid and hydrogen peroxide. It results in the formation of sulphuric acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not the characteristics of conductivitimetry method used to measure sulphur dioxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast response",
            "b) High sensitivity",
            "c) Free from interference by other gases",
            "d) Good accuracy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conductivitimetry instruments are affected by other gases and they cause interference. The other gases may produce or remove ions in the solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not the characteristics of colorimetry method used to monitor sulphur dioxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is simple",
            "b) It has high sensitivity",
            "c) It has good specificity",
            "d) It is affected by interference from H2SO4, SO3, NH3, etc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Colorimetry method is free from by the interference due to other gases such as It is affected by interference from H2SO4, SO3, NH3, etc. Colour intensity is sensitive to temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about using gas chromatography for measuring pollutants in the air?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pollutants react rapidly in the column",
            "b) Pollutants may not be detected by the detectors",
            "c) Special column and support materials are required",
            "d) Pollutants may elude rapidly from the column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Most of the pollutants are extreme reactive materials. Hence, they may not pass through the column and appear at the detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The ability of sulphur dioxide to reduce iodine is used in which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colorimetry",
            "b) Conductivitimetry",
            "c) Coulometry",
            "d) Gas chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ability of sulphur dioxide to reduce iodine is used in Coulometry method to measure sulphur dioxide. The mass of I2 reacted per unit time will indicate the amount of sulphur dioxide."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are used as electrodes in the coulometric method for the measurement of sulphur dioxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gold",
            "b) Silver",
            "c) Platinum",
            "d) Nickel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Coulometric arrangement, the electrodes are made of platinum. These act as the anode and the cathode."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the detection limit of the coulometric method used for measurement of sulphur dioxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 ppm",
            "b) 1 ppm",
            "c) 2 ppm",
            "d) 0.01 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The detection limit of the coulometric method is 0.01 ppm. The shift in anode cathode potential is detected by a third electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Sensitivity to total sulphur by Flame-photometric detector is which of the following levels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 ppm",
            "b) 1 ppm",
            "c) 2 ppm",
            "d) 0.01 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sensitivity to total sulphur by Flame-photometric detector is 0.01 ppm. Here, sample air is introduced into a hydrogen-rich air flame."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods are not used for the measurement of sulphur dioxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colorimetric method",
            "b) Correlation spectroscopy",
            "c) Paramagnetic analyzers",
            "d) Flame-photometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sulphur di-oxide cannot be analysed using paramagnetic analyzer. This is because sulphur dioxide does not have paramagnetic property."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the wavelength of the radiation generated when an air stream containing sulphur dioxide is burned in a hydrogen-rich flame?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 243 nm",
            "b) 394 nm",
            "c) 467 nm",
            "d) 516 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wavelength of the radiation generated when an air stream containing sulphur dioxide is burned in a hydrogen-rich flame is 394 mm. A narrow band interference filter is used to shield radiations with all other wavelengths."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "In conductivitimetric method, the concentration of sulphur dioxide is proportional to which of the following parameters of the saw-tooth waveform?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average voltage",
            "b) Peak voltage",
            "c) Slope",
            "d) RMS voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unmarked block is Fluorescence chamber. Here, fluorescence of SO2 is emitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "In the conductivitimetric method, to measure the conductivity of the cell, 5V ___________ is applied across the electrodes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DC",
            "b) AC",
            "c) Pulsating DC",
            "d) DC or AC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In conductivitimetric method, the concentration of sulphur dioxide is proportional to slope of the saw-tooth waveform. Current is recorded every 15 minutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "In Saltzman method, which of the following are formed when air containing NO2 is passed in an absorbing solution consisting of the sulphanilic acid and diamine dissolved in the acetic acid medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blue colour dye complex",
            "b) Green colour dye complex",
            "c) Pink colour dye complex",
            "d) Orange colour dye complex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Saltzman method, a pink colour dye is formed when air containing NO2 is passed in an absorbing solution consisting of the sulphanilic acid and diamine dissolved in the acetic acid medium. It is sensitive in the ppm range."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "NO can be analysed by converting it into NO2 and passing it through potassium permanganate. Which of the following is the main disadvantage of this method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less accuracy",
            "b) Dye formed is unstable",
            "c) Dye formed is colourless",
            "d) Quantity of dye is low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: NO can be analysed by converting it into NO2 and passing it through potassium permanganate. The main disadvantage of this method is that the dye formed is unstable. Hence, it is not suitable for a collection of 24 hours sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "In Jacob-Hochheiser method, NO2 is passed through a dilute solution of sodium hydroxide forming the nitrite ion. The nitrite ion is reacted with sulphanilamide and ethylene diamine in which of the following to form the highly coloured azo dye?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphuric acid",
            "b) Hydrochloric acid",
            "c) Nitric acid",
            "d) Phosphoric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Jacob-Hochheiser method, NO2 is passed through a dilute solution of sodium hydroxide to form the nitrite ion. The nitrite ion is treated with sulphanilamide and ethylene diamine in phosphoric acid to form the highly coloured azo dye. Then, colorimetric analysis is done."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods results in the formation of yellow coloured compound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Griess-Saltzman method",
            "b) Phenoldisul phonoic acid method",
            "c) Chemiluminescence method",
            "d) West-Gaeke method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phenoldisul phonoic acid method results in the formation of yellow coloured compound. The intensity of the colour is measured to determine the concentration of NOx."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most common application of Chemiluminescence method used for the analysis of Nitrogen oxides?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In medical applications",
            "b) In automotive exhaust gases",
            "c) In manufacturing processes",
            "d) In chemical industries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most common application of Chemiluminescence method used for the analysis of Nitrogen oxides is to measure the amount of NO in automotive exhaust gases. Chemiluminescence occurs due to the formation of new chemical bonds."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the wavelength at which CO laser operates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.005 µm",
            "b) 5.307 µm",
            "c) 4.952 µm",
            "d) 6.179 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CO laser operates at a wavelength of 5.307 µm. It is a DC-excited continuous working laser."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The chemiluminescence reactor with ozonator is specific to which of the following compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) N2",
            "b) NO",
            "c) NO2",
            "d) N2O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CO laser is operated at liquid nitrogen temperature. It is a DC-excited continuous working laser."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "In which of the following ways can chemiluminescence occur in compounds of nitrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When NO2 returns to ground state from excited state",
            "b) When NO reacts with oxygen",
            "c) When NO reacts with ozone",
            "d) When NO2 is reduced to NO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chemiluminescence reactor with ozonator is specific to NO. Here, the sample containing NO is converted into NO2 by the ozonator."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the full scale range of Infrared spectroscopy method used for measurement of carbon monoxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-2 ppm",
            "b) 0-500 ppm",
            "c) 0-1 ppm",
            "d) 0-50 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The full scale range of Infrared spectroscopy method used for measurement of carbon monoxide is 0-50 ppm. It depends on the characteristic absorption of the CO molecule at a particular wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the full scale range of Gas chromatography method used for measurement of carbon monoxide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-200 ppm",
            "b) 0-500 ppm",
            "c) 0-1 ppm",
            "d) 0-50 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The full scale range of Gas chromatography method used for measurement of carbon monoxide is 0-200 ppm. The detector used in this method is a flame ionization detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not the characteristics of Non-dispersive infrared analyzer method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy to maintain",
            "b) High response speed",
            "c) Effect of interfering components is high",
            "d) High sensitivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Effect of interfering components is small for Non-dispersive infrared analyzer method. It depends on the characteristic absorption of the CO molecule at a particular wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Non-dispersive infrared analyzer depends on the characteristic absorption of the CO molecule at a wavelength of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.4 µm",
            "b) 4.6 µm",
            "c) 8.9 µm",
            "d) 10.8 µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Non-dispersive infrared analyzer depends on the characteristic absorption of the CO molecule at a wavelength of 4.6 µm."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "The zero of the scale is calibrated using which of the following as the sample?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air",
            "b) Water",
            "c) Inert gas",
            "d) Pure nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The zero of the scale is calibrated using pure nitrogen as the sample. Optical filters are used to minimize the effects of interfering gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "A stripper column used in gas chromatography, can be used to retain which of the following when an air sample is passed through it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO",
            "b) Methane",
            "c) Light hydrocarbons",
            "d) Heavy hydrocarbons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Non-dispersive infrared analyzer, the effect of flow rate is small. Optical filters are used to minimize the effects of interfering gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of the mixture present in the reference cell of Non-dispersive infrared analyzer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Water vapour",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A stripper column can be used to retain heavy hydrocarbons when an air sample is passed through it. It passes CO and methane into the column."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "CO analyzers based on infrared absorption would give greater sensitivity under which of the following conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With larger cell path lengths",
            "b) With smaller cell path lengths",
            "c) By changing the gases in the reference cell",
            "d) By increasing the sample flow rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reference cell contains a fixed quantity of gases. It contains CO, nitrogen and water vapour."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods cannot be used for the estimation of hydrocarbons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass spectroscopy",
            "b) Chemiluminescence method",
            "c) Ultraviolet absorption",
            "d) Gas chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemiluminescence method cannot be used for the estimation of hydrocarbons. This is because hydrocarbons do not produce chemiluminescence effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most abundant hydrocarbon which is emitted into the atmosphere by biological activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethane",
            "b) Methane",
            "c) Poly Aromatic hydrocarbons",
            "d) Pentane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most abundant hydrocarbon which is emitted into the atmosphere by biological activity is methane. It is also emitted by automobile exhausts, burning of coal, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Flame ionization detectors are sensitive to which of the following gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon dioxide",
            "b) Methane",
            "c) Carbon monoxide",
            "d) Sulphur dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flame ionization detectors are sensitive to methane since they are sensitive to organic compounds. They are insensitive to non-combustible gases. Hence, they are not sensitive to carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide and sulphur dioxide."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "How can carbon monoxide be detected using flame ionization detectors while using gas chromatography technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By converting it into carbon dioxide",
            "b) By converting it into methane",
            "c) By mixing it with combustible gases",
            "d) It cannot be detected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbon monoxide cannot be detected directly using flame ionization detectors while using gas chromatography technique. Hence, it is converted into methane and is then detected."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Which of the following organic compounds will have the highest intensity of response when introduced in a flame ionization detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methane",
            "b) Ethane",
            "c) Propane",
            "d) Butane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Butane will have the highest intensity of response when introduced in a flame ionization detector. This is because the intensity of response will be in proportion with the number of carbon atoms in the chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "In flame ionization detectors, which of the following is the range adequate for atmospheric sampling?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-1 ppm",
            "b) 0-2 ppm",
            "c) 0-20 ppm",
            "d) 0-100 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Propane would give three times the intensity of response as compared to methane. This is because the intensity of response will be in proportion with the number of carbon atoms in the chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods make use of pyrolysis while used for detecting methane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass spectroscopy",
            "b) Flame ionization detector",
            "c) Ultraviolet absorption",
            "d) Gas chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In flame ionization detectors, the range adequate for atmospheric sampling is 0-20ppm. It is useful for detecting organic compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of flame ionization detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good linearity",
            "b) Narrow range of concentration",
            "c) High sensitivity",
            "d) Fast response"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flame ionization detector makes use of pyrolysis while used for detecting methane. It is used to detect organic compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the formula for pH calculation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) log10[H+] ",
            "b) -log10[H+] ",
            "c) log2[H+] ",
            "d) -log2[H+]"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: pH is defined as the negative logarithm of hydrogen ion concentration. Hence, its formula is -log10[H+]."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Pure water is known to be which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weak electrolyte",
            "b) Strong electrolyte",
            "c) Neither weak nor strong",
            "d) Not an electrolyte"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pure water is a weak electrolyte. It dissociates to form hydrogen ions and hydroxyl ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the value of hydrogen ion concentration of pure water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1×107 moles/litre",
            "b) 1×105 moles/litre",
            "c) 1×106 moles/litre",
            "d) 1×108 moles/litre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydrogen ion concentration of pure water is 1×107 moles/litre. It can be represented as [H+]=1×107 moles/litre."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the value of hydroxyl ion concentration of pure water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1×107 moles/litre",
            "b) 1×105 moles/litre",
            "c) 1×106 moles/litre",
            "d) 1×108 moles/litre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydroxyl ion concentration of pure water is 1×107 moles/litre. It can be represented as [OH-]=1×107 moles/litre."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the relation between hydrogen and hydroxyl ion concentration of pure water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Value of hydrogen ion concentration is greater",
            "b) Value of hydroxyl ion concentration is greater",
            "c) They are both always the same",
            "d) The concentrations keep changing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In water, the value of hydrogen and hydroxyl ion concentrations are the same. It can be represented as [H+]=[OH-]."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The Nernst equation is given by which of the following statements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E=Eo + 2.303 RT/F log CH",
            "b) E=Eo – 2.303 RT/F log CH",
            "c) E=Eo + 2.303 RT×F log CH",
            "d) E=Eo – 2.303 RT×F log CH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Nernst equation is represented as, E=Eo + 2.303 RT/F log CH. it is used for measuring the potential of electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the relation between the concentration of hydrogen and hydroxyl ions in an acidic solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Value of hydrogen ion concentration is greater",
            "b) Value of hydroxyl ion concentration is greater",
            "c) They are both always the same",
            "d) The concentrations keep changing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In acidic solution, the value of hydrogen ion concentration is greater than that of hydroxyl ion concentration. It can be represented as [H+]>[OH-]."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the relation between the concentration of hydrogen and hydroxyl ions in a basic solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Value of hydrogen ion concentration is greater",
            "b) Value of hydroxyl ion concentration is greater",
            "c) They are both always the same",
            "d) The concentrations keep changing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In basic solution, the value of hydroxyl ion concentration is greater than that of hydrogen ion concentration. It can be represented as [H+]<[OH-]."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of a reference electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It must have a known output potential",
            "b) It must have a constant output potential",
            "c) Its output potential is dependent on the composition of the solution",
            "d) It is employed in conjunction with the indicator or working electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The output potential of a reference electrode must be insensitive to the composition of the solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Why is Standard hydrogen electrode called as the primary reference electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has a known output potential",
            "b) It has a constant output potential",
            "c) Its output potential is independent of the composition of the solution",
            "d) Its output potential is zero volts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Standard hydrogen electrode is called the primary reference electrode as its output potential is zero volts. It is employed in conjunction with the indicator or working electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the simple and most convenient hydrogen electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pascal Hydrogen electrode",
            "b) Bourne Hydrogen electrode",
            "c) Hilderbant Hydrogen electrode",
            "d) West Hydrogen electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hydrogen electrode given by Hilderbant is the simple and most convenient hydrogen electrode. A number of hydrogen electrodes are available."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the disadvantage of hydrogen electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Platinum can be easily poisoned",
            "b) Presence of oxidising agents alters the potential",
            "c) It gives a salt error",
            "d) H2 gas at 1 atmospheric pressure is difficult to set up and transport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrogen electrode does not give a salt error. A number of hydrogen electrodes are available."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "In Hydrogen electrode, the electrode is placed in a solution of ____ M Hcl. Fill in the blank.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Hydrogen electrode, the electrode is placed in a solution of 1M Hcl. H2 gas at 1 atm pressure is passed through the side arm in such a way that the platinum is half immersed in Hcl."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Hydrogen electrode which is the reference electrode can be used as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anode only",
            "b) Cathode only",
            "c) Anode or Cathode",
            "d) Salt bridge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrogen electrode which is the reference electrode can be used as the anode or the cathode. It depends on the half-cell to which it is coupled."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "The composition of glass membrane in glass electrode cannot have which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium silicate",
            "b) Calcium silicate",
            "c) Lithium silicate",
            "d) Barium silicate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If hydrogen electrode acts as cathode, hydrogen is reduced. If hydrogen electrode acts as anode, hydrogen is oxidised."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the purpose of added membranes in the glass membrane of the glass electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They act as tightners",
            "b) They act as filters",
            "c) They act as conditioners",
            "d) They act as collectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hydrogen at 1 atm is sent through the side tube. The electrode is placed in a solution of 1M Hcl."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot form the inner reference electrode in glass electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silver electrode",
            "b) Copper electrode",
            "c) Calomel electrode",
            "d) Silver chloride electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glass electrode consists of either sodium or calcium silicate or lithium silicates containing glass membrane. It has lanthanum and barium ions added to the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the advantage of glass electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It gives accurate results for high as well as low pH values",
            "b) It is simple to operate",
            "c) It has no salt error",
            "d) Modern electrodes can withstand severe treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ions in the added membranes act as tightners. They reduce the mobility of sodium ion."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the disadvantage of glass electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poor readings are obtained in buffered or unbuffered solutions",
            "b) The electrode must be washed thoroughly with distilled water to obtain proper results",
            "c) Materials suspended on glass should be wiped out neatly to obtain proper results",
            "d) It is affected by oxidation reduction potentials in the solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Copper electrode cannot form the inner reference electrode in glass electrodes. Inner reference electrode is immersed in a buffer solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be used as secondary reference electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calomel electrode",
            "b) Silver-silver chloride electrode",
            "c) Mercury-mercury sulphate electrode",
            "d) Glass electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glass electrode cannot be used as secondary reference electrode. It is an indicator electrode. It responds to the changes in the activity of the analyte ion."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as calomel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silver chloride",
            "b) Mercury chloride",
            "c) Potassium chloride",
            "d) Mercury sulphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mercury chloride is known as calomel. The most important general purpose secondary electrode is calomel electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "The calomel electrodes are classified based on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Materials used in the electrode",
            "b) Amount of mercury present",
            "c) Concentration of Kcl",
            "d) Purity of mercury"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Several convenient calomel electrodes are available. They are classified based on the concentration of Kcl."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the following calomel electrodes are used for accurate work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saturated calomel electrode",
            "b) Electrode with 0.1M Kcl",
            "c) Electrode with 1M Kcl",
            "d) Electrode with 2M Kcl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Calomel electrode with 0.1M Kcl is used for accurate work. Saturated calomel electrodes are easy to prepare and maintain."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Calomel electrode can behave as which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anode only",
            "b) Cathode only",
            "c) Anode or cathode",
            "d) Salt bridge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Calomel electrode can behave as anode or cathode depending upon the half cell. A salt bridge is used for coupling."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "When the calomel electrode acts as the cathode which of the following does not occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mercury ions are discharged at the electrode",
            "b) More calomel passes into the solution",
            "c) There is a decrease in the concentration of chloride ions",
            "d) There is an increase in the concentration of chloride ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When the calomel electrode acts as the cathode. When the calomel electrode acts as the cathode, mercury ions are discharged at the electrode. More calomel passes into the solution. Hence, there is an increase in the concentration of chloride ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristics of a calomel electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The potential of electrode is not temperature dependent",
            "b) Preparation of electrode is easy",
            "c) Value of potential or emf is higher for lower concentration of Kcl",
            "d) Value of potential decreases with increasing concentration of Kcl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The potential of calomel electrode is temperature dependent. When temperature changes potential comes to a new value. It cannot be used in places where high temperatures exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristics of silver/silver chloride electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) These electrodes have good electrical and chemical stability",
            "b) It can be used in temperatures greater than 600oC",
            "c) It can be used in places or solutions that have strong reducing agents",
            "d) It should not be used in solutions that contain proteins, sulphide or bromide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The silver/silver chloride electrode cannot be used in places or solutions that have strong reducing agents. They will reduce the silver ions to silver metal."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following salt bridge solutions must be used for silver/silver chloride electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saturated KCl",
            "b) Saturated K2SO4",
            "c) Saturated LiCl",
            "d) Saturated KNO3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While using reference electrodes, the internal liquid level should always be kept above that of the sample solution. This is done to prevent contamination of the electrolyte solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "In combination electrode, which of the following electrodes are built together?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary electrode, secondary reference electrode",
            "b) Primary reference electrode, glass electrode",
            "c) Glass electrode, secondary reference electrode",
            "d) Glass electrode with another glass electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In combination electrode, glass electrode and secondary reference electrode are built together. Internal reference electrode is identical with an external reference electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which of the following reference electrodes are used as internal and external reference electrodes in combination electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silver/silver chloride electrode",
            "b) Calomel electrode",
            "c) Mercury/mercury sulphate electrode",
            "d) Mercury/mercury chloride electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silver/silver chloride electrode is used as internal and external reference electrodes in combination electrodes. Internal reference electrode is identical with an external reference electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "The reference electrodes in combination electrodes are protected against light using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emerald green glass",
            "b) Ruby red glass",
            "c) Sapphire blue glass",
            "d) Pearl white glass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reference electrodes in combination electrodes are protected against light using ruby red glass. The ruby red glass absorbs light."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Combination electrodes containing the electrolyte in gel format have which of the following advantages over normal ones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple to use",
            "b) Low maintenance",
            "c) Low cost",
            "d) More accurate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Combination electrodes containing the electrolyte in gel format provide the advantage of low maintenance. They are more rugged."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the advantage of gel-filled electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low maintenance",
            "b) Rugged in construction",
            "c) Easy to maintain",
            "d) Does not cause clogging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gel-filled electrodes cause clogging. Hence, the output becomes less accurate."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Good choice for storing combination electrodes is in a buffer solution having which of the following pH?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pH1",
            "b) pH2",
            "c) pH3",
            "d) pH4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Good choice for storing combination electrodes is in a buffer solution having pH4. They can be stored in KCl solutions having particular pH values."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "The gel used in combination electrodes does not have which of the following characteristic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-toxic",
            "b) USP grade",
            "c) Inorganic material",
            "d) Polyacrylamide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gel used in combination electrodes is organic. It can also be made of polyacrylamide."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Beckman coulter gel filled combination electrodes provide which of the following features to overcome various problems that occur in gel filled electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filters",
            "b) Semi-permeable membrane",
            "c) Gas-permeable membrane",
            "d) Micro-pore junction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Beckman coulter gel filled combination electrode provides a special micro-pore junction to overcome various problems that occur in gel filled electrodes. Here, there is direct contact between the sample and the gel."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "In which of the following solutions must combination electrodes be soaked after cleaning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) KCl",
            "b) LiCl",
            "c) KNO3",
            "d) K2SO4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Combination electrodes can be soaked in KCl solution after cleaning. This will re-condition the bulb and increases its life."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "pH meters can be considered as voltage sources with which of the following internal resistances?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low resistance",
            "b) Moderate resistance",
            "c) Very high resistance",
            "d) No resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: pH meters can be considered as voltage sources with very high internal resistance. In order to eliminate errors, no current should flow from the source."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "The electrodes used in pH measurement have which of the following internal resistances?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low resistance",
            "b) Moderate resistance",
            "c) Very high resistance",
            "d) No resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electrodes used in pH measurement have very high internal resistance. It is of the order of 1000M ohm."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a failure in pH meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defective electrodes",
            "b) Defective input circuitry",
            "c) Defective electronic circuitry",
            "d) Defective calibration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Defective calibration is not a failure in pH meters. Failure occurs due to defective electrodes, defective input circuitry and defective electronic circuitry."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the simplest of pH meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Null-detector type pH meter",
            "b) Direct reading type pH meter",
            "c) Digital pH meter",
            "d) Modern pH meter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Null-detector type pH meter is the simplest of all pH meters. It is also known as the potentiometer type."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "In which of the following ways can zero drift be reduced in pH meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using filter",
            "b) Giving zero adjustment arrangement",
            "c) Keeping the input impedance high",
            "d) Using balanced and differential amplifiers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Zero drift be reduced in pH meters using balanced and differential amplifiers. Their response to external signals are additive and to internal noise are subtractive."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used to provide automatic temperature compensation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proper insulation",
            "b) Calibration for different temperatures",
            "c) Thermistor",
            "d) Thermometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To provide automatic temperature compensation, thermistors must be used. As the temperature of the solution changes, the circuit constants are altered accordingly."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of null-detector type pH meter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It can be battery operated",
            "b) It has less accuracy",
            "c) It is easy to maintain",
            "d) Its electronic circuits are simple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Null-detector type pH meter has greater accuracy than 0.01 pH. pH value is read from the calibrated precision voltage source dial."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of direct reading type pH meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple operation",
            "b) Quick to use",
            "c) Continuous indication output",
            "d) It requires balancing process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Direct reading type pH meters do not require balancing process. Its operation is simple and readings can be read directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of chopper amplifier pH meter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct voltage from the electrodes is chopped at the main frequency",
            "b) Using choppers for high-input resistance gives rise to spikes of waveforms at the output",
            "c) It leads to stability in DC output of phase-sensitive rectifier",
            "d) Magnitude of surge increases in the glass electrode output"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The use of chopper amplifier in pH meter leads to zero instability. It leads to various other problems for high-input resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "In which of the following ways can the disadvantages of chopper amplifier type pH meter be overcome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Using zero corrected DC amplifier",
            "b) Using modern design",
            "c) Using digital design",
            "d) Using vibrating condenser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The disadvantages of chopper amplifier type pH meter can be overcome using a vibrating condenser. It is used in the place of the mechanical chopper."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "In vibrating condenser amplifier type pH meter, to maintain good performance which of the following has to be done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of the vibrator should be stable",
            "b) Frequency of the vibrator should be constant",
            "c) Amplitude of the vibrator should be constant",
            "d) Both frequency and amplitude of the vibrator should be constant and stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The zero stability of vibrating condenser amplifier type pH meter is much better than a direct coupled amplifier. The capacity can be changed by vibrating one of its plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of ion selective electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is fragile",
            "b) Easy to use",
            "c) Available in different sizes and shapes",
            "d) It is insensitive to many ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ion selective electrode is rugged in construction. It is highly selective to a particular ion."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "In glass membrane electrode, the glass containing 11% Na2O, 18% Al2O3, 71% SiO2 is highly sensitive to which of the following ions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium",
            "b) Hydrogen",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Chlorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In glass membrane electrode, the glass containing 11% Na2O, 18% Al2O3, 71% SiO2 is highly sensitive to sodium ions. Glass electrodes can be used to measure various ions by changing the glass membrane composition."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "In liquid membrane electrode, the liquid ion exchanger is held in a porous disc of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid material",
            "b) Semi-permeable membrane",
            "c) Hydrophobic material",
            "d) Water absorbing material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a liquid membrane electrode, the liquid ion exchanger is held in a porous disc of hydrophobic material. It is water repelling material."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "In recent liquid membrane electrodes, the porous liquid membrane is replaced with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyvinyl chloride",
            "b) Polyacryl chloride",
            "c) Polyester membrane",
            "d) Polyacryl amide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In recent liquid membrane electrodes, the porous liquid membrane is replaced with polyvinyl chloride membrane. The measured potential is a direct measure of the concentration of specific ion."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used in potassium electrode in liquid membrane electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ionomycin",
            "b) Valinomycin",
            "c) Nonactin",
            "d) Gramicidin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Valinomycin is used in potassium electrode in liquid membrane electrodes. It is a doughnut shaped electron rich pocket."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "In solid state membranes, the body of the electrodes are made of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyvinyl chloride",
            "b) Plastic",
            "c) Polythene",
            "d) Teflon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In solid state membranes, the body of the electrodes are made of Teflon. The membrane is held in position using epoxy resin."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of ion selective electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple to use",
            "b) Inexpensive",
            "c) Narrow concentration range",
            "d) Operates in wide range of temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ion selective electrodes have a wide concentration range. It is highly selective to a particular ion."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a problem of ion selective electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interference with other ions",
            "b) Output is influences by ionic strength",
            "c) Drift in electrode potential during a sequence of measurements",
            "d) Can measure only positive ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ion selective electrode are unaffected by colour or turbidity of the solution. It operates in wide range of temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the effective concentration measured at the electrode head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selectivity coefficient",
            "b) Ionic strength",
            "c) Activity",
            "d) Activity coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ion selective electrodes can measure both positive and negative ions. It is affected by interference from other ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The value of activity coefficient is always in which of the following ranges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Less than zero",
            "c) Less than 1",
            "d) Greater than 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Activity is the effective concentration measured at the electrode head. Concentration is different from the activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of the following specifies the relation between ionic strength and activity coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) No particular relation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of activity coefficient is always less than 1. It is the ratio of activity divided by concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Ion selective electrodes have ________ linear range and _________ detection limit than the pH electrode.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower, lower",
            "b) Lower, higher",
            "c) Higher, lower",
            "d) Higher, higher"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Activity co-efficient and ionic strength are inversely proportional to each other. If the ionic strength increases, the value of activity decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "In Ammonia electrode, diffusion of dissolved ammonia occurs through the membrane until which of the following conditions occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration becomes equal on both sides",
            "b) Activity becomes equal on both sides",
            "c) Partial pressure becomes equal on both sides",
            "d) Differential pressure is low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Ammonia electrode, diffusion of dissolved ammonia occurs through the membrane until partial pressure becomes equal on both sides. Partial pressure is proportional to its concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "When electrode potential response is plotted as a function of ammonia concentration on a semi-log graph, the graph obtained will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A straight line",
            "b) Parabolic",
            "c) Sigmoidal",
            "d) A curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When electrode potential response is plotted as a function of ammonia concentration, the graph obtained will be a straight line. The slope will be about 58mV per decade."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "How can samples above 1M in ammonia concentration be measured using ammonia electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It must be diluted and measured",
            "b) It cannot be measured",
            "c) The electrode has to be modified for measuring",
            "d) It can be measured directly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Samples above 1M in ammonia concentration be measured by diluting the solution. Samples having concentrations below that can be measured directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The dilution of solution must not reduce the level of ammonia below _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-2 M",
            "b) 10-5 M",
            "c) 10-8 M",
            "d) 10-9 M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dilution of solution must not reduce the level of ammonia below 10-5 M. The total level of dissolved species must be below 1M."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors does not the reproducibility of the ammonia electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Drift",
            "c) Noise",
            "d) Dilution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dilution does not affect reproducibility. The other three factors affect reproducibility."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "In fluoride ion electrode, the potential corresponding to level of the fluoride ion is described by which of the following equations when E is the measured electrode potential, Eo is the reference potential and A is the level of fluoride ions in solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E=Eo+0.0591 log A",
            "b) E=Eo-0.0591 log A",
            "c) E=Eo+0.0896 log A",
            "d) E=Eo-0.0896 log A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The performance of ammonia electrode is not affected by sample colour and turbidity. Temperature affects its output."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "What does TISAB which is used to overcome interferences stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total Isolation Strength Absolute Buffer",
            "b) Total Ionic Strength Absolute Buffer",
            "c) Total Ionic Strength Adjustment Buffer",
            "d) Total Isolation Strength Adjustment Buffer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In fluoride ion electrode, the potential corresponding to level of the fluoride ion is described by the equation, E=Eo-0.0591 log A. A is the activity or effective concentration of fluoride ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes main interference in Fluoride electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H+ ions",
            "b) OH– ions",
            "c) Li+ ions",
            "d) Cl– ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TISAB stands for ‘Total Ionic Strength Adjustment Buffer’. It is added in excess and in exactly the same amount to each of the solutions that is to be measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Crystal membrane of ion selective electrode can be regenerated by washing with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Iodine solution",
            "c) Acidic solution",
            "d) Basic solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The main interference in fluoride ions is caused by OH– ions. It has excellent selectivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of the following gas permeable membrane is used for ammonia gas sensing electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon rubber",
            "b) Microporous Teflon membrane",
            "c) Fluorocarbon",
            "d) Polythene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gas permeable membrane used for ammonia sensing electrode is fluorocarbon membrane. For each gas different membranes are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which of the following gas permeable membrane is used for carbon dioxide gas sensing electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon rubber",
            "b) PVC membrane",
            "c) Fluorocarbon",
            "d) Polythene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gas permeable membrane used for carbon dioxide sensing electrode is silicon rubber membrane. For each gas different membranes are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following reference electrode is placed in the solution of carbon dioxide electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calomel electrode",
            "b) Silver/silver chloride electrode",
            "c) Mercury/mercury sulphate electrode",
            "d) Glass electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The response time of the biocatalytic membrane electrode is good even when used with complex organic molecules. But, the membrane is costly."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Biocatalytic membrane electrode cannot be used for the measurement of which of the following gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ammonia",
            "b) Carbon dioxide",
            "c) Hydrogen",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A silver/silver chloride reference electrode is placed in the solution. A glass electrode is also placed in the solution but it is not a reference electrode."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "The biocatalytic membrane used in the ammonia selective electrode is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urea",
            "b) Urease",
            "c) Acrylamide",
            "d) Polyacrylamide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Biocatalytic membranes cannot be used for the measurement of nitrogen. It can be used for the measurement of other three gases."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are used as a gel to which biocatalytic membrane is fixed in ammonia selective electrode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urea",
            "b) Urease",
            "c) Acrylamide",
            "d) Polyacrylamide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The biocatalytic membrane used in the ammonia selective electrode is urease. It is used for the detection of ammonia."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "The biocatalytic membrane is attached to the glass electrode using which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nylon mesh",
            "b) Teflon",
            "c) Silicon rubber",
            "d) Polythene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The material used as a gel to which biocatalytic membrane is fixed in ammonia selective electrode is acrylamide. This is attached to the ion selective electrode directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "In carbon dioxide electrode, the membrane separates which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium carbonate, magnesium chloride",
            "b) Magnesium hydrogen carbonate, sodium chloride",
            "c) Sodium hydrogen carbonate, sodium chloride",
            "d) Magnesium carbonate, magnesium chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The biocatalytic membrane is attached to the glass electrode using nylon mesh. Cellophane film can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "If a solid or liquid membrane is placed in pure water, the membrane dissolves slightly, producing an equilibrium concentration of the measured ion. This is represented as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A constant, Eo",
            "b) Activity",
            "c) Blank correction, Cb",
            "d) Concentration of standard solution, Cs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If a solid or liquid membrane is placed in pure water, the membrane dissolves slightly, producing an equilibrium concentration of the measured ion. This is represented as a blank correction, Cb. This is the constant background for all measurements."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "During which of the following conditions is the blank correction not necessary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If sample concentration rises in linear response region",
            "b) If sample concentration falls in linear response region",
            "c) If sample concentration rises in non-linear response region",
            "d) If sample concentration falls in non-linear response region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The blank correction is not necessary if sample concentration falls in the linear response region. This is the constant background for all measurements."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "During which of the following conditions is the blank correction necessary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If sample concentration rises in linear response region",
            "b) If sample concentration falls in linear response region",
            "c) If sample concentration rises in non-linear response region",
            "d) If sample concentration falls in non-linear response region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The blank correction is necessary if sample concentration falls in non-linear response region. This is the constant background for all measurements."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Ion analysers need calibration once in which of the following durations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Every two or three hours",
            "b) Every nine or ten hours",
            "c) Every 24 hours",
            "d) Every 48 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ion analysers need calibration every two or three hours. Temperature affects the output."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "In ion analysers, which of the following serve the dual purpose of controlling the operating current of FET and providing current gain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FET itself does it",
            "b) SCR",
            "c) Op-amp",
            "d) Diode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ion analysers, op-amp serves the dual purpose of controlling the operating current of FET and providing current gain. Two FETs are operated as source followers."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "The presence of dirt or moisture degrades which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circuit components",
            "b) High input impedance of buffer amplifier",
            "c) Low input impedance of buffer amplifier",
            "d) Low output impedance of buffer amplifier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The presence of dirt or moisture degrades the high input impedance of the buffer amplifier. Solder flux may also degrade it."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of ground in ion analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chassis and electrostatic ground",
            "b) Digital ground",
            "c) Analog ground",
            "d) Reference ground"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There is no such point as a reference ground. Three types of grounding are provided which are chassis and electrostatic ground, digital ground and analog ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the only operator entry required in PC-based ion analysers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardware set-up",
            "b) Signal measurement",
            "c) Calibration",
            "d) Sample calculation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The timing for a microprocessor and for all signals is generated by the CPU clock. A crystal may be present to provide clock signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of the immobilized enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They cannot be re-used",
            "b) It produces reproducible results",
            "c) Stability exists",
            "d) Same catalytic activity is present for number of analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Immobilized enzymes can be reused. This ensures that the same catalytic activity is present for a number of analyses."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the physico-chemical component?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzymes",
            "b) Anti-bodies",
            "c) Transducer",
            "d) Cells or tissues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transducer is referred to as the physico-chemical component. Enzymes and anti-bodies are biological components."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "An example of biosensor, urea electrode makes use of which of the following electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon dioxide electrode",
            "b) Ammonia electrode",
            "c) Fluoride electrode",
            "d) Ammonium electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An example of biosensor, urea electrode makes use of the ammonium electrode. A urease membrane is also present."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "In glucose electrode, glucose oxidase has been coupled to an electrode by which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ferrocene derivatives",
            "b) Urease",
            "c) Polyacrylamide",
            "d) Biochips"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In glucose electrode, glucose oxidase has been coupled to an electrode by using ferrocene derivatives. It is used to measure blood glucose in diabetic patients."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Biosensors measure glucose concentrations between which of the following ranges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-1 to 10-2 M",
            "b) 10-2 to 10-4 M",
            "c) 10-1 to 10-4 M",
            "d) 10-1 to 10-7 M"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Biosensors measure glucose concentrations between 10-1 to 10-7 M. It is linear in the range of 10-2 to 10-4 M."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Transducers employed in the bulk of enzyme electrodes use which of the following principles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amperometric",
            "b) Optical",
            "c) Magnetic",
            "d) Colorimetric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transducers employed in the bulk of enzyme electrodes use amperometric principle. It may also use the potentiometric principle."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Which of these biosensors use the principle of heat released or absorbed by a reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Potentiometric biosensor",
            "b) Optical biosensors",
            "c) Piezo-electric biosensors",
            "d) Calorimetric biosensors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Calorimetric biosensors use the principle of heat released or absorbed by a reaction. The heat is measured to determine the concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of the following biosensors use the movement of electrons produced during redox reactions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amperometric biosensor",
            "b) Potentiometric biosensors",
            "c) Piezo-electric biosensors",
            "d) Optical biosensors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Amperometric biosensor uses the movement of electrons produced during redox reactions. Redox reactions involve both reduction and oxidation."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "For constructing the glucose sensor, which of the following is used as a gel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Urea",
            "b) Urease",
            "c) Acrylamide",
            "d) Polyacrylamide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nanoscopic optical biosensors have a fast response. They also have excellent biochemical sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of the following transducers must be used for dissolved oxygen analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Potentiometric",
            "b) Polarographic",
            "c) Ion-selective electrode",
            "d) Optical transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polarographic transducer must be used for dissolved oxygen analyser. Dissolved oxygen is the measure of ability of water to sustain aquatic life."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "How does solubility of oxygen in water change with respect to temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It decreases with increase in temperature",
            "b) It increases with increase in temperature",
            "c) It decreases with decrease in temperature",
            "d) It does not depend on temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Solubility of oxygen in water decreases with increase in temperature. Dissolved oxygen is the measure of ability of water to sustain aquatic life."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "The water to be analysed flows into the condenser through which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filter",
            "b) Semi-permeable membrane",
            "c) Throttling device",
            "d) Platinum filament"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The water to be analysed flows into the condenser through a throttling device. It is cooled in the condenser."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the function of the throttling device?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filtering",
            "b) Maintains pH of a water",
            "c) Purifies water",
            "d) Maintains constant flow rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The function of the throttling device is to maintain a constant flow rate. The water then passes into the condenser."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Which of the following section plays a major role in maintaining the accuracy of the dissolved oxygen analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analysing section",
            "b) Inlet section",
            "c) Transmitting section",
            "d) Condensing section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transmitting section plays a major role in maintaining the accuracy of the dissolved oxygen analyser. It is the section after the analysing section."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Which of the following bridges are used in dissolved oxygen analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kelvin’s bridge",
            "b) Wheatstone bridge",
            "c) Schering’s bridge",
            "d) Anderson’s bridge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wheatstone bridge is used in dissolved oxygen analyser. Initially, the bridge is in a balanced condition."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "In dissolved oxygen analyser, the electrometer consists of which of the following solutions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium hydroxide solution",
            "b) Magnesium hydroxide solution",
            "c) Potassium hydroxide solution",
            "d) Calcium oxide solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In dissolved oxygen analyser, the electrometer consists of potassium hydroxide solution. It produces hydrogen due to the electrolysis process."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The dissolved oxygen analyser is based on which of the following meters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amperometer",
            "b) Katharometer",
            "c) pH meter",
            "d) Voltmeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dissolved oxygen analyser is based on katharometer. It works on the principle of thermal conductivity detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Oxygen content can be controlled by adding which of the following materials with water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acidic solution",
            "b) Basic solution",
            "c) Iodine",
            "d) Hydrazine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Oxygen content can be controlled by adding hydrazine with water. It is important to maintain dissolved oxygen content in boilers to reduce corrosion."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "Which of the following indicate leakages in a condenser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The concentration of sodium in steam and condensate are very high",
            "b) The concentration of sodium in steam and condensate are very low",
            "c) The concentration of sodium in steam and condensate are equal",
            "d) The concentration of sodium in steam and condensate are not equal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the concentration of sodium in steam and condensate are not equal, it means that leakage is present in the condenser. If the values are equal, then it means that no leakage is present."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following are added for pH adjustment in sodium analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acidic solution",
            "b) Basic solution",
            "c) Hydrazine",
            "d) Ammonia buffer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ammonia buffer is added for pH adjustment in sodium analyser. This is added to the reference and sample solutions."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Normally, electrodes measure which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activity",
            "b) Activity co-efficient",
            "c) Blank constant",
            "d) Ionic co-efficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Normally, electrodes measure activity of the ion. It is a measure of free ions in the solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Which of the following represent the concentration of a solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only free ions",
            "b) Only bound ions",
            "c) Free ions and bound ions",
            "d) Either free ions or bound ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concentration refers to the sum of free ions and bound ions. Activity refers only to free ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Sodium selective electrode provides a good response in measurement when the pH is above which of the following values?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sodium selective electrode provides a good response in measurement when the pH of the solution is above 10. Hence, the buffer solution is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "Which of the following are used to free bound ions or liberate bound ions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colouring agents",
            "b) Ammonia Buffer",
            "c) Reagents",
            "d) Iodine solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reagents are used to free bound ions or liberate bound ions. The addition of reagent prevents unwanted ions from entering into the measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "In which part of the apparatus is the reference and ion selective electrodes placed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Head tank",
            "b) Flow cell",
            "c) Reservoir",
            "d) Solenoid valve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reference and ion selective electrodes are placed in the flow cell. Sample is maintained in the constant head tank."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "The output of the electrode in sodium analyser is proportional to which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activity",
            "b) Concentration",
            "c) Negative logarithm of sodium ion concentration",
            "d) Logarithm of sodium ion concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output of the electrode in sodium analyser is proportional to the logarithm of sodium ion concentration. The value is recorded and indicated."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of the following principles are used in silica analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amperometric principle",
            "b) Colorimetric principle",
            "c) Coulometric principle",
            "d) Magnetic principle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The principle used in silica analyser is colorimetric principle. The colour of the final solution is measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not added to the sample during analysis during silica analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ammonium Molybdate",
            "b) Sulphuric acid",
            "c) Reducing solution",
            "d) Iodine solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Iodine solution is not added to the sample during analysis. Ammonium molybdate, sulphuric acid and reducing solution are added to the sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors are used in silica analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photovoltaic cell",
            "b) Photo multiplier",
            "c) Photo emissive tubes",
            "d) Flame emission detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photovoltaic cell is used as a detector in silica analyser. This detector does not need a battery for operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The output from both the detectors is given to which of the following devices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filters",
            "b) Microprocessor",
            "c) Recorder",
            "d) Differential Amplifier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The output from both the detectors is given to the differential amplifier. The amplified signal is read through a display."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "If the differential amplifier gives zero as output then it infers which of the following (Reference output is given to the positive terminal and sample output is given to the negative terminal)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The concentration of silica in sample and reference solution is equal",
            "b) The concentration of silica in a reference solution is more than that in the sample solution",
            "c) The concentration of silica in sample solution is more than that in the reference solution",
            "d) Further processing is required to come to any conclusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the differential amplifier gives zero as output then, it means that the concentration of silica in sample and reference solution is equal. It means that the photodetectors’ output is equal."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "If the differential amplifier gives a positive output then it infers which of the following (Reference output is given to the positive terminal and sample output is given to the negative terminal)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The concentration of silica in sample and reference solution is equal",
            "b) The concentration of silica in a reference solution is more than that in the sample solution",
            "c) The concentration of silica in sample solution is more than that in the reference solution",
            "d) Further processing is required to come to any conclusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the differential amplifier gives a positive output then, it means that the concentration of silica in sample solution is more than that in the reference solution. It means that the photodetectors’ output is not equal."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "If the differential amplifier gives a negative output then it infers which of the following (Reference output is given to the positive terminal and sample output is given to the negative terminal)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The concentration of silica in sample and reference solution is equal",
            "b) The concentration of silica in a reference solution is more than that in the sample solution",
            "c) The concentration of silica in sample solution is more than that in the reference solution",
            "d) Further processing is required to come to any conclusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the differential amplifier gives a negative output then, it means that the concentration of silica in a reference solution is more than that in the sample solution. It means that the photodetector’s output is not equal."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements are true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More light is absorbed if the silica content is high in a solution",
            "b) More light is transmitted if the silica content is high in a solution",
            "c) Less light is absorbed if the silica content is high in a solution",
            "d) More light is absorbed if the silica content is low in a solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: More amount of light is absorbed if the silica content is high in a solution. Less amount of light is transmitted if the silica content is high in a solution."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "How will the photodetector output be if silica content is high in a solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The output will be high",
            "b) The output will be low",
            "c) The output will be zero",
            "d) Output cannot be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If silica content is high in a solution, the detector output will be low. This is because more light is absorbed by the solution and less amount of light is transmitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "What will be the final colour of the solution obtained during silica analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pink",
            "b) Red",
            "c) Blue",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This method works on the principle of molybdenum blue method. Hence, the colour of the final solution will be blue."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which of the following are highly effective in producing ion pairs when they pass through the matter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha particles",
            "b) Beta particles",
            "c) Gamma particles",
            "d) X-ray particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alpha particles are highly effective in producing ion pairs when they pass through the matter. They have relatively large mass and charge."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following can liberate photo electrons when they fall on certain metals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha particles",
            "b) Beta particles",
            "c) Gamma particles",
            "d) X-ray particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: X-rays can liberate photo electrons when they fall on certain metals. They penetrate through certain substances that are opaque to ordinary light."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Which of these particles are highly penetrating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha particles",
            "b) Beta particles",
            "c) Gamma particles",
            "d) X-ray particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gamma particles are highly penetrating. Upon interaction with matter, they lose energy in three modes."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a mode by which beta particles lose energy on interaction with matter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photoelectric effect",
            "b) Compton effect",
            "c) Pair production",
            "d) Collision effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alpha emission is characteristic of heavier radioactive elements such as thorium, uranium, etc. They are most harmful to human tissue."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The stability of the nucleus can be predicted by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron to neutron ratio",
            "b) Neutron to proton ratio",
            "c) Proton to electron ratio",
            "d) Neutron to electron ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Upon interaction with matter, gamma rays lose energy in three modes. They are photoelectric effect, pair production and Compton Effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about radiochemical methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eliminate the need for chemical preparation",
            "b) Not sensitive",
            "c) Not accurate",
            "d) Not specific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stability of the nucleus can be predicted by neutron to proton ratio. The number of protons will always be equal to the number of electrons."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Which of the following formulae gives the expression for half-life of a radioactive isotope when ‘λ’ is the decay constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.762/λ",
            "b) 0.693/λ",
            "c) 0.937/λ",
            "d) 0.258/λ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radiochemical methods eliminate the need for chemical preparation. In other methods, chemical preparation has to be done before the measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Which of the following emissions have low ionizing power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alpha particles",
            "b) Beta particles",
            "c) Gamma particles",
            "d) X-ray particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The formula to calculate half-life of a radioactive isotope is 0.693/λ. It is the time required for half the initial stock of atoms to decay."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following effect occurs when a gamma ray and an electron make an elastic collision?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photoelectric effect",
            "b) Compton effect",
            "c) Pair production",
            "d) Collision effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gamma particle emissions have low ionizing power. They also have high penetrating power."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which of the following effects transfers all the energy of the gamma ray to an electron in the inner orbit of the atom of the absorber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photoelectric effect",
            "b) Compton effect",
            "c) Pair production",
            "d) Collision effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Upon interaction with matter, gamma rays lose energy in three modes. Compton effect occurs when a gamma ray and an electron make an elastic collision."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of radiation detectors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geiger Muller counter",
            "b) Proportional counter",
            "c) Semiconductor detector",
            "d) Flame emission detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flame emission detector is not a type of radiation detector. Radiation can be detected by several methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "‘When nuclear radiations pass through, gas ionization is produced.’ This is the principle of which of the following detectors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proportional counter",
            "b) Flow counter",
            "c) Geiger Muller counter",
            "d) Scintillation counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ‘When nuclear radiations pass through, gas ionization is produced.’ This is the principle of which of Geiger Muller counter. It is used to measure the intensity of radioactive radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as quenching gas in Geiger Muller counter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Argon gas",
            "c) Krypton",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alcohol acts as quenching gas in Geiger Muller counter. It is present in a gas tight envelope along with the electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as ionising gas in Geiger Muller counter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Argon gas",
            "c) Krypton",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Argon gas acts as ionising gas in Geiger Muller counter. It is present in a gas type envelope along with the electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Which of the detectors is similar to Geiger Muller counter in construction but is filled with heavier gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proportional counter",
            "b) Flow counter",
            "c) Semiconductor detector",
            "d) Scintillation counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Proportional counter is similar to Geiger Muller counter in construction but is filled with heavier gas. The output is proportional to the intensity of radiation incident on it."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases are used in the proportional counter as the ionising gas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Argon gas",
            "c) Krypton",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Proportional counter is filled with krypton. It acts as ionising gas. Xenon can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the main disadvantage of solid state semiconductor detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low accuracy",
            "b) Low sensitivity",
            "c) It should be maintained at low temperature",
            "d) High pressure has to be produced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main disadvantage of solid state semiconductor detector is that it must be maintained at low temperature. This is necessary to reduce noise and to prevent deterioration of detector characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Scintillation detector is a large flat crystal of which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium chloride",
            "b) Sodium iodide",
            "c) Sodium sulphate",
            "d) Sodium carbonate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Scintillation detector is a large flat crystal of sodium iodide. It is coated with thallium doping."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials are used as the insulation between the inner and outer electrodes of the ion chamber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polythene",
            "b) Plastic",
            "c) Polytetrafluoroethylene",
            "d) Polyacrylamide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When X-ray enters the solid state detector it produces electron-hole pair rather than an ion pair. The output signal is taken from an aluminium layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Liquid samples must be counted using ionization chamber by placing them in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test tube",
            "b) Curvette",
            "c) Ampoules",
            "d) Flask"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polytetrafluoroethylene is used as the insulation between the inner and outer electrodes of the ion chamber. The material has very high resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Liquid Scintillators are used for which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low energy beta materials",
            "b) High energy beta materials",
            "c) Low energy gamma materials",
            "d) High energy gamma materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Liquid samples must be counted using ionization chamber by placing them in ampoules. The ampoules are placed in the chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "The first gamma camera is also known by which of the following names?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hal camera",
            "b) Anger camera",
            "c) Muller camera",
            "d) West camera"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first gamma camera is also known as an Anger camera. It was developed by Hal Anger."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of gamma camera?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Detector crystal",
            "c) Pre-amplifier",
            "d) Position logic circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pre-amplifier is not a component of the gamma camera. It is an imaging device commonly used in medical applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first object that an emitted gamma photon encounters after exciting the body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Detector crystal",
            "c) Photo multiplier tubes",
            "d) Position logic circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Collimator is the first object that an emitted gamma photon encounters after exciting the body. In the conventional method, the collimator is placed over the detector crystal."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a pattern of holes through gamma ray absorbing material, usually lead or tungsten?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Detector crystal",
            "c) Photo multiplier tubes",
            "d) Position circuitry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Collimator is a pattern of holes through gamma ray absorbing material, usually lead or tungsten. In the conventional method, the collimator is placed over the detector crystal."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "When the energy of an absorbed gamma photon is released, a flash of light is produced. This is similar to which of the following effects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photoelectric effect",
            "b) Compton effect",
            "c) Pair production",
            "d) Collision effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given effect is similar to the photoelectric effect. It occurs in a scintillation detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Which of the following components adds all the signals and determines where each scintillation event occurred in the detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Detector crystal",
            "c) Photo multiplier tubes",
            "d) Position circuitry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Position circuitry adds all the signals and determines where each scintillation event occurred in the detector. It is an electronic circuit and it receives all the signals from photo multiplier tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "Gamma camera uses which of these components to produce a position intensity picture of a radioactive area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Scintillation detector",
            "c) Photo multiplier tubes",
            "d) Position circuitry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gamma camera uses multiple scintillation detectors. Hence, it is also known as scintillation camera."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as a scintillation counter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scintillator",
            "b) Scintillator along with a photo multiplier tube",
            "c) Scintillator along with the crystal",
            "d) Scintillator along with position circuitry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gamma camera uses a scintillation detector to produce a position intensity picture of a radioactive area. It is an imaging device commonly used in medical applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "In liquid scintillation counter, which of the following is a fluorescent substance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solvent",
            "b) Solute",
            "c) Crystal",
            "d) Reagent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In liquid scintillation counter, a mixture of solvent and solute is used. The solute is a fluorescent substance."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "When UV light is absorbed by the fluor molecules the light emitted is in which of the following colours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pink",
            "b) Red",
            "c) Green",
            "d) Blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When UV light is absorbed by the fluor molecules the light emitted is in blue colour. Light is emitted when the molecules return to the ground state."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "In liquid scintillation counter, which of the following is used to convert light into electrical signals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photo multiplier tube",
            "b) Photo emissive tube",
            "c) Photo voltaic cell",
            "d) Photo reflector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The photo multiplier tube converts light into electrical signals in a liquid scintillation counter. Two photo multiplier tubes are used in the liquid scintillation counter."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "The reduction in counting efficiency of the scintillation detector is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disintegration",
            "b) Decay",
            "c) Quenching",
            "d) Reduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reduction in counting efficiency of the scintillation detector is called as quenching. Substances added to the counting vial can reduce efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of quenching?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical quench",
            "b) Interference quench",
            "c) Colour quenching",
            "d) Self-absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are three types of quenching. Interference quench is not a type of quenching."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "In which type of quenching, the radiation emitted by the isotope is not detected due to absorption of the radiation by the sample itself?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical quench",
            "b) Interference quench",
            "c) Colour quenching",
            "d) Self-absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In self-absorption, the radiation emitted by the isotope is not detected due to the absorption of the radiation by the sample itself. It may occur due to precipitates."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Due to the presence of red, green and yellow colour in the vial, which of the following occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical quench",
            "b) Interference quench",
            "c) Colour quenching",
            "d) Self-absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Variation of gain with temperature causes instability. There are various other factors that cause instability."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "A quench curve can be constructed by plotting the counting efficiency versus ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q-number",
            "b) Quench factor",
            "c) H-number",
            "d) Disintegrations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Scintillators emit light in the blue region of the spectrum. Due to the presence of other colours, colour quenching may occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "A discriminator circuit is which of the following circuits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheatstone bridge",
            "b) Instrumentation amplifier",
            "c) Astable multivibrator",
            "d) Schmitt trigger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A discriminator circuit is a Schmitt trigger circuit. There are two discriminator circuits in pulse height analyser."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the function of the discriminator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rejects signals below a certain voltage",
            "b) Rejects signals above a certain voltage",
            "c) Rejects signal in a range alone",
            "d) Filters noise alone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The discriminator can be set to reject signals below a certain voltage. This is required for excluding scattered radiation and noise."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "The difference between the pulses having amplitudes between the two triggering levels is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse width",
            "b) Energy gap",
            "c) Window width",
            "d) Amplitude variation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The difference between the pulses having amplitudes between the two triggering levels is called as window width. It is also called the channel width."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "The pulses having amplitudes between the two triggering levels are given by which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-amplifiers",
            "b) Linear amplifiers",
            "c) Anti-coincidence circuits",
            "d) Discriminators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pulses having amplitudes between the two triggering levels are given by discriminators. There are two discriminators."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Schmitt triggers are followed by which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-amplifier",
            "b) Linear amplifier",
            "c) Anti-coincidence circuit",
            "d) Discriminator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Schmitt triggers are followed by anti-coincidence circuits. The output of the anti-coincidence circuit is given to counters."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of the following components cancels all the pulses which trigger both the discriminators?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-amplifier",
            "b) Linear amplifier",
            "c) Anti-coincidence circuit",
            "d) Discriminator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Anti-coincidence circuit cancels all the pulses which trigger both the discriminators. The output of the anti-coincidence circuit is given to counters."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used when the number of channels is ten or less?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two discriminators in series",
            "b) Two discriminators in parallel",
            "c) Series array of discriminators",
            "d) Parallel array of discriminators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Parallel array of discriminators are used when the number of channels is ten or less. If the number is more than ten this is not preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The signal reaching which of the following components is the one lying in the window of pulse height analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-amplifier",
            "b) Linear amplifier",
            "c) Counter",
            "d) Discriminator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If number of channels is more than ten, the problems of stability of discrimination voltages arise. Problems also arise with an increase of adequate differential non-linearity."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "In X-ray spectrometers, the specimen or the sample is placed after which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X-ray tube",
            "b) Monochromator",
            "c) Collimator",
            "d) Detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In X-ray spectrometers, the specimen or the sample is placed after the X-ray tube. The X-ray tube is the source of the X-ray."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Which of the following components are used to generate X-rays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meyer tube",
            "b) West tube",
            "c) Anger tube",
            "d) Coolidge tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Coolidge tube is used to generate X-rays. It the source of X-rays. Coolidge tube requires stabilised current and high voltage."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Using which of the following components is the generated x-rays focussed upon the specimen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X-ray tube",
            "b) Monochromator",
            "c) Collimator",
            "d) Detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Collimator is used to focus the generated x-rays upon the specimen. The collimator is in between the specimen under analysis and the Coolidge tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "The cathode in the Coolidge tube is made of which of the following elements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quartz",
            "b) Iron",
            "c) Tungsten",
            "d) Barium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cathode in the Coolidge tube is made of tungsten. The anode is made of copper."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a target metal used in the Coolidge tube?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodium",
            "b) Cobalt",
            "c) Gold",
            "d) Silver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The anode in the Coolidge tube is kept in an inclined manner. The anode is made of copper."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "How can the resolution of the collimator be increased?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By reducing the separation between the metal plates of the collimator",
            "b) By increasing the separation between the metal plates of the collimator",
            "c) By increasing the number of metal plates",
            "d) By decreasing the number of metal plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gold is not used as a target metal in the Coolidge tube. The other target metals are copper, molybdenum and chromium."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "When x-rays emitted from molybdenum are allowed to pass through a zirconium filter, which of the following occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It absorbs radiation of shorter wavelength",
            "b) It absorbs radiation of longer wavelength",
            "c) It allows radiation of shorter wavelength to pass through",
            "d) It allows radiation in a particular band to pass through"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resolution of the collimator can be increased by reducing the separation between the metal plates of the collimator. Collimator has a series of closely spaced parallel metal plates."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "Which of the following crystals are not suited for x-ray grating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topaz",
            "b) Lithium fluoride",
            "c) Calcium fluoride",
            "d) Sodium fluoride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When x-rays emitted from molybdenum are allowed to pass through a zirconium filter, it absorbs radiation of shorter wavelength. It allows radiation of a stronger wavelength to pass through."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "The x-rays generated come out of the Coolidge tube through which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beryllium window",
            "b) Tungsten window",
            "c) Collimator",
            "d) Target material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When compared to filters, monochromators provide much signal to noise ratio. Monochromators are used for removal of unwanted wavelengths."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "X-ray diffractometers are not used to identify the physical properties of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metals",
            "b) Liquids",
            "c) Polymeric materials",
            "d) Solids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: X-ray diffractometers are not used to identify the physical properties of liquids. It is used to identify the physical properties of metals, solids and polymeric materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "X-ray diffractometers provide ____________ information about the compounds present in a solid sample.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantitative",
            "b) Qualitative",
            "c) Quantitative and qualitative",
            "d) Either quantitative or qualitative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: X-ray diffractometers provide quantitative and qualitative information about the compounds present in a solid sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Using the powder method of diffractometers, which of the following can be determined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Percentage of K+",
            "b) Percentage of Na+ and Cl-",
            "c) Percentage of KBr and NaCl",
            "d) Percentage of Br-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Using the powder method of diffractometers, percentage of KBr and NaCl can be determined. Other analytical methods provide the only percentage of K+, Na+, Cl- and Br-."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "In powder method, the powder sample is contained in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin walled glass capillary tubes",
            "b) Thin walled test tube",
            "c) Thin walled curvettes",
            "d) Thin walled flask"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In powder method, the powder sample is contained in thin walled glass capillary tubes. Thin walled cellophane capillary tubes can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most common instrument for photographic recording of diffraction patterns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Debye-Scherrer powder camera",
            "b) Gamma camera",
            "c) Geiger tube",
            "d) Scintillation counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diffracted x-ray beam can be detected photographically or by using a scintillation counter or Geiger tube. Debye-Scherrer powder camera is the most common instrument for photographic recording of diffraction patterns."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "With the help of which of the following equations is the distance calculated from a known wavelength of the source and measured angle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coolidge equation",
            "b) Bragg’s equation",
            "c) Debye equation",
            "d) Scherrer equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distance is calculated from a known wavelength of the source and measured angle using Bragg’ equation. The diffracted angle is calculated by the spacing between a particular set of plane."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "In Diffractometer, the identification of a component of the sample from its powder diffraction pattern is based upon the _________ of lines and their relative ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number, length",
            "b) Number, intensity",
            "c) Position, length",
            "d) Position, intensity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The identification of a component of the from its powder diffraction pattern is based upon the position of lines and their relative intensities. Diffractometers are used for powder diffraction."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Diffractometers are similar to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optical grating spectrometer",
            "b) Prism spectrometer",
            "c) Photo multiplier",
            "d) Photovoltaic cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When certain geometric requirements are met, X-rays scattered from a crystalline solid can constructively interfere with each other and produce a diffracted beam. The relationship among different factors is given by Bragg’s law."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "In Diffractometers, line intensities depend on ______ and kind of atomic reflection centres in each set of plates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number",
            "b) Position",
            "c) Length",
            "d) Distance between lines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Diffractometers are similar to optical grating spectrometers. The differences are that lenses and mirrors are not used with X-rays."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "In powder diffractometer, the sharpness of the lines is greatly determined by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quality of the sample, size of the slit",
            "b) Quality of the slit, size of the sample",
            "c) Thickness of the slit, amount of the sample",
            "d) Number of slits, composition of the sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Diffractometers, line intensities depend on number and kind of atomic reflection centres in each set of plates. Diffraction is a wave property of electromagnetic radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Absorption meter is __________ and ____________ of the chemical state of the element concerned.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-destructive, independent",
            "b) Destructive, independent",
            "c) Non-destructive, dependent",
            "d) Destructive, dependent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Absorption meters give information about the absorbing material. It is non-destructive and independent of the chemical state of the element concerned."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "X-ray absorption meters have which of the following major disadvantages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low accuracy",
            "b) Low range",
            "c) Low sensitivity",
            "d) It is destructive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Absorption meters give information about the absorbing material. X-ray absorption meters have low sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "In absorption meter, which of the following is placed between the cell and the X-ray tube?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Filter",
            "c) Chopper",
            "d) Attenuator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The applications of X-ray absorption meters are limited when compared with X-ray emission procedures. They are also limited when compared with fluorescence procedures."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "In absorption meter, which of the following is placed between the chopper and the reference cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Filter",
            "c) Photomultiplier tube",
            "d) Attenuator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Absorption meter, chopper is placed between the cell and the X-ray tube. It interrupts the half of the X-ray beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "In absorption meter, the two halves of the X-ray beam are allowed to fall on which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Filter",
            "c) Photomultiplier tube",
            "d) Attenuator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In absorption meter, attenuator is placed between the chopper and the reference cell. A variable thickness aluminium attenuator is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "The photomultiplier tube used is absorption meter is coated with which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium",
            "b) Potassium",
            "c) Phosphorous",
            "d) Chlorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In absorption meter, the two halves of the X-ray beam are allowed to fall on the photomultiplier tube. One beam passes through the sample and the other beam passes through the reference."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "In absorption meter, which of the following is adjusted until the absorption of two X-ray beams are brought into balance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Filter",
            "c) Photomultiplier tube",
            "d) Attenuator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The photomultiplier tube used is absorption meter is coated with phosphorous. Only one photomultiplier tube is commonly present for both the beams."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "In absorption meter, the change in thickness of aluminium required for different samples is a function of the difference in which of the following parameters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amount",
            "b) Concentration",
            "c) Colour",
            "d) Composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In absorption meter, the attenuator is adjusted until the absorption of two X-ray beams are brought into balance. A variable thickness aluminium attenuator is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "If the absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter results in the emission of radiation of the same or longer wavelengths for a long or a short time, the phenomenon is termed as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Luminescence",
            "b) Fluorescence",
            "c) Phosphorescence",
            "d) Spontaneous emission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter results in the emission of radiation of the same or longer wavelengths for a short or a long time, the phenomenon is termed as luminescence. Usually, absorption of electromagnetic radiation results in the emission of radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "If the absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter results in the emission of radiation of the same or longer wavelengths for a short time, the phenomenon is termed as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Luminescence",
            "b) Fluorescence",
            "c) Phosphorescence",
            "d) Spontaneous emission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter results in the emission of radiation of the same or longer wavelengths for a short time, the phenomenon is termed as fluorescence. Fluorescence emissions are characteristic of the particular element."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "If the absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter results in the emission of radiation of the same or longer wavelengths for a long time, the phenomenon is termed as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Luminescence",
            "b) Fluorescence",
            "c) Phosphorescence",
            "d) Spontaneous emission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the absorption of electromagnetic radiation by matter results in the emission of radiation of the same or longer wavelengths for a long time, the phenomenon is termed as phosphorescence. Phosphorescence is a type of luminescence."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Prompt emission of X-ray by an atom ionised by a higher energy X-ray is a type of which of the following phenomena?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Luminescence",
            "b) Fluorescence",
            "c) Phosphorescence",
            "d) Spontaneous emission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prompt emission of X-ray by an atom ionised by a higher energy X-ray is a type of fluorescence. Fluorescence emissions are characteristic of the particular element."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "The measurement of intensity of fluorescent X-rays provide a simple and ____________ way of _____________ analysis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Destructive, quantitative",
            "b) Non-destructive, quantitative",
            "c) Destructive, qualitative",
            "d) Non-destructive, qualitative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The measurement of an intensity of fluorescent X-rays provide a simple and non-destructive way of quantitative analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "The energy of the emitted X-rays depends upon the _________ of the atom and their intensity depends upon the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomic number, amount of sample",
            "b) Mass number, amount of sample",
            "c) Mass number, concentration of atoms",
            "d) Atomic number, concentration of atoms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy of the emitted X-rays depends upon the atomic number of the atom and their intensity depends upon the concentration of atoms in the sample. X-ray fluorescence spectroscopy is based on this principle."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which of the following is Mosely’s equation if ‘C’ is the speed of light, ‘a’ is proportionality constant, ‘σ’ is a constant which depends on electronic transition series, ‘Z’ is the atomic number and ‘λ’ is the wavelength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cλ= a(Z-σ)2",
            "b) C/λ= a(Z-σ)2",
            "c) C(Z-σ)2= aλ",
            "d) C(Z-σ)2= a/λ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Mosely’s equation is, C/λ= a(Z-σ)2.\nIt gives the relationship between the speed of light, reciprocal of wavelength and atomic number."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "In X-ray fluorescence spectrometer, the relationship between the excitation intensity and the intensity of fluorescence does not depend on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spectrum of the incident radiation",
            "b) Angle of radiance",
            "c) Molecular weight",
            "d) Incident angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The problem of spectral interference is not severe in X-ray spectroscopy. This is due to the relative simplicity of the X-ray spectra."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "Which of the following components of the X-ray fluorescent spectrometer induces fluorescent radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excitation source",
            "b) Energy analyser",
            "c) X-ray spectrometer",
            "d) Detection System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Excitation source induces fluorescent radiation in X-ray fluorescent spectrometer. A mono-energetic source is required for this purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Why is a mono-energetic radiation source required in X-ray fluorescent spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To provide good sensitivity",
            "b) To provide high accuracy",
            "c) To provide a proper range",
            "d) To reduce unwanted background"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mono-energetic radiation source is required in X-ray fluorescent spectrometer to reduce unwanted background. This occurs due to the scattering occurring over a broad range of wavelengths."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not make the X-ray tube nearly monochromatic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmission-anode X-ray tube",
            "b) Secondary fluorescence target",
            "c) Slit",
            "d) Filters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Slits do not make the X-ray tube nearly monochromatic. The most commonly used source is X-ray tubes."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Which of the following components make use of a thin metal foil to isolate a nearly mono-energetic excitation beam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmission-anode X-ray tube",
            "b) Secondary fluorescence target",
            "c) Slit",
            "d) Filters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Filters make use of a thin metal foil to isolate a nearly mono-energetic excitation beam. Nickel is one of the metals that is used in filters."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Energy dispersive system uses which of the following detectors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optical detector",
            "b) Semiconductor detector",
            "c) Thermistor",
            "d) Bolometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Energy dispersive system uses semiconductor detectors. It consists of an excitation source and a sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "In Energy dispersive system, the energy level and the number of pulses is related to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amount of sample, element involved",
            "b) Element involved, concentration of the element",
            "c) Concentration of the element, element involved",
            "d) Number of atoms, amount of sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Energy dispersive system, the energy level is related to the element involved. The number of pulses is related to the concentration of the element involved."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "The crystal used as X-ray grating has _______ dimensional lattice arrays.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The analysis of X-ray beam by diffraction is similar to spectrum analysis carried out with a diffraction grating. Wavelength dispersive type of meter derives its name from this fact."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be done to avoid loss of intensities of X-rays due to the absorption of long wavelength X-rays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Apparatus must be contained in a chamber",
            "b) Air in the chamber must be replaced by helium",
            "c) Inert gas atmosphere must be provided",
            "d) Proper slits must be used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crystal used as X-ray grating has three dimensional lattice arrays. Photons can be coherently scattered using the crystals."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of silicon semiconductor detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low stable",
            "b) Can be operated only at low temperatures",
            "c) Have low count-rate",
            "d) Low resolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Air in the chamber must be replaced by helium to avoid loss of intensities of X-rays due to the absorption of long wavelength X-rays. Vacuum chambers can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "In total reflection X-ray fluorescence spectrometer, the specimen is excited by the primary X-ray beam at a grazing angle _______ the critical angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than",
            "b) Less than",
            "c) Equal to",
            "d) Which is a complement of"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In total reflection X-ray fluorescence spectrometer, the specimen is excited by the primary X-ray beam at a grazing angle less than the critical angle. Total internal reflection occurs at the critical angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "The x-ray beam produced by the primary x-ray tube passes through which of the following components to produce the incident radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Detector",
            "b) Slit-collimator arrangement",
            "c) Sample reflector",
            "d) Monochromator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The x-ray beam produced by the primary x-ray tube passes through the slit-collimator arrangement. This forms the incident radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Which of the following crystals are polished to act as the cut-off reflector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quartz",
            "b) Beryllium",
            "c) Silicon",
            "d) Lithium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quartz crystals are polished to act as the cut-off reflector. It is mounted on the first reflector stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "The suppression of high energy bremsstrahlung radiation improves which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal to background ratio",
            "b) Accuracy",
            "c) Sensitivity",
            "d) Coherence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The suppression of high energy bremsstrahlung radiation improves the signal to background ratio.  Hence, it is performed in total reflection X-ray fluorescence spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which of the following components are used as the sample carrier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curvette",
            "b) Flask",
            "c) Capillary tube",
            "d) Float glass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Float glass is used as the sample carrier. It is mounted as the second reflector stage."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Which of the following devices are used as a detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermistor",
            "b) Optical detector",
            "c) Solid state detector",
            "d) Golay cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The detection system comprises of peltier cooled solid state detector. It also has a spectroscopy amplifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of the following happens when a large solid angle is intercepted as the detector is placed close to the sample?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum efficiency increases",
            "b) Maximum efficiency decreases",
            "c) Efficiency is not affected",
            "d) Process response becomes fast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the detector is placed very close to the sample, the maximum efficiency increases. This is because large angle is intercepted."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "To monitor the primary beam, which of the following is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scintillation counter",
            "b) GM counter",
            "c) Gamma counter",
            "d) Proportional counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To monitor the primary beam, Gm counter is used. It is placed in the specular reflection direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "The major problem associated with sample preparation is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preparing sample in the right quantity",
            "b) Choosing sample holders",
            "c) Matrix effects",
            "d) Reflection by holders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The major problem associated with sample preparation is matrix effects. The primary and emitted radiation is absorbed by the element present along with the elements of interest."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "In computer-controlled corrective iteration method, which of the following is used to estimate absorption corrections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial raw intensity data",
            "b) Elemental composition",
            "c) Amount of sample",
            "d) Amount of radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Computer-controlled corrective iteration is the only reliable method of matrix effects correction. This is used in places where an unknown matrix occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of optics employed in electron probe microanalyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron optics",
            "b) Light optics",
            "c) X-ray optics",
            "d) Gamma optics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gamma optics is not a type of optics used in electron probe microanalyser. Electron optics, light optics and X-ray optics are employed."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "The electron optics consists of an electron gun followed by which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collimator",
            "b) Slit",
            "c) Amplifier",
            "d) Electron beam probe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electron optics consists of an electron gun followed by an electron beam probe. This is formed by two electro-magnetic lenses."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "The specimen is mounted inside which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Test tube",
            "b) Glass capillary tube",
            "c) Vacuum column",
            "d) Curvette"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specimen is mounted inside the vacuum column in the instrument. It is under the beam as the target."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "The electrons are accelerated by voltages in which of the following ranges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 and 50kV",
            "b) 50 and 500kV",
            "c) 500 and 5000kV",
            "d) 25 and 250kV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The whole system operates in a vacuum. The electrons are accelerated by voltages in the range of 5 and 50kV."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the effective resolution limit in electron probe microanalyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1mm",
            "b) 10mm",
            "c) 100mm",
            "d) 1000mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electron probe microanalyser uses a finely focussed electron beam to excite the X-rays. It is a method of destructive elemental analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "X-ray emission must be analysed against a background of _______ radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blue",
            "b) Yellow",
            "c) White",
            "d) Green"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electrons spread laterally and longitudinally in the sample by approximately 1mm. Hence, the effective resolution limit is 1mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the limit of detectability of electron microprobe analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-14 g",
            "b) 10-140 g",
            "c) 10-7 g",
            "d) 10-70 g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Micro probe analyser can be used on inhomogeneous material. It can also be focussed on a very small area."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "The alternative method using laser does not analyse vapours by which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass spectrometer",
            "b) Optical emission",
            "c) Absorption photometry",
            "d) X-ray photometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: X-ray emission must be analysed against a background of white radiation. Microprobe has poorer sensitivity than XRF spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "NMR spectroscopy is used for determining structure in which of the following materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radioactive materials",
            "b) Insoluble chemical compounds",
            "c) Liquids",
            "d) Gases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NMR spectroscopy is used for determining structure in liquids. It is also used for determining the structure in soluble chemical compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "NMR is the study of the absorption of __________ by nuclei in a magnetic field.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radioactive radiation",
            "b) IR radiation",
            "c) Radio frequency radiation",
            "d) Microwaves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NMR is the study of absorption of radio frequency radiation by nuclei in a magnetic field. For a particular nucleus, an NMR absorption spectrum may consist of one to several groups of absorption lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "NMR spectrometer provides ____________ and _____________ method of determining structure in soluble chemical compounds.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accurate, destructive",
            "b) Accurate, non-destructive",
            "c) Inaccurate, destructive",
            "d) Inaccurate, non-destructive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: NMR spectrometer provides an accurate and non-destructive method of determining structure in soluble chemical compounds. For a particular nucleus an NMR absorption spectrum may consist of one to several groups of absorption lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "NMR spectroscopy indicates the chemical nature of the __________ and spatial positions of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrons, Protons",
            "b) Neutrons, electrons",
            "c) Nuclei, electrons",
            "d) Nuclei, neighbouring nuclei"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: NMR spectroscopy indicates the chemical nature of the nuclei and spatial positions of neighbouring nuclei. It is one of the most powerful techniques for chemical analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "In NMR spectroscopy, the spinning nuclei in a strong magnetic field must be irradiated by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perpendicular and stronger field",
            "b) Perpendicular and weaker field",
            "c) Parallel and stronger field",
            "d) Parallel and weaker field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In NMR spectroscopy, the spinning nuclei in a strong magnetic field must be irradiated by a weaker field which is perpendicular to it. This permits the identification of atomic configurations in molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Interaction between matter and electromagnetic radiation can be observed by subjecting a substance to magnetic fields in which of the following manner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Both fields should be stationary",
            "b) Both fields should be varying",
            "c) One field should be stationary and the other should be varying",
            "d) It must be subjected to only one field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Interaction between matter and electromagnetic radiation can be observed by subjecting a substance to two magnetic fields. One magnetic field must be stationary and the other field must be varying at some radio frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "When energy is absorbed by the sample, the absorption can be observed as a change in signal developed by which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplifier",
            "b) Photodetector",
            "c) GM counter",
            "d) Radiofrequency detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When energy is absorbed by the sample, the absorption can be observed as a change in signal developed by a radiofrequency detector. It is then given to an amplifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Which of the following are considered to be the lowest form of Electromagnetic radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IR radiation",
            "b) Micro waves",
            "c) UV radiation",
            "d) Radio waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Radio waves are considered to be the lowest form of Electromagnetic radiation. NMR uses radio frequency radiation for detection of the structure of substances."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "The amount of energy available in radio frequency radiation is sufficient for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excite an atom",
            "b) Vibrate an atom",
            "c) Vibrate a molecule",
            "d) Affect the nuclear spin of an atom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The amount of energy available in radio frequency radiation is sufficient for affecting the nuclear spin of an atom. It constitutes the most fundamental part of spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Nuclei having either the number of protons or neutrons as odd have _______ spin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integral spin",
            "b) Half integral spin",
            "c) Zero spin",
            "d) Positive spin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nuclei having either the number of protons or neutrons as odd have half-integral spin. Examples are H1 and B11."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "If the number of protons or neutrons is even the spin of the nucleus will be which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integral spin",
            "b) Half integral spin",
            "c) Zero spin",
            "d) Positive spin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the number of protons or neutrons is even the spin of the nucleus will be zero. Examples are C12 and O16."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "The difference between the field necessary for resonance in the sample and in some arbitrary a chosen compound is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Field shift",
            "b) Matrix effects",
            "c) Chemical shift",
            "d) Resonance shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The difference between the field necessary for resonance in the sample and in some arbitrary chosen compound is called a chemical shift. Chemical shift is expressed in parts per million."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of NMR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimal type",
            "b) Maximal type",
            "c) Multipurpose type",
            "d) Wideline type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximal type is not a type of NMR spectrometer. Minimal type, Multipurpose type and Wideline type are types of NMR spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Which of the following NMR spectrometers have stressed reliability and ease of operation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimal type",
            "b) Maximal type",
            "c) Multipurpose type",
            "d) Wideline type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Minimal type has stressed the reliability and ease of operation. It uses a permanent magnet."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of NMR spectrometer uses a frequency synthesizer to generate RF fields?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimal type",
            "b) Maximal type",
            "c) Multipurpose type",
            "d) Wideline type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wideline type NMR spectrometer uses a frequency synthesizer to generate RF fields. It is a type of continuous wave NMR spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "In wideline NMR spectrometers, which of the following has to be supplied to the electromagnet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slowly varying low voltage",
            "b) Rapidly varying low voltage",
            "c) Slowly varying scan voltage",
            "d) Rapidly varying scan voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In wideline NMR spectrometers, slowly varying scan voltage has to be supplied to the electromagnet. This is injected using a regulator."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Which among the following NMR spectrometer is the more diverse spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimal type",
            "b) Maximal type",
            "c) Multipurpose type",
            "d) Wideline type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Multipurpose type NMR spectrometer is more diverse. These instruments are designed mainly for research."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which of the following NMR spectrometer emphasises on high performance versatility with cost being a secondary consideration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimal type",
            "b) Maximal type",
            "c) Multipurpose type",
            "d) Wideline type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Permanent magnet can be used in wideline type NMR spectrometer. Compact, light-weight electromagnet can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Which of the following NMR spectrometer does not require a power supply and cooling system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimal type",
            "b) Maximal type",
            "c) Multipurpose type",
            "d) Wideline type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Multipurpose type is mainly used for research. Hence, it emphasises on high performance versatility with cost being a secondary consideration."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as a coolant for magnets in continuous-wave NMR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Liquid He",
            "c) Liquid Na",
            "d) Heavy water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Minimal type NMR spectrometer uses a permanent magnet. Hence, it does not require a power supply and cooling system."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of the following components are used to separate the nuclear spin energy states?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RF channels",
            "b) Magnet",
            "c) Sample probe",
            "d) Sweep generator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A magnet is used to separate the nuclear spin energy states. Permanent magnet or electromagnets can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "In frequency sweep method, which of the following parameters are varied continuously?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic field",
            "b) RF signal",
            "c) Sample concentration",
            "d) Amplification factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In frequency sweep method, magnetic field is held constant. RF signal is swept or varied continuously."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "In field sweep method, which of the following parameters are varied continuously?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic field",
            "b) RF signal",
            "c) Sample concentration",
            "d) Amplification factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In frequency sweep method, RF signal is held constant. Magnetic field is swept or varied continuously."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements are not true about permanent magnets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are simple",
            "b) They are inexpensive",
            "c) They don’t require shielding",
            "d) They don’t require power supply"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Permanent magnets are simple and inexpensive. But, permanent magnets require extensive shielding."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true of electromagnets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are expensive",
            "b) They require a power supply",
            "c) They don’t require a cooling system",
            "d) They don’t require extensive shielding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electromagnets require a power supply. They also require cooling systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of the following must not be done to maintain the magnetic field over the sample uniform in space and time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large pole pieces need to be used",
            "b) Pole faces must be polished",
            "c) Wide pole gap must be present",
            "d) Magnets can be permanent or electromagnet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For high resolution work the magnetic field over the entire sample volume must be maintained uniform in space and time. To do this all the components must be kept in specified conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "The sample is contained in which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flask",
            "b) Capillary tube",
            "c) Curvette",
            "d) Bore glass tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Narrow pole gap must be present to maintain the magnetic field over the sample uniform in space and time. The pole faces must be polished to optical tolerances."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "The single coil probe supplies the RF radiation to the sample and also serves as a part of which of the following circuits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RF channels",
            "b) Magnet",
            "c) Detector",
            "d) Sweep generator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sample is contained in a bore glass tube. It should be cylindrical and thin-walled."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Nuclear induction probes’ one coil is used for signal detection. What is the function of the other coil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample irradiation",
            "b) Magnet",
            "c) Detector",
            "d) Sweep generator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The single coil probe supplies the RF radiation to the sample and also serves as a part of the detector circuit. It has only one coil."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The amplification required for continuous-wave NMR is of the order of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 101",
            "b) 102",
            "c) 103",
            "d) 105"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crossed coil probes are also called nuclear induction probes. One coil is used for irradiating the sample. The other coil is mounted orthogonally for signal detection."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used instead of magnets to produce the magnetic field?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductor",
            "b) Motor",
            "c) Generator",
            "d) Superconducting solenoids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unmarked component is sweep generator. Either field or frequency can be swept."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "How is the inhomogeneity of magnetic fields compensated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With large magnetic fields",
            "b) With small magnetic fields",
            "c) By using two or more magnets",
            "d) By providing required insulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The voltage generated by the receiver coil is small and it must be amplified. It is them fed to the recorder or oscilloscope."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Fourier transform NMR spectrometer has which of the following characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased sensitivity, long time to obtain data",
            "b) Decreased sensitivity, long time to obtain data",
            "c) Increased sensitivity, reduced time to obtain data",
            "d) Decreased sensitivity, reduced time to obtain data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fourier transform NMR spectrometer is a type of NMR spectrometer. It allows samples to be observed simultaneously instead of serially."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be done due to the multiplex advantage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repetitive signals can be summed",
            "b) Repetitive signals can be averaged",
            "c) Increases signal to noise ratio",
            "d) Decreases signal to noise ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fourier transform NMR spectrometer has increased sensitivity. It takes less time to obtain NMR data."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of conventional mode of spectrometer or continuous-wave NMR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are unstable",
            "b) Maintenance is difficult",
            "c) High operating cost",
            "d) Excitation is inefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The multiplexing advantage allows improvement of the signal to noise ratio. It also allows repetitive signals to be summed and averaged."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Which of the following must be done to improve sensitivity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency sweep mode must be preferred",
            "b) Field sweep mode must be preferred",
            "c) Single channel excitation must be preferred",
            "d) Multichannel excitation must be preferred"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only one coil is necessary for Fourier transform NMR spectroscopy. The coil serves as both antenna for transmitting and receiving RF radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of multichannel excitation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low sensitivity",
            "b) Low resolution",
            "c) Small number of frequencies is present",
            "d) Uneconomical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The disadvantage of conventional mode of a spectrometer or continuous-wave NMR spectrometer is that the excitation is inefficient. Only a narrow band of frequencies are contributing to the signal at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "How can the need for an array of narrow-band filters and detectors be eliminated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By using multi-channel excitation",
            "b) By using a detector for each frequency",
            "c) By reducing the number of detectors",
            "d) By using Fourier transform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sweep techniques have less sensitivity. To improve sensitivity, multichannel excitation must be preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Fourier transform can be accomplished by using which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spin decoder",
            "b) Detector",
            "c) Spectrum analyser",
            "d) Oscilloscope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Large number of frequencies is present in multichannel excitation. This is uneconomical since a receiver is required for each channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "A 15.4 MHz crystal generates the _________ resonance frequency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen",
            "b) Deuterium",
            "c) Tritium",
            "d) Helium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fourier transform plays the role of a multichannel receiver. Hence, the need for array of narrow-band filters can be eliminated"
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Sensitivity is the ratio of peak signal amplitude to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Rms noise",
            "c) Average noise",
            "d) Peak-to-peak noise"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sensitivity is the ratio of peak signal amplitude to rms noise. It is a measure of the ability of an instrument to differentiate signal from surrounding noise."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operating technique for sensitivity enhancement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optimization of sample volume",
            "b) Optimization of instrumental parameters",
            "c) Optimization of noise",
            "d) Time averaging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are only three operating techniques for sensitivity enhancement. Optimization of noise is not an operating technique for sensitivity enhancement."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques do not enhance sensitivity by a factor of 10 at normal operating conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optimization of sample volume",
            "b) Optimization of instrumental parameters",
            "c) Optimization of noise",
            "d) Time averaging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Time averaging techniques does not enhance sensitivity by a factor of 10. The other two techniques enhance sensitivity by a factor of 10 at normal operating conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "The most common spherical cells have which of the following dimensions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4mm diameter",
            "b) 40mm diameter",
            "c) 8mm diameter",
            "d) 80mm diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most common spherical cells have 4mm diameter. A 1mm capillary cell is centred along the axis of the coil."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Better sensitivity with good resolution can be achieved by concentrating the sample inside which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample cell",
            "b) Micro cell",
            "c) Sample tube",
            "d) Cylindrical tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Better sensitivity with good resolution can be achieved by concentrating the sample inside a specially designed NMR microcell. It could be a spherical cell or a capillary cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "Frequency spectrum of noise occupies a band that is _________ the signal spectrum. Choose the most appropriate option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrow than",
            "b) Wider than",
            "c) Different from",
            "d) Same as"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency spectrum of noise occupies a band that is wider than the signal spectrum. Filters operate on this concept."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Suppression of frequencies which contain no signal does which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases S/N ratio",
            "b) Decreases S/N ratio",
            "c) S/N ratio is kept constant",
            "d) S/N ratio becomes 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Suppression of frequencies which contain no signal increases S/N ratio. The noise decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not involved in signal averaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A system to repeatedly scan the spectral region of interest",
            "b) Some storage device to store information",
            "c) A system to coherently add individual spectra",
            "d) Sweep generator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amplitude of the NMR signal caused by the absorption of RF energy at the radio frequency depends on the power of the RF energy applied. It also depends on the sweep rate selected."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "In Spin Decoupler, the output of the DC amplifier is applied to which of the following to control the power supplied to the oven heaters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Power diode",
            "b) Power transistor",
            "c) Power MOSFET",
            "d) Power IGBT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sweep generator is not involved in signal averaging. This is usually accomplished using a small computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "In Spin Decoupler, the difference frequency circuit provides a means of mixing two signals and a filter to recover which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low-frequency component",
            "b) High-frequency component",
            "c) Low-voltage component",
            "d) High-voltage component"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In order to have a long measuring time for increasing sensitivity, it is better to have several fast scans than a single slow scan. The sensitivity increases by the square root of a number of scans."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Mass spectrometers are used to determine which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Composition in sample",
            "b) Concentration of elements in sample",
            "c) Relative mass of atoms",
            "d) Properties of sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mass spectrometers are used to determine the relative mass of atoms and molecules. Aston made the instrument more accurate."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Who invented mass spectrometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) J.J Thompson",
            "b) Goldstein",
            "c) Nikola Tesla",
            "d) Aston"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: J.J Thompson introduced mass spectrometers. Aston modified the instrument to make it more accurate."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "In mass spectrometer, the sample that has to be analysed is bombarded with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protons",
            "b) Electrons",
            "c) Neutrons",
            "d) Alpha particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In mass spectrometer, the sample which is to be analysed is bombarded with electrons. As a result, ions are produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Mass spectrometer separates ions on the basis of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass",
            "b) Charge",
            "c) Molecular weight",
            "d) Mass to charge ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mass spectrometer separates ions on the basis of mass to charge ratio. Most of the ions are singly charged. Hence, the mass to charge ratio is equal to the mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "In mass spectrometer, the ions are sorted out in which of the following ways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By accelerating them through electric field",
            "b) By accelerating them through magnetic field",
            "c) By accelerating them through electric and magnetic field",
            "d) By applying a high voltage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In mass spectrometer, the ions are sorted out by accelerating them through an electric and magnetic field. A record of number of different kinds of ions is called mass spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The procedure for mass spectroscopy starts with which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The sample is bombarded by electron beam",
            "b) The ions are separated by passing them into electric and magnetic field",
            "c) The sample is converted into gaseous state",
            "d) The ions are detected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: No two molecules will be fragmented and ionized in exactly the same manner. This is how different molecules are identified in a complex mixture."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "In a mass spectrometer, the ion currents are measured using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scintillation counter",
            "b) Ion counter",
            "c) Electrometer tube",
            "d) Electric fields"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The procedure for mass spectroscopy starts with converting the sample into a gaseous state. This is done by chemical processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Which of the following ions pass through the slit and reach the collecting plate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Negative ions of all masses",
            "b) Positive ions of all masses",
            "c) Negative ions of specific mass",
            "d) Positive ions of specific mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ion currents are measured using a sensitive electrometer tube. The ions reaching the collecting plate are measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is not true about mass spectrometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impurities of masses different from the one being analysed interferes with the result",
            "b) It has great sensitivity",
            "c) It is suitable for data storage",
            "d) It is suitable for library retrieval"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Positive ions of specific mass pass through the slit and reach the collecting plate. These ions are measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inlet system",
            "b) Sweep generator",
            "c) Ion transducer",
            "d) Mass analyser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sweep generator is not a component of a mass spectrometer. It is a component of NMR spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be introduced into the ionization chamber directly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid samples with low vapour pressure",
            "b) Solid samples with high vapour pressure",
            "c) Liquid samples with low density",
            "d) Liquid samples with high density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Solid samples with low vapour pressure can be introduced into the ionization chamber directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Inlet system is also known as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial system",
            "b) Sample reservoir",
            "c) Sample handling system",
            "d) Element injection system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inlet system introduces the sample into the ion source. Hence, it is called a sample handling system."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which of the following is normally done to convert the sample into the gaseous state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sample is pressurized",
            "b) Chemical reactions are made to occur",
            "c) Sample is heated",
            "d) Sample is cooled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sample must always be in the gaseous state. Hence, the liquid sample must be heated before introducing them into the ionization chamber."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "Which of the following probes are used for the introduction of the sample?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silica",
            "b) Quartz",
            "c) Graphite",
            "d) Silver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Solid samples with low vapour pressure are introduced into the entrance of the chamber. They are introduced using silica or platinum probe."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of ionisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Field ionisation",
            "b) Spontaneous ionisation",
            "c) Spark ionisation",
            "d) Chemical ionisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spontaneous ionisation is not a type of ionisation. In mass spectrometer, ionisation is brought about by thermal or electrical energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Mass analyser is similar to which of the following in optical spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Source",
            "b) Monochromator",
            "c) Detector",
            "d) Sample"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mass analyser is similar to monochromator in an optical spectrometer. It separates ions according to their mass/charge ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the types of mass analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic sector analyser",
            "b) Frequency sweep analyser",
            "c) Double focussing spectrometer",
            "d) Time of flight analyser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Frequency sweep analyser is not a type of mass analyser. There are many devices available for mass analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of ion detector used in mass spectrometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron multiplier",
            "b) Flame emission detector",
            "c) Faraday cup collector",
            "d) Photographic plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flame emission detector is not a type of ion detector used in mass spectrometers. Ion detectors produce a current on the output side when there are ions on the input side."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to inject liquid samples?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypodermic needle",
            "b) Glass bulb",
            "c) Capillary tube",
            "d) Curvette"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Liquid samples are injected through hypodermic needles. It is vaporized at low pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Under which of the following temperatures is the ionisation chamber maintained?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100oC",
            "b) 200oC",
            "c) 300oC",
            "d) 400oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ionisation chamber is maintained at 200oC. It is also maintained at low pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of nebulizers that are commonly used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cost",
            "b) Low uptake rate",
            "c) High efficiency",
            "d) High uptake rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unmarked component is ion transducer. It will give current at the output at its output side when ions are present on the input side."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "In glow discharge ion source, the sample is atomised by which of the following process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation",
            "b) Sputtering",
            "c) Heating",
            "d) Annealing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Commonly used nebulizers have a low uptake rate. They also have low cost and high efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Which of the following produces the electron beam in magnetic deflection mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten filament",
            "b) Quartz rod",
            "c) Silica",
            "d) Rhodium filament"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tungsten filament produces the electron beam in magnetic deflection mass spectrometer. The electrons are produced by the heated filament."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "In magnetic deflection mass spectrometer, in which of the following ways is acceleration applied to the direction of motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In random manner",
            "b) Parallel to it",
            "c) Perpendicular to it",
            "d) Along it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acceleration in the mass spectrometer, is applied perpendicular to the direction of motion. The velocity of the object remains constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "Direct focussing is obtained by deflecting the ion beam along a _________ trajectory through the magnetic field.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120o",
            "b) 150o",
            "c) 190o",
            "d) 180o"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Direct focussing is obtained by deflecting the ion beam along a 180o trajectory through a magnetic field. The gap between the poles must be large enough to contain the ion source."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Which of the following separate the ions according to their mass-to-charge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion source",
            "b) Detector",
            "c) Magnetic sector",
            "d) Electric sector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnetic sector will separate the ions according to their mass-to-charge. The magnet will decide the mass to charge ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Mattauch-Herzog geometry involves a deflection of which of the following radians in a radial electrostatic field analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) √2Π",
            "b) Π/2",
            "c) Π/3√4",
            "d) Π/4√2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mattauch-Herzog geometry involves a deflection of Π/4√2 radians in a radial electrostatic field analyser. It is followed by a magnetic deflection of Π/2 radians."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Which of the following leads to the limitation of resolution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All ions do not have same energy",
            "b) All ions do not have same charge",
            "c) All ions are not of the same size",
            "d) All ions do not have the same charge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resolution is limited as all ions do not have the same energy. Hence, the ions would not have the same velocity."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Which of the following components need to be added in order to increase the resolution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion source",
            "b) Detector",
            "c) Magnetic sector",
            "d) Electric sector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electric sector field is not subject to hysteresis. Hence, the relationship between mass to charge ratio and accelerating voltage is linear."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "Which of the following is commonly varied in magnetic deflection mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric sector",
            "b) Magnetic fold strength",
            "c) Magnetic constant",
            "d) Electric constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electric sector needs to be added in order to increase the resolution. This compensates for the decrease in resolution due to varying velocities."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Nier-Johnson geometry involves a deflection of which of the following radians in a radial electrostatic field analyser?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Π",
            "b) Π/2",
            "c) Π/3",
            "d) Π/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnetic fold strength is usually varied in magnetic deflection mass spectrometer. Electric sector is kept constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of the time of flight analyser spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion source",
            "b) Field free separation region",
            "c) Electron multiplication region",
            "d) Photo tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phototube is not a component of time of flight mass spectrometer. Time of flight mass analyser is a type of mass spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple",
            "b) Rugged",
            "c) High sensitivity",
            "d) Unlimited mass range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Time of flight mass spectrometer is a type of mass spectrometer. It has unlimited mass range."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "If all the ions have the same kinetic energy how are their masses related to their velocities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass and velocity are equal",
            "b) Mass and velocity are not related",
            "c) Mass and velocity are directly proportional",
            "d) Mass and velocity are inversely proportional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Time of flight mass spectrometers have limited sensitivity and resolution. They are simple and rugged."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about time of flight analyser spectrometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lighter particles arrive at the detector earlier",
            "b) Heavier particle arrive at the detector earlier",
            "c) Lighter and heavier particles arrive together at the detector",
            "d) Lighter particles do not reach the detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Separation of ions occurs while they are moving from the ion source to the detector. All the ions entering the tube have the same kinetic energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "In the time of flight mass spectrometer, ions are formed by which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulsed ionization method",
            "b) Acceleration method",
            "c) Dynamic method",
            "d) Ion excitation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If all the ions have the same kinetic energy, mass and velocity are inversely proportional. This is used in the separation of ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "The evacuated tube is also known as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse tube",
            "b) Detector tube",
            "c) Drift tube",
            "d) Acceleration tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lighter particles arrive at the detector earlier than the heavier particles. The time difference is used to separate the electrons according to their mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "The current produced by ions arriving at the collector necessitates the use of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wide band amplifier",
            "b) Narrow band amplifier",
            "c) Wide band filter",
            "d) Narrow band filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the time of flight mass spectrometer, ions are formed by pulsed ionisation method. It is a type of mass spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an ion optic device in which ions pass through a mirror and their flight is reversed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reversal device",
            "b) Reflectron",
            "c) Mirror arrangement",
            "d) Separation chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The evacuated tube is also known as a drift tube. The electrons move from source to detector through the tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements about mass spectrometers are not true?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time of flight mass spectrometer has the ability to record the entire mass spectrum at a time",
            "b) Time of flight mass spectrometers have poor resolution",
            "c) Conventional spectrometer detects only one peak at a time",
            "d) All spectrometers have the ability to record the entire mass spectrum at a time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The current produced by ions arriving at the collector has very short duration. Hence, it necessitates the use of wide band amplifier."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Which of the following is placed just before the detector in a radiofrequency mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion source",
            "b) Potential energy selector",
            "c) Ionisation chamber",
            "d) Reflectron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A potential energy selector is placed before the detector. It balances out the energy of the ion beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of the following is applied in one or more stages where each stage is a series of three equally spaced parallel grids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ionisation field",
            "b) Reflection",
            "c) RF field",
            "d) Acceleration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RF field is applied in one or more stages. Each stage is a series of three equally spaced parallel grids."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "The alternating voltage rf voltage is applied to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All grids",
            "b) Central grid",
            "c) Alternate grids",
            "d) None of the grids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The alternating voltage rf voltage is applied to the central grid. All the other grids are kept at ground potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "The DC ion accelerating voltage is swept from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 to 50 V",
            "b) 50 to 100 V",
            "c) 200 to 300 V",
            "d) 50 to 250 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rf spectrometer does not contain a magnet. Rf field is applied for this type of mass spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "The resolution of the Bennet tube can be improved by using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sine wave rf signal",
            "b) Square wave rf signal",
            "c) Triangular wave rf signal",
            "d) Random signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The DC ion accelerating voltage is swept from 50 to 250 V. This is done twice per second."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "The spurious lines can be reduced to a minimum by using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single stage tube",
            "b) Two stage tube",
            "c) Three stage tube",
            "d) Reflectron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resolution of the Bennet tube can be improved by using square wave rf signal. Usually, sinusoidal wave signal is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of using three stage tubes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduced resolution",
            "b) Bulky construction",
            "c) Complex",
            "d) Heavy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Bennet spectrometer, the rf voltage has a fixed frequency. It is modulated at 10 percent at 1kHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the feature of Bennet type spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lightweight",
            "b) Simple",
            "c) Absence of spurious lines",
            "d) Moderate resolution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The spurious lines can be reduced to a minimum by using three stage tubes. Two stage tubes tend to produce spurious lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "The resolving power of Bennet type spectrometer is primarily based on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distance between detector and reflectron",
            "b) Difference between the individual rf accelerating stages",
            "c) Length of the drift tube",
            "d) Laser beam used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spurious lines can be reduced to a minimum by using three stage tubes. This results in reduced resolving power."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of quadrupole mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cost",
            "b) Light weight",
            "c) Low speed electronic scanning",
            "d) Simple in construction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In quadrupole mass spectrometer, electronic scanning takes place. The scanning takes place at high speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of quadrupole mass filter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrodes",
            "b) Choke",
            "c) DC potential",
            "d) Detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Detector is not a part of the filter. The filter uses DC potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "If to one pair of electrodes one potential with one sign is applied, which of the following is applied to the other pair of electrodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same potential with same sign",
            "b) Different potential with same sign",
            "c) Different potential with different sign",
            "d) Same potential with different sign"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mass selection scheme uses a dc potential. It also uses radio frequency potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the heart of quadrupole instrument?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrodes",
            "b) Choke",
            "c) DC potential",
            "d) Detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If to one pair of electrodes one potential with one sign is applied, same potential with a different sign is applied to the opposite electrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Which of the following has to be done to increase the resolution of the quadrupole mass spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing distance between detector and reflectron",
            "b) Increasing difference between the individual rf accelerating stages",
            "c) Increasing the length of the drift tube",
            "d) Increasing the rod length of the electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrodes are the heart of quadrupole instrument. Opposite electrodes are electrically connected."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not affect the resolution of the instrument?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Changing length of electrode",
            "b) Changing slope of scan line",
            "c) Quality of machining of the rods",
            "d) Changing length of drift tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resolution depends upon the electrode. The length of the electrode has to be increased for increasing the resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "In cases where differentiation is required between very similar substances, which of the following techniques making use of quadrupole principle is preferred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation mass spectrometry",
            "b) Pyrolysis mass spectrometry",
            "c) Plasma mass spectrometry",
            "d) Trapped ion mass spectrometry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Changing length of drift tube does not affect the resolution of the instrument. Increase in resolution results in an increase in the number of ions reaching the detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "In pyrolysis spectrometry, heating is done until which of the following is reached?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curie point",
            "b) Boiling point",
            "c) Until production of superheated vapour",
            "d) Until 100oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In cases where differentiation is required between very similar substances, pyrolysis mass spectrometry is used. The sample is usually solid or involatile liquid in this case."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to cool the ion source?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid sodium shield",
            "b) Liquid nitrogen shield",
            "c) Water",
            "d) Freon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In pyrolysis spectrometry, heating is done until curie point is reached. At this point, magnetic permeability drops abruptly."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "When a value of q is kept constant, the value of m/e is proportional to which of the following when ‘m’ is the mass number, ‘e’ is the electric charge, ‘u’ is the DC potential, ‘v’ is the peak amplitude and ‘f’ is the frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) u/v ratio",
            "b) u",
            "c) v",
            "d) f"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Liquid nitrogen cooled shield is used to cool the ion source. It reduces source contamination."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an ion transducer or detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channeltron",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Flame ionization detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flame ionization detector is not an ion transducer. It is a detector used in chromatography."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Which of the following is similar to photo multiplier transducer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channeltron",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electron multiplier transducer is similar to photo multiplier transducer. The difference is that its primary cathode detects ions rather than photons."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used in places where ion currents are very low?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channeltron",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electron multiplier transducer is used in places where ion currents are very low. Its primary cathode detects ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Discrete type electron multiplier transducers can provide current gain upto which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 102",
            "b) 105",
            "c) 107",
            "d) 1011"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Discrete type electron multiplier transducers can provide current gain upto 102. Upto 20 dynodes need to be used for this purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Continuous dynode electron multiplier transducer is a trumpet shaped device made with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass doped with lead",
            "b) Steel doped with bronze",
            "c) Phosphor bronze doped with iron",
            "d) Iron doped with calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Continuous dynode electron multiplier transducer is a trumpet shaped device made of glass. It is heavily doped with lead."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The potential maintained across the continuous dynode multiplier transducer is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 5kV",
            "b) 5 to 10kV",
            "c) 2.5 to 6.2kV",
            "d) 1.8 to 2kV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The potential maintained across the continuous dynode multiplier transducer is 1.8 to 2kV. Electrons cascade down the tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not the characteristics of an electron multiplier transducer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rugged",
            "b) Reliable",
            "c) Microsecond of response time required",
            "d) High current gain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electron multiplier transducer requires the only nanosecond of response time. It provides a high current gain."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Which of the following are true about dynodes used in discrete dynode electron multiplier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The dynodes are all kept at same voltage",
            "b) Successive dynodes are held at lower potential",
            "c) Successive dynodes are held at higher potential",
            "d) All dynodes are held at very low potential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In discrete dynode electron multiplier, successive dynodes are held at higher potential. Dynodes are metal plates with copper or beryllium surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "In which of the following detectors, the collector is placed in an inclined manner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channeltron",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The collector is placed in an inclined manner in a faraday cup collector. This is to reflect the ions away from the entrance of the cup."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the least sensitive ion detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channeltron",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Faraday cup collector is the least sensitive ion detector. It is used in places where great sensitivity is not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Photographic plates are coated with which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lead",
            "b) Quartz",
            "c) Silver bromide",
            "d) Mercuric sulphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Photographic plates are coated with silver bromide. These are sensitive to energetic ions."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors are well suited for spark source instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Photographic plates",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Photographic plates are well suited for spark source instruments. It has great sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors consist of an array of glass capillaries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Photographic plates",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photographic plates have greater sensitivity and resolution than electron multipliers. This is because they integrate the ion signals over a period of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Which of the following detectors can be used for ions with short life time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Photographic plates",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Electron multiplier transducer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Micro-channel plate consists of an array of glass capillaries. They are coated with electron emissive materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "ICP’s principle is similar to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flame emission spectroscopy",
            "b) Fourier transforms spectroscopy",
            "c) Atomic emission spectroscopy",
            "d) Absorption spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ICP’s principle is similar to atomic emission spectroscopy. Samples are decomposed to neural elements in argon plasma in this method."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "ICP is used to analyse samples in which of the following states?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solids",
            "b) Liquids",
            "c) Gases",
            "d) Solids and liquids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ICP is used to analyse samples in both solid and liquid states. Atomic emission spectrometer is used to analyse only solid samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Solid samples are introduced into the ICP spectrometer using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nebulizer",
            "b) Curvette having glass windows",
            "c) Probe",
            "d) Laser ablation system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ICP spectrometer can be used for solid samples. They are introduced using a laser ablation system."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Liquid samples are introduced into the ICP spectrometer using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nebulizer",
            "b) Curvette having glass windows",
            "c) Probe",
            "d) Laser ablation system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ICP spectrometer can be used for liquid samples. Aqueous samples are introduced using the nebulizer."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Atomisation or ionisation occurs at which of the following conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum pressure",
            "b) Atmospheric pressure",
            "c) Low pressure",
            "d) High pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Atomization or ionisation occurs at atmospheric pressure. The interface between the ICP and MS components are crucial in creating a vacuum."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Ions flow is pumped into the vacuum system using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orifice",
            "b) Nozzle",
            "c) Venturi meter",
            "d) Dall tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ions flow is pumped into the vacuum system using orifice. It expands in the vacuum system."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of ICP spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy sample introduction",
            "b) It can trace multiple elements",
            "c) High detection limits",
            "d) Accurate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ICP spectrometer has low detection limits of a mass spectrometer. It is capable of tracking multiple elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "ICP spectrometer is a sequential multi-element analyser that has scan times less than ____ for one sweep.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10ms",
            "b) 20ms",
            "c) 50ms",
            "d) 100ms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ICP spectrometer is a sequential multi-element analyser that has scan times less than 20ms for one sweep. Quadrupole mass analyser gives a better unit mass resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "The most common type of ion detector found in ICP system is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channeltron",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Flame ionization detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Double focussing section analysers offer better resolution than ICP spectrometry system. Their disadvantage is that they are large and have a high capital cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most accurate method of determination of elemental composition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spectroscopy",
            "b) Isotope dilution",
            "c) Isobar dilution",
            "d) Chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most common type of ion detector found in ICP system is channel tron electron multiplier. It is a cone or horn shaped tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of ICP mass spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incapable of multi-element analysis",
            "b) Less sensitivity",
            "c) Impossible to obtain isotopic information",
            "d) Not useful for detection of non-metals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most accurate method of determination of elemental composition is isotope dilution. It permits the calculation of the concentration of an element."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "The isobaric interference is not caused in which of the following elements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Helium",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ICP mass spectroscopy has a multi-element capability and high sensitivity. It is not capable of multi-element analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most sensitive of the spectral methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Absorption spectroscopy",
            "b) Mass spectroscopy",
            "c) Flame emission spectroscopy",
            "d) Atomic emission spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mass spectroscopy is the most sensitive of the spectral methods. It permits direct introduction of a gas effluent’s stream."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the disadvantage of gas chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is not a good method",
            "b) It cannot be used for qualitative analysis",
            "c) It cannot be used for the separation of volatile components",
            "d) It does not provide direct identification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gas chromatography is a very good method for separation of components of a mixture. It does not provide direct identification."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Which of the following is most often used in the chromatograph in gas chromatograph MS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curvette",
            "b) Paper support",
            "c) Capillary tube",
            "d) Flask"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cold tray is provided for liquid N2 or CO2. It is used only for mass spectral analysis of very small samples."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "GC- MS has been developed for which of the following systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packed column",
            "b) Open tubular column",
            "c) Capillary column",
            "d) Porous layer column"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Capillary tube is most often used in the chromatograph in gas chromatograph MS. This is because low pressure has to be maintained."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Which of the following problems occur when combining gas chromatography and mass spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference in operating pressures",
            "b) Reduction in sensitivity",
            "c) Direct identification is not possible",
            "d) It does not permit direct introduction of the effluent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: GC- MS has been developed for packed column system. These allow for analyte molecules to be dynamically extracted from the carrier gas stream."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the type of separator used in commercial GC-MS systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jet type molecular separator",
            "b) Porous tube",
            "c) Teflon tube",
            "d) Flow type separator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The problem that occurs when combining gas chromatography and mass spectroscopy is the difference in operating pressures. The pressure at the exit of the GC column is atmospheric."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The system for measurement of ion intensity in GS-MS system consists of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrometer",
            "b) Ion meter",
            "c) Ion transducer",
            "d) Intensity meter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The carrier gas with low molecular weight would diffuse at a higher rate than the higher molecular weight sample. The carrier gas would diffuse away from the line of flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "The system for measurement of ion intensity in GS-MS system consists of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Band pass amplifier",
            "b) Narrow band amplifier",
            "c) Wide band amplifier",
            "d) Low pass amplifier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jet type molecular separator is the type of separator used in commercial GC-MS systems. Other methods are porous tube and Teflon tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "The gas burden from conventional LC flow rates creates nearly _____ times more gas than cryo-pumped vacuum system can handle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Introduction of total HPLC effluent into MS is not feasible. The simplest method is the introduction of liquid from LC to the MS ion source region."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Which of the following should be in a position to split the effluent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interface",
            "b) Ion source",
            "c) Makeup gas",
            "d) Microbore"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gas burden from conventional LC flow rates creates nearly 20 times more gas than cryo-pumped vacuum system can handle."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most commonly used interface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nebulizer",
            "b) Chopper",
            "c) Filter",
            "d) Vapourising chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Interface should be in a position to split the effluent. LC-MS is a very advantageous method."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Only ______ percent of the effluent of the liquid chromatography must be introduced in the mass spectrometer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2 %",
            "b) 1-5 %",
            "c) 1-20 %",
            "d) 1-15 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nebulizer is the most commonly used interface. The nebulizer gas and the make-up gas are introduced coaxially into the heated nebulization region."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the normal nebuliser temperature used in LC mass spectrometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50-100oC",
            "b) 100-200oC",
            "c) 125-150oC",
            "d) 150-200oC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only 1-5 percent of the effluent of the liquid chromatography must be introduced in the mass spectrometer. Therefore, the total effluent must be split."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "The ions are focussed and de-clustered through which of the following regions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry helium region",
            "b) Wet oxygen region",
            "c) Wet chlorine region",
            "d) Dry nitrogen region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 125-150oC is the normal nebuliser temperature used in LC mass spectrometry. It is suitable for a variety of applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "The ions are passed into the high vacuum analyser through which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orifice",
            "b) Nozzle",
            "c) Nebulizer",
            "d) Venturi tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ions are focussed and de-clustered through a dry nitrogen region. It is then sent into the high vacuum analyser."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Gas burden from conventional LC flow rates is which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1ml/min of water produces 1.2 l/mm of gas",
            "b) 1ml/min of water produces 2.4 l/mm of gas",
            "c) 2ml/min of water produces 3.2 l/mm of gas",
            "d) 1ml/min of water produces 4.2 l/mm of gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ions are sent into the high vacuum analyser through an orifice. It is then mass analysed."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "Tandem mass spectroscopy combines which of the following devices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass spectrometer and gas-solid chromatograph",
            "b) Mass spectrometer and gas-liquid chromatograph",
            "c) Mass spectrometer and gas chromatograph",
            "d) Mass spectrometer and mass spectrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tandem mass spectroscopy combines two mass spectrometers. It is represented as MS/MS."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to separate a single mass that is characteristic of a given analyte in a mixture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First mass spectrometer",
            "b) Second mass spectrometer",
            "c) Filter",
            "d) Precursor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In tandem spectroscopy, the first stage sepatation device is a mass spectrometer. It is represented as MS/MS."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "The mass-selected ions are activated in which of the following ways that cause them to fall apart to produce product ions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collisional activation",
            "b) Evaporational activation",
            "c) Inert gas activation",
            "d) Thermal activation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: First mass spectrometer is used to separate a single mass that is characteristic of a given analyte in a mixture. The single mass is known as the precursor."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "In reverse-geometry mass spectrometer which of the following precedes the electric sector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nebulizer",
            "b) Orifice",
            "c) Magnetic sector",
            "d) Mass spectrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mass-selected ions are activated by some means that cause them to fall apart to produce product ions. They are activated by collisional activation."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "A magnetic sector alone can be used as a mass spectrometer, with roughly _____ resolution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) High",
            "c) Unit",
            "d) Infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The final MS/MS spectrum consists only of product ions from the selected precursor. The chemical background and other mixture components are absent."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What does the acronym ‘MIKES’ stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass-analysed ion kinetic energy spectrometer",
            "b) Mass-based induced kinetic energy spectrometer",
            "c) Mass invasive kinetic electric spectrometer",
            "d) Mass-analyser in a kinetic energy-type spectrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In reverse-geometry mass spectrometer magnetic sector precedes the electric sector. Early work on MS/MS was done with reverse-geometry double focussing mass spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "In MIKES experiments which of the following are measured?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Product ions",
            "b) Product ion kinetic energies",
            "c) Product ions mass to charge ratio",
            "d) Product ions masses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A magnetic sector alone can be used as a mass spectrometer, with roughly unit resolution. Early work on MS/MS was done with reverse-geometry double focussing mass spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "All ions with the same number of charges will have __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same kinetic energy",
            "b) Different kinetic energies",
            "c) Same mass",
            "d) Different mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ‘MIKES’ stands for mass-analysed ion kinetic energy spectrometer. It is related to spectrometers having magnetic field sectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "A tandem mass spectrometer has which of the following analysers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time of flight mass analyser",
            "b) Magnetic deflection analyser",
            "c) Radiofrequency analyser",
            "d) Quadrupole analyser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In MIKES experiments, mass to charge ratios are not measured. Product ion kinetic energies are measured in these experiments."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of the following filters are used in tandem spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quadrupole mass filter",
            "b) Low energy filter",
            "c) High energy filter",
            "d) Time of flight mass filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All ions with the same number of charges will have the same kinetic energy. It is assumed that all ions have a single charge."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "B/E scan is which of the following scans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Product ion scan",
            "b) Precursor ion scan",
            "c) Mass scan",
            "d) Charge scan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A tandem mass spectrometer has a filter. The filter is followed by a time of flight mass analyser."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Which of the following is located in the region between two analysers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nebuliser",
            "b) Collision cell",
            "c) Filter",
            "d) Vacuum chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A tandem mass spectrometer has a quadrupole mass filter. The filter is followed by an analyser."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Surface is usually more than _____ atomic layer deep and is a region of ________ atomic potentials.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One, uniform",
            "b) One, non-uniform",
            "c) Two, uniform",
            "d) Two, non-uniform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface is more than one atomic layer deep and is a region of non-uniform atomic potentials. The outermost layer of atoms is called a surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "In surface spectrometer, which of the following beam is analysed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reflected beam",
            "b) Absorbed beam",
            "c) Refracted beam",
            "d) Incident beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Surface analysis can provide information that classic methods like microscopic cannot. It is better than reflectivity, adsorption isotherms, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a type of electron spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MIKES",
            "b) Auger spectroscopy",
            "c) Secondary ion mass spectroscopy",
            "d) Ion scattering spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a beam is focussed on a surface, one beam enters the material and a second beam is reflected. The reflected beam is analysed."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger electron spectroscopy",
            "b) Electron impact spectroscopy",
            "c) Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis",
            "d) Secondary ion mass spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Auger spectroscopy is a type of electron spectroscopy. Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis is also a type of electron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods utilizes the emission of low energy electrons in a process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger electron spectroscopy",
            "b) Electron impact spectroscopy",
            "c) Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis",
            "d) Secondary ion mass spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Surface analysis can provide chemical information. Electron and ion spectroscopic techniques are types of surface analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the abbreviation of ESCA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron scattering chemical analysis",
            "b) Emission spectroscopy combination analysis",
            "c) Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis",
            "d) Electron spectrum chemically analysed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis is also known as X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy. It is an effective technique for detecting the elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods use soft X-rays to eject electrons from inner shell orbitals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auger electron spectroscopy",
            "b) Electron impact spectroscopy",
            "c) Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis",
            "d) Secondary ion mass spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Auger electron spectroscopy utilizes the emission of low energy electrons in auger process. It is one of the commonly employed techniques."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the abbreviation of SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary ion mass spectroscopy",
            "b) Spectrum ionization mass spectroscopy",
            "c) Scattering ions mass spectroscopy",
            "d) Spectral ionization mass spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The abbreviation of ESCA is Electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis. It is a type of electron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "The kinetic energy of the photoelectron energies is dependent on _________ of the atom, which makes XPS useful to identify the oxide state.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass",
            "b) Charge",
            "c) Chemical environment",
            "d) Volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The kinetic energy of the photoelectron energies is dependent on the chemical environment of the atom, which makes XPS useful to identify the oxide state. It also helps to identify the ligands of the atom."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "The kinetic energy of the ejected photoelectron is dependent upon the energy of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ions around",
            "b) Photons around",
            "c) Material",
            "d) Impinging photon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ion etching techniques provides the depth profiling from the surface. Binding energy can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "ESCA gives sufficient chemical information up to a depth about ________ armstrong in metals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-20",
            "b) 15-40",
            "c) 40-100",
            "d) 100-200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electron spectroscopy is based on the ionization phenomenon. It can be ionization of photon or electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "ESCA gives sufficient chemical information up to a depth about ________ armstrong in polymers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-20",
            "b) 15-40",
            "c) 40-100",
            "d) 100-200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The kinetic energy of the ejected photoelectron is dependent upon the energy of an impinging photon. A free electron is ejected."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "ESCA gives sufficient chemical information up to a depth about ________ armstrong in oxide.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-20",
            "b) 15-40",
            "c) 40-100",
            "d) 100-200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ESCA gives sufficient chemical information up to a depth about 5-20 armstrong in metals. ESCA is also known as X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "ESCA can identify elements in the periodic table above which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Boron",
            "c) Helium",
            "d) Potassium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ESCA gives sufficient chemical information up to a depth about 40-100 armstrong in polymers. ESCA is also known as X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Discrete electrons cannot be observed in electron ionization of an atom due to which of the following reasons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Environmental disturbances",
            "b) Same mass",
            "c) Same charge",
            "d) Electron- electron interaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ESCA gives sufficient chemical information up to a depth about 15-40 armstrong in oxide. ESCA is also known as X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "ESCA focusses on which of the following information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass of the electron",
            "b) Charge of the electron",
            "c) Binding energy of the electron",
            "d) Mass of atoms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ESCA can identify elements in the periodic table above helium. Adjacent elements are clearly distinguished."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "In the spectrum, two main peaks at _________ and ________ are observed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 284.6, 532.5",
            "b) 248.6, 523.5",
            "c) 264.8, 535.2",
            "d) 246.8, 553.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Discrete electrons cannot be observed in electron ionization of an atom because of electron-electron interaction. Therefore, ESCA cannot be observed when using electron ionization."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "284.6 eV matches which of the following specific atom type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Argon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ESCA focusses on binding energy of the electrons. It focusses on the binding energy which the electrons had before they left the atom."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "532.5 eV matches which of the following specific atom type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Argon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the spectrum, two main peaks at 284.6 and 532.5 are observed. The unit for counting energy is electron-volt."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "By studying which of the following can we determine if the surface corresponds to C-O or C=O chemical form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass of the electron",
            "b) Energy of the carbon peak",
            "c) Binding energy",
            "d) Charge of electron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each energy matches a specific atom type. 284.6 eV matches carbon."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the detection limit of ESCA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1% monolayer",
            "b) 0.5% monolayer",
            "c) 1% monolayer",
            "d) 2% monolayer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each energy matches a specific atom type. 532.5 eV matches carbon."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "The characterisation of auger spectroscopy can be achieved up to which of the following depths?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 nm",
            "b) 2 nm",
            "c) 4 nm",
            "d) 8 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The characterisation of auger spectroscopy can be achieved up to a depth of 1nm. Best instruments can characterise few nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Auger electron spectroscopy can be used for surface chemical analysis in a way similar to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ESCA",
            "b) SIMS",
            "c) ISS",
            "d) Ion spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Auger electron spectroscopy can be used for surface chemical analysis in a way similar to ESCA. ESCA is also known as X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Qualitative chemical analysis is very often performed using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ESCA",
            "b) SIMS",
            "c) AES",
            "d) Ion spectroscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AES is limited when it comes to very high resolution studies. It is very characteristic for various elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Electron ionization can produce which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ESCA electron",
            "b) Auger electron",
            "c) Ion",
            "d) Photon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Qualitative chemical analysis is very often performed using AES. Auger nomenclature follows the old x-ray notation."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an Auger transition starting from a hole in 1s levels which would be filled up from the 2p level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) KLM transition",
            "b) KLL transition",
            "c) LMN transition",
            "d) LLM transition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electron ionization can produce Auger electron. Photo-ionisation can also produce Auger electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "In ESCA process, the photon ejects which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1s electron",
            "b) 1p electron",
            "c) 2s electron",
            "d) 2p electron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electron ionisation cannot produce ESCA electrons. It can produce only Auger electrons."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "In Auger process, an electron drops to fill which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1s hole",
            "b) 1p hole",
            "c) 2s hole",
            "d) 2p hole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: KLL transition is an Auger transition starting from a hole in 1s levels which would be filled up from the 2p level. 2p electron would also be emitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Auger electron spectroscopy involves the irradiation of the surface to be analysed with a beam of electrons of energy in the _________ range.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2 KeV",
            "b) 2-4 KeV",
            "c) 4-8 KeV",
            "d) 1-8 KeV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ESCA process, the photon ejects 1s electron. For X-ray, an electron drops from the 2p orbit."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "In Auger spectroscopy, beam currents are typically _____ in a beam of diameter 0.5mm.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10 µA",
            "b) 5-20 µA",
            "c) 5-30 µA",
            "d) 5-50 µA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Auger process, an electron drops to fill 1s hole. It expels a 2p electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the detection limit of Auger Electron Spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1% monolayer",
            "b) 0.5% monolayer",
            "c) 1% monolayer",
            "d) 2% monolayer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Auger electron spectroscopy involves the irradiation of the surface to be analysed with a beam of electrons of energy in the 1-2 KeV range. Auger and X-ray emission are competitive processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Which of the following denotes the sample destruction that occurs in Auger electron spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) None in 95% of sample",
            "b) None in 99% of sample",
            "c) None in 100% of sample",
            "d) Frequent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Auger spectroscopy, beam currents are typically 5-50 µA in a beam of diameter 0.5mm. Auger and X-ray emission are competitive processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "How is the specificity of Auger electron spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very bad",
            "b) Bad",
            "c) Good",
            "d) Very good"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The detection limit of AES is 0.5% monolayer. It has 0.5µ x-y resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "AES is more sensitive than XPS because of which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binding energies of electrons",
            "b) Kinetic energies of electrons",
            "c) Mass of electrons",
            "d) Mass to charge ratio of electrons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Frequent sample destruction occurs in Auger electron spectroscopy. It is bad for organics."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "A basic X-ray source includes which of the following components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large target anode",
            "b) Large target cathode",
            "c) Small target anode",
            "d) Small target cathode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A basic X-ray source includes a large target anode. It also has a heating element."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "The anode is held at __________ positive potential and the filament is held at ____________ potential.",
        "Options": [
            "a) High, ground",
            "b) Ground, high",
            "c) Low, high",
            "d) High, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The anode is held at high potential and the filament is held at ground potential. Electrons are accelerated from the filament."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Which of the following is one of the most commonly used anode material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon",
            "b) Tungsten",
            "c) Magnesium",
            "d) Cesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnesium is one of the most commonly used anode material. Aluminium is also commonly used."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Which is the most intense line in the X-ray spectrum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kα1",
            "b) Kα2",
            "c) Kα12",
            "d) Kα22"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Kα12 is the most intense line in the X-ray spectrum. Different lines have specific energies."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "Which of the following must be used with the X-ray source to have high energy resolution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chopper",
            "b) Vacuum chamber",
            "c) Accelerator",
            "d) Monochromator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Monochromator must be used with the X-ray source to have high energy resolution. It will also remove the satellite lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "Double-pass cylindrical mirror energy analyser has how many mirrors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic deflection energy analysers are effective than electrostatic types. It is less convenient to design and use."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "In spherical sector analyser, __________ is detected and plotted as a function of energy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass",
            "b) Charge",
            "c) Number of electrons striking the detector",
            "d) Mass to charge ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Double-pass cylindrical mirror energy analyser has two mirrors. It is commonly used in electron spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most commonly used detector in ESCA and AES?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron multiplier",
            "b) Dynodes",
            "c) Photovoltaic cell",
            "d) Photomultiplier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In spherical sector analyser, the number of electrons striking the detector is detected and plotted as a function of energy. It is detected for a constant potential."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Electron detector has a _______ doped glass tube with a secondary semiconducting coating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quartz",
            "b) Silica",
            "c) Lead",
            "d) Cesium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electron multiplier is the most commonly used detectors in ESCA and AES. It is similar to photomultiplier."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "The output of the multiplier is fed to which of the following immediately?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse amplifier discriminator",
            "b) DAC",
            "c) ADC",
            "d) Multichannel analyser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electron detector has a lead doped glass tube with a secondary semiconducting coating. It has a high secondary electron shield."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ideal vacuum for electron spectrometers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-6 torr",
            "b) 10-7 torr",
            "c) 10-8 torr",
            "d) 10-9 torr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The output of the multiplier is fed to pulse amplifier discriminator. It is then fed to a multichannel analyser."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most commonly used magnetic shielding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helmholtz coils",
            "b) Ferro-magnetic shielding",
            "c) Faraday shield",
            "d) Magnetometer probe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 10-6 torr is the ideal vacuum for electron spectrometers. Vacuum below 10-6 torr can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Charging effect can be suppressed by supplying flood of electrons having which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform low energy",
            "b) Uniform low mass",
            "c) Uniform high energy",
            "d) Uniform high mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ferro-magnetic shielding is the most commonly used magnetic shielding. Helmholtz coil can be used as alternative."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "In Ion spectroscopy, the primary ion is usually which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inert gas ion",
            "b) Halogen ion",
            "c) Oxygen group gas ion",
            "d) Hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Ion spectroscopy, the primary ion is usually an inert gas ion. When primary ion having particular kinetic energy is incident on a surface certain phenomena can occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "The kinetic energy of the primary ion should be in which of the following range?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1-4 keV",
            "b) 0.2-1 keV",
            "c) 0.4-2 keV",
            "d) 0.3-5 keV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The kinetic energy of the primary ion should be 0.3-5 keV. These primary ions are made incident on the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "If the primary ion is elastically scattered, the kinetic energy of the reflected primary ion will depend on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Charge of the primary ion",
            "b) Charge of the surface ion",
            "c) Mass of the surface ion",
            "d) Number of surface ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the primary ion is elastically scattered, the kinetic energy of the reflected primary ion will depend on the mass of the surface ion. The reflected ion is measured by ISS."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes the phenomena of sputtering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary ion gets embedded in the solid",
            "b) Primary ion is elastically scattered",
            "c) Primary ion is reflected",
            "d) Primary ion is refracted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Primary ion may penetrate through a few layers of the surface and get embedded in the solid. This causes scattering."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the energy range of ISS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 keV",
            "b) 2 keV",
            "c) 4 keV",
            "d) 8 keV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The fragments formed during sputtering can be either neutral atoms or ions. The ions can be positive or negative."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the spectral range of SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-10 amu",
            "b) 0-100 amu",
            "c) 0-500 amu",
            "d) 0-1000 amu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The energy range of the ISS is 1 keV. ISS stands for ion scattering spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Which of the following is denotes the absolute quantitative analysis of SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30%",
            "b) 70%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) Not possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The spectral range of SIMS is 0-500 amu. SIMS stands for secondary ion mass spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the amount of matrix effect that occurs in SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Some",
            "d) Severe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both ISS and SIMS have depth profiling capability. ISS is slow in depth profiling but SIMS is rapid."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the x-y resolution of ISS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 µ",
            "b) 10 µ",
            "c) 100 µ",
            "d) 1000 µ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Absolute quantitative analysis is not possible in SIMS. It is possible in ISS."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the x-y resolution of SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 µ",
            "b) 10 µ",
            "c) 100 µ",
            "d) 1000 µ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Severe matrix effects occur in SIMS. Some matrix effects occur in ISS."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "In ion spectroscopy, the positive ions are focussed on the sample at which of the following angles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20o",
            "b) 30o",
            "c) 45o",
            "d) 90o"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ion spectroscopy, the positive ions are focussed on the sample at 45o. Ions are formed by bombardment."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Only those electrons which are in a selected small solid angle are received in the ________ electrostatic analyser.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100o",
            "b) 127o",
            "c) 180o",
            "d) 263o"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only those electrons which are in a selected small solid angle are received in the 127o electrostatic analyser. Ions are scattered in all directions."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used as the detector in ion spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup collector",
            "b) Channel electron multiplier",
            "c) Micro-channel plate",
            "d) Flame ionization detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Channel electron multiplier can be used as the detector in ion spectroscopy. Solid state detector can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "In order to obtain ISS spectra, the backscattered primary ions are sampled by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faraday cup analyser",
            "b) Photographic analyser",
            "c) Micro-channel analyser",
            "d) Cylindrical mirror analyser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to obtain ISS spectra, the backscattered primary ions are sampled by cylindrical mirror analyser. Their kinetic energies are then measured."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the energy after collision with a surface atom for a scattering angle of 90o when Eo is the energy of the incident ion, M1 is the mass of the incident ion and M2 is the mass of the target surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eo(M2-M1)/(M2+M1)",
            "b) Eo(M2+M1)/(M2-M1)",
            "c) Eo(M2×M1)/(M2+M1)",
            "d) Eo(M2-M1)/(M2×M1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eo(M2-M1)/(M2+M1) is the energy after collision with a surface atom for a scattering angle of 90o. But, this is valid only when M1<M2."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases is not often used in ion spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helium",
            "b) Argon",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Neon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is advantageous to use ions from a variety of gases. Few gases are chosen to avoid side effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "ISS is sensitive to every element heavier than which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helium",
            "b) Hydrogen",
            "c) Nitrogen",
            "d) Neon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Helium, argon and inert gases are usually chosen for ion spectroscopy. These gases are chosen to avoid side effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the lightest isotope used as a primary ion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) He",
            "b) 2He",
            "c) 3He",
            "d) 3H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ISS is sensitive to every element heavier than helium. The lightest isotope used as a primary ion is that of helium."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "ISS is less sensitive than which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SIMS",
            "b) Auger",
            "c) ESCA",
            "d) AES"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 3He is the lightest isotope used as a primary ion. Though hydrogen is lightest it is not used."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the detection limit of ISS for monolayer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 -1 %",
            "b) 10 -2 %",
            "c) 10 -3 %",
            "d) 10 -4 %"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The specificity will vary depending on the scattering gas used. Only a few gases are preferred to avoid side effects."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "After passing through the pre-filter, ions are passed through which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quadrupole mass spectrometer",
            "b) Time of flight mass spectrometer",
            "c) Radiofrequency mass spectrometer",
            "d) Magnetic deflection mass spectrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ISS is less sensitive than SIMS. It is more sensitive than Auger or ESCA."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the range of quadrupole mass spectrometer used in SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-200 amu",
            "b) 200-300 amu",
            "c) 500-1000 amu",
            "d) 200-500 amu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 10-3% of the monolayer is the detection limit of ISS. It can be effectively used for depth profiling."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the resolution of quadrupole mass spectrometer used in SIMS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 amu",
            "b) 2 amu",
            "c) 5 amu",
            "d) 3 amu"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: After passing through the pre-filter, ions are passed through quadrupole mass spectrometer. Pre-filter is a discriminator."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Electron spin resonance involves detecting the detection of a physical phenomenon of _________ of electromagnetic radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adsorption",
            "b) Absorption",
            "c) Radiation",
            "d) Reflection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electron spin resonance uses the detection of a physical phenomenon of absorption of electromagnetic radiation. Paramagnetic species absorb EM radiation."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Electron spin resonance is also known as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron paramagnetic resonance",
            "b) Electron diamagnetic resonance",
            "c) Electron paramagnetic reoccurrence",
            "d) Electron diamagnetic reoccurrence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electron spin resonance is also known as electron paramagnetic resonance. It is a valuable research analysis tool."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "The value of the magnetic moment is known as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thompson magneton",
            "b) Bohr magneton",
            "c) Goldstein magneton",
            "d) Rutherford magneton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electron spin resonance is based on the spin associated with the electron. There is a magnetic moment the value of which is known as Bohr magneton."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "When the electrons are aligned either parallel or antiparallel to the direction of the external magnetic field, the electrons will precess about the axis at a frequency that is proportional to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Applied magnetic field",
            "b) Electron magnetic moment",
            "c) Applied magnetic field and electron magnetic moment",
            "d) Neither applied magnetic field not electron magnetic moment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a strong magnetic field is applied to the unpaired spins of an electron, the electrons will be split into two groups. Electron spin resonance is based on the spin associated with the electron."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "If a weaker radiofrequency alternating magnetic field, having the frequency of precession of the electron is applied at right angles to fixed magnetic field, which of the following occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fragmentation",
            "b) Scattering",
            "c) Resonance",
            "d) Absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the electrons are aligned either parallel or antiparallel to the direction of external magnetic field, the electrons will start to precess about the axis at a frequency that is proportional to both applied magnetic field and electron magnetic moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "If the population of ground state exceeds the population of the excited state a net absorption of __________ radiation takes place.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrared",
            "b) Ultraviolet",
            "c) Microwave",
            "d) X-ray"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Resonance occurs when a weaker radiofrequency alternating magnetic field with the frequency of precession of the electron is applied at right angles to a fixed magnetic field."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "The population ratio can be given by which of the following laws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bohr law",
            "b) Beer-Lambert law",
            "c) Kelvin law",
            "d) Boltzmann law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the population of ground state exceeds the population of the excited state a net absorption of microwave radiation takes place. The signal would be proportional to the population difference."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "The sensitivity of measurement is greatly enhanced by using which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High magnetic field",
            "b) Low magnetic field",
            "c) High electric field",
            "d) Low electric field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The population ratio can be given by Boltzmann law. ‘k’ is the Boltzmann constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "ESR sensitivity increases with __________ temperature and with _________ magnetic field strength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing, increasing",
            "b) Increasing, decreasing",
            "c) Decreasing, increasing",
            "d) Decreasing, decreasing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sensitivity of measurement is greatly enhanced by using a high magnetic field. Low magnetic field reduces sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "Reflex klystron is used in which of the following frequency ranges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 to 2000 MHz",
            "b) 1000 to 10000 MHz",
            "c) 1000 to 15000 MHz",
            "d) 1000 to 20000 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ESR sensitivity increases with decreasing temperature and with increasing magnetic field strength. ESR sensitivity means net absorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Under ideal conditions, a commercial X-band spectrometer can detect of the order of which of the following number of spins at room temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 101",
            "b) 105",
            "c) 1010",
            "d) 1012"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ESR is remarkably sensitive when compared with NMR. NMR stands for Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "Waveguides look like _________ cross-section pipes with dimensions of the order of the wavelength to be transmitted.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triangular",
            "b) Circular",
            "c) Rectangular",
            "d) Square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reflex klystron is used in the frequency range of 1000 to 20000 MHz. It is a low power device."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Klystron can generate power in which of the following ranges?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 – 100 mW",
            "b) 10 – 200 mW",
            "c) 10 – 500 mW",
            "d) 100 – 400 mW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Under ideal conditions, a X-band spectrometer is capable of detecting of the order of 1012 spins at room temperature. ESR is very sensitive."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "Microwave frequency can be tuned over a small range by adjusting the distance between which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode and anode",
            "b) Anode and the reflector",
            "c) Cathode and the reflector",
            "d) Cathode and grid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The component is the reflector electrode. Cathode is on the left side and anode is in the middle."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Microwaves are generated by __________ and the power level is adjusted with the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triode, rectifier",
            "b) Pentode, attenuator",
            "c) Klystron tube, attenuator",
            "d) Diode, rectifier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Microwave frequency can be tuned over a small range by adjusting the distance between anode and the reflector. Reflector voltage can also be adjusted."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as reflex oscillator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triode",
            "b) Pentode",
            "c) Special tube",
            "d) Klystron tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Microwaves are generated by klystron tube and the power level is adjusted with the attenuator. Klystron tube is a low power device."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "Microwaves reflected back from the cavity are routed to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attenuator",
            "b) Klystron",
            "c) Load",
            "d) Diode detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Klystron tube is also known as the reflex oscillator. It is a low power device."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Which of the following routes are the microwaves entering from the klystron towards the cavity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oscillator",
            "b) Attenuator",
            "c) Circulator",
            "d) Reflector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Microwaves reflected back from the cavity are routed to diode detector. Power reflected from diode is absorbed by a load."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "By introducing which of the following, signal-to-noise ratio can be improved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small amplitude field modulation",
            "b) Large amplitude field modulation",
            "c) Small amplitude field attenuation",
            "d) Large amplitude field attenuation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Circulator routes the microwaves entering from the klystron towards the cavity. The sample is mounted in the cavity."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "Which of the following is adjusted as a fine control for frequency tuning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode",
            "b) Anode",
            "c) Reflector voltage",
            "d) Grid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By introducing small amplitude field modulation, signal-to-noise ratio can be improved. This is because the previous DC measurement is too noisy."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "The cavity resonant frequency should be equal to which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of electric field",
            "b) Klystron frequency",
            "c) Frequency of magnetic field",
            "d) Mechanical frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reflector voltage is adjusted as a fine control for frequency tuning. Distance is the coarse frequency adjustment."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "From which of the following are electrons emitted in the klystron tube?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cathode",
            "b) Anode",
            "c) Grid",
            "d) Reflector electrode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In basic ESR spectrometer, the cavity length is not adjustable. It is of one wavelength."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the operating frequency of the ESR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7 to 3.4 GHz",
            "b) 1.5 to 4.2 GHz",
            "c) 3.2 to 5.4 GHz",
            "d) 8.8 to 9.6 GHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cavity resonant frequency should be equal to klystron frequency. It must be tuned in this manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "At which of the following frequencies is the magnetic field at the sample modulated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 kHz",
            "b) 10 kHz",
            "c) 100 kHz",
            "d) 1000 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When klystron frequency is close to the cavity resonant frequency, much less power is reflected from the cavity to the diode. It results in a dip in a power mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "The output of the klystron does not pass through which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isolator",
            "b) Reflector",
            "c) Power leveller",
            "d) Directional coupler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The electrons are emitted by the cathode in the klystron tube. The cathode is heated."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as detector crystal in ESR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon rectifier",
            "b) Silicon tungsten rectifier",
            "c) Silicon boron rectifier",
            "d) Silicon quartz rectifier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Silicon tungsten rectifier is used as detector crystal in ESR spectrometer. This is the commonly used detector."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "After detection, the resulting signal will have which of the following frequencies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 kHz",
            "b) 10 kHz",
            "c) 100 kHz",
            "d) 1000 kHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After detection, the resulting signal will have 100 kHz. It contains ESR information."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the modulation amplitude range of ESR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1mG to 10G",
            "b) 2mG to 15G",
            "c) 3mG to 20G",
            "d) 5mG to 40G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 5mG to 40G is the modulation amplitude range of ESR spectrometer. It is applied in steps."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "In which of the following ranges will the receiver time constant of the ESR spectrometer lie?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 to 10 s",
            "b) 0.3 to 1 s",
            "c) 0.03 to 10 s",
            "d) 0.003 to 100 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The receiver time constant of the ESR spectrometer lies from 0.003 to 100 s. It is one of the important parameters of ESR spectrometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the oscilloscope field width of the ESR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2 to 40 G",
            "b) 0.1 to 20 G",
            "c) 0 to 10 G",
            "d) 0.01 to 20 G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The oscilloscope field width of the ESR spectrometer lies between 0.2 to 40 G. it is one of the important parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "The magnet used in ESR spectrometer provides a magnetic field which can be varied from ________ to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mgauss, 100mgauss",
            "b) 200 mgauss, 20kgauss",
            "c) 20 mgauss, 20kgauss",
            "d) 100 mgauss, 10kgauss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnet used in ESR spectrometer provides a magnetic field which can be varied from 200 mgauss to 20kgauss. It is calibrated in steps."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "Which of the following sensor is used in ESR spectrometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hall-effect sensor",
            "b) Load cell",
            "c) Strain gauge",
            "d) Bourdon gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hall-effect sensor is used in ESR spectrometer. It is given as an input to the summation circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "Which of the following oscillator is used as 1230 Hz oscillator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hartley oscillator",
            "b) Crystal oscillator",
            "c) RC oscillator",
            "d) Wien bridge oscillator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Wien bridge oscillator is used as 1230 Hz oscillator. The output level is internally regulated."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "What does AFC stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Auto frequency correct",
            "b) Automated frequency correct",
            "c) Automatic frequency control",
            "d) Automatic frequency circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: AFC stands for automatic frequency control. A 70 kHz AFC is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Klystron requires _______ for the klystron beam and up to _____ for the klystron reflector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) +400 V, -730 V",
            "b) +650 V, -400 V",
            "c) +200 V,-530 V",
            "d) +180 V,-270 V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Klystron requires +650 V for the klystron beam and up to -400 V for the klystron reflector. Klystron is also known as reflex oscillator."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "The 100 kHz oscillator acts as which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmitter",
            "b) Receiver",
            "c) Modulator",
            "d) Transmitter and receiver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The klystron body is insulated from ground by an insulating gas casket. It is placed between klystron flange and water cooling flange."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Which of the following removes residual harmonics from the phase-detected signal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High-pass filter",
            "b) Low-pass filter",
            "c) Band-pass filter",
            "d) Chopper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 100 kHz oscillator acts as the transmitter and receiver. It is crystal controlled."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "In the sample cell, which of the following is selected to give maximum optical transmission in the UV-visible region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tungsten",
            "b) Quartz",
            "c) Phosphor",
            "d) Potassium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Low-pass filter removes residual harmonics from the phase-detected signal. It removes the residual 100 kHz if any."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "Which of the following samples the analog signals to obtain their digital equivalent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analog to digital converter",
            "b) Electronic counter",
            "c) Comparator",
            "d) Digital to analog converter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In analytical instrumentation, most circuitry is concerned with the amplification and processing of signals. The signals are usually in analog form."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used to store information?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gates",
            "b) ADC",
            "c) DAC",
            "d) Flip-flops"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Analog to digital converter samples the analog signals to obtain their digital equivalent. There are different types of analog to digital converters."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as a nibble?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 bit",
            "b) 4 bits",
            "c) 8 bits",
            "d) 16 bits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flip-flops can be used to store information. They are used in sequential circuits."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the binary equivalent of the decimal number 10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1100",
            "b) 1010",
            "c) 1011",
            "d) 1110"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 4-bit units are known as nibbles. A byte consists of two nibbles."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "1001 is a data presented on a set of binary coded decimal output lines. What would be the decimal equivalent of this number in the case of negative logic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The binary equivalent of the decimal number 10 is 1010. The base of binary numbers is 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "Two switches are in parallel and are connected with a lamp and supply in series. This represents which of the following logic gate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AND gate",
            "b) OR gate",
            "c) EX-OR gate",
            "d) NOT gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The decimal equivalent of the number 1001 in the case of negative logic is 6. In the case of positive logic, the decimal equivalent will be 9."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "The output will be logic ‘1’ only if all the inputs are ‘0’. Which gate must be used to execute this condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AND gate",
            "b) NAND gate",
            "c) NOR gate",
            "d) EX-OR gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given circuit is the AND gate. The output of the gate is, Y=X1.X2"
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "INHIBIT gate is ________ gate with an inhibiting input.",
        "Options": [
            "a) AND gate",
            "b) OR gate",
            "c) EX-OR gate",
            "d) NOT gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two switches are in parallel and are connected with a lamp and supply in series. This forms the OR gate."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most widely employed logic family?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emitter-coupled logic",
            "b) Transistor-transistor logic",
            "c) CMOS logic family",
            "d) NMOS logic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transistor-transistor logic is the most widely employed logic family. It is the most popular logic family."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "The basic function of TTL gate is which of the following functions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AND",
            "b) OR",
            "c) NOR",
            "d) NAND"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The basic function of TTL gate is a NAND function. It is the most popular logic family."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "In TTL logic, the input transistor has a number of ________ equal to the desired fan-in of the circuit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base",
            "b) Collect",
            "c) Emitter",
            "d) Gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In TTL logic, the input transistor has a number of emitters equal to the desired fan-in of the circuit. This is a major advantage."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the propagation delay of TTL circuits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 s",
            "b) 1 ms",
            "c) 1 ns",
            "d) 1 ps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The propagation delay of the TTL circuit is 1 ns. It is the main characteristic of the TTL circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "The standard TTL gates are marketed as _______ series.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80",
            "b) 82",
            "c) 74",
            "d) 08"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The standard TTL gates are marketed as 74 series. They can operate up to 700C."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "Schottky TTL logic family does not have which of the following features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good fan-in",
            "b) Good fan-out",
            "c) High speed capability",
            "d) High propagation delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Schottky TTL circuits have reduced propagation delay than normal TTL circuits. The propagation delay of 10ns is very high for some applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "The logic ‘0’ of ECL is represented as ______V and logic ‘1’ is represented as ______V.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1, 1.65",
            "b) 0.9, 1.75",
            "c) 1.2, 2.35",
            "d) 1.9, 4.3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The logic ‘0’ of ECL is represented as 0.9 V and logic ‘1’ is represented as 1.75 V. ECL stands for emitter-coupled logic."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the advantage of MOS gates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low power dissipation",
            "b) Small size",
            "c) Good immunity to noise",
            "d) High switching speeds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We can achieve a high speed of gate by sing ECL. ECL stands for emitter-coupled logic."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "CMOS gates are commercially available as which of the following series?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000",
            "b) 2000",
            "c) 3000",
            "d) 4000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: MOS gates do not have a high switching speed. They have limited switching capability."
    }
]